hear that that's nothing which is what I
as a speaker at today's conference have
for you all I have nothing not a zip zilch
Zippo nothing smart nothing inspirational
nothing even remotely researched at all I
have absolutely nothing to say whatsoever
and yet through my manner of speaking I
will make it seem like I do like what I am
saying is brilliant and maybe just maybe
you will feel like you've learned
something now I'm going to get started with
the opening I'm going to make a lot of hand
gestures I'm going to do this with my right
hand I'm going to do this with my left I'm
going to adjust my glasses and then I'm gonna
ask you all a question by show of hands
how many of you all have been asked a
question before okay great I'm seeing some
hands and again I have nothing here
and act like I'm telling you a personal
anecdote.
Something to break the tension,
something to endear myself a little bit,
something kind of embarrassing.
Ha ha ha.
And you guys are going to make an aww
sound.
It's true. It really happened.
And now I'm going to bring it to a broader
point.
I'm going to really back in.
I'm going to make it intellectual.
I'm going to bring it to this man right
here.
Now, what this man did was important, I'm
sure.
Ha ha ha. But I, for one, have no idea who
he is.
I simply Google images the word, scientist.
Ha ha ha. And now you see, I'd like it to
seem like I'm making points,
building an argument,
inspiring you to change your life, when in
reality this is just me buying time.
believe me let's take a look at the
numbers this is a real thing that's
happening right now the number of talks
that I'm giving is one interesting facts
imparted thus far in said talk well that's
going to be a zero my height in inches is 70
.5 note the point five there two times six
equals 12 and then interestingly enough
six times two also equals 12 that's math
352 is a three-digit number one two three
four five
Now,
to add more filler here, I'm going to give
you a couple more numbers to consider.
18, 237,
5, 601,
2 .6 million,
4,
24,
staggering.
These are real numbers, all of them.
And to follow that up, let's take a look
at some graphs. Now, if you take a look at
this pie chart, what you're going to see
is that the majority far exceeds the
minority.
Everybody see that?
Cool, isn't it?
And let's take a look at this bar graph,
because it shows similarly irrelevant
data.
Now, I'm doing this because I'd like to
make it seem like I've done my homework.
If you were, say, watching this on YouTube
with the sound off, you might think, huh,
okay, this guy knows what he's talking
about,
but I don't. I'm flying.
I've got nothing. I'm a total and utter
phony, but you know what?
I was offered a TED talk and
Damn it. I'm going to see it through
Now if you take a look behind me, these
are just words paired with vaguely thought
-provoking stock photos
I'm gonna point at them like I'm making
use both of my time and your time
I don't know what half of them mean.
I'm just gonna start saying gibberish.
Gabba,
turkey,
mouth in a mouth,
chip,
trip, my dog skip,
rip it and dip it, Richard.
I'm an Kitty bitty baby bopper, and I'm
hungry in my tum.
Brad Pitt,
Uma Thurman,
names, things,
words, words, and more things. And see, it
feels like it might make sense, doesn't
it?
Like maybe, just maybe, I'm building to
some sort of satisfying conclusion. I
mean, I'm gesticulating as though I am.
I'm pacing, I'm growing in intensity. I'm
taking off my glasses, which, by the way,
are just frames.
I wore them to look smart, even though my
vision is perfect.
And now I'm going to slow things down a
little bit.
I'm going to change the tone.
I'm going to make it seem like I'm
building to a moment.
And what if I was?
Amazing, isn't it? What can you do?
Life's a roller coaster.
You know, if there's one thing you take
away from my talk, I'd like you to think
about what you heard at the beginning.
And I'd like you to think about what you
hear now.
Because it was nothing,
and it's still nothing. Think about that.
Or don't. That's fine.
And now I'm going to stop talking.
Thank you.