So, I want to start by offering you a free
no -tech life hack.
And all it requires of you is this, that
you change your posture for two minutes.
But before I give it away, I want to ask
you to right now do a little audit of your
body and what you're doing with your body.
So, how many of you are sort of making
yourself smaller? Maybe you're hunching,
crossing your legs, maybe wrapping your
ankles. Sometimes we hold on to our arms
like this,
sometimes we spread out.
I see you.
So, I want you to pay attention to what
you're doing right now. We're going to
come back to that in a few minutes. And
I'm hoping that if you sort of learn to
tweak this a little bit, it could
significantly change the way your life
unfolds.
So, we're really fascinated with body
language.
And we're particularly interested in other
people's body language.
You know, we're interested in, like,
you know,
an awkward interaction or a smile or a
contemptuous glance or maybe a very
awkward wink or maybe even something like
a handshake.
Here they are arriving at number 10 and
look at this lucky policeman gets to shake
hands with the president of the United
States.
Oh, and here comes the prime minister of
the,
no.
So, um, I hand
of a handshake can have us talking for
weeks and weeks and weeks, even the BBC
and the New York Times.
So obviously when we think about nonverbal
behavior or body language, but we call it
Nonverbal as social scientists,
it's language. So we think about
communication.
When we think about communication, we
think about interactions.
So what is your body language
communicating to me? What's mine
communicating to you? And there's a lot of
reason to believe that this is a valid way
to look at this. So social scientists have
spent a lot of time looking at the effects
of our body language or other people's
body language on judgments.
And we make sweeping judgments and
inferences from body language.
And those judgments can predict really
meaningful life outcomes like who we hire
or promote,
who we ask out on a date. For example,
at Tufts University shows that when people
watch 30 -second soundless clips of real
physician -patient interactions,
their judgments of the physician's
niceness predict whether that
physician will be sued.
So it doesn't have to do so much with
whether or not that physician was
incompetent, but do we like that person
and how they interacted?
Even more dramatic,
Alex Topologic Princeton has shown us that
judgments of political candidates faces
in just one second predicts 70 % of US
Senate and gubernatorial race outcomes.
And even, let's go digital,
emoticons used well in online negotiations
can lead you to claim more value from that
negotiation if you use them poorly.
Bad idea,
right?
So when we think of not -
we judge others, how they judge us, and
what the outcomes are. We tend to forget
though the other audience that's
influenced by our nonverbal, and that's
ourselves.
We are also influenced by our nonverbal,
our thoughts, and our feelings, and our
physiology.
So what nonverbal am I talking about? I'm
a social psychologist,
I study prejudice,
and I teach at a competitive business
school. So it was inevitable that I would
become interested in power dynamics.
I became especially interested in
nonverbal expressions of power and
dominance.
And what are nonverbal expressions of
power and dominance? Well,
this is what they are. So in the animal
kingdom, they are about expanding. So you
make yourself big,
you stretch out, you take up space, you're
basically opening up. It's about opening
up.
And this is true across the animal
kingdom. It's not just limited to
primates, and humans do the same thing.
So they do this both when they have power
sort of chronically, and also when they're
feeling powerful at the moment.
And this one is especially interesting,
because it really shows us how universal
and old these expressions of power are.
This expression, which is known as pride,
Jessica Tracy has studied,
she shows that people who are born with
sight and people who are congenitally
blind do this when they win at a physical
competition. So when they cross the finish
line and they've won, it doesn't matter if
they've never seen anyone do it, they do
this.
So the arms up in the V,
the chin is slightly lifted.
What do we do when we feel powerless? We
do exactly the opposite.
We close up, we wrap ourselves up, we make
ourselves small. We don't want to bump
into the person next to us. So again, both
animals and humans do the same thing.
And this is what happens when you put
together.
comes to power is that we complement the
other's nonverbal.
So if someone's being really powerful with
us, we tend to make ourselves smaller. We
don't mirror them, we do the opposite of
them.
So I'm watching this behavior in the
classroom,
and what do I notice? I notice that MBA
students really exhibit the full range of
power nonverbal. So you have people who
are like caricatures of alphas, like
really coming to the room, they get right
into the middle of the room
before class even starts, like they really
want to occupy space.
When they sit down, they're sort of spread
out, they raise their hands like this.
You have other people who are virtually
collapsing when they come in, as soon as
they come in, you see it. You see it on
their faces and their bodies, and they sit
in their chair and they make themselves
tiny, and they go like this when they
raise their hand.
I noticed a couple of things about this.
One, you're not going to be surprised,
it seems to be related to gender.
So, women are much more likely to do this
kind of thing than men.
Women feel chronically less powerful than
men, so this is not surprising.
But the other thing I noticed is that it
also seemed to be related to the extent to
which the students were participating and
how well they were participating, and this
is really important in the MBA classroom
because participation counts for half the
grade.
So,
business schools have been struggling with
this gender grade gap.
You get these equally qualified women and
men coming in,
and then you get these differences in
grades, and it seems to be partly
attributable to participation.
So, I started to wonder,
okay,
so you have these people coming in like
this and they're participating,
is it possible that we could get people to
fake it and would it lead them to
participate more? So,
my main collaborator, Dana Carney,
who's at Berkeley,
and I really wanted to know, can you fake
it till you make it? Like, can you do this
just for a little while
and actually experience a behavioral
outcome that makes you seem more powerful?
So, we know that our nonverbal
govern how other people think and feel
about us. There's a lot of evidence, but
our question really was,
do our nonverbal govern how we think and
feel about ourselves?
There's some evidence that they do. So,
for example,
we smile when we feel happy, but also when
we're forced to smile by holding a pen in
our teeth like this,
it makes us feel happy.
So, it goes both ways.
When it comes to power,
it also goes both ways.
So, when you feel...
to do this, but it's also possible that
when you pretend to be powerful,
you are more likely to actually feel
powerful.
So the second question really was,
you know,
so we know that our minds change our
bodies, but is it also true that our
bodies change our minds?
And when I say minds, in the case of the
powerful, what am I talking about?
So I'm talking about thoughts and feelings
and the sort of physiological things that
make up our thoughts and feelings, and in
my case, that's hormones.
I look at hormones.
So what do the minds of the powerful
versus the powerless look like?
So powerful people tend to be not
surprisingly more assertive and more
confident,
more optimistic.
They actually feel that they're going to
win even at games of chance.
They also tend to be able to think more
abstractly. So there are a lot of
differences.
They take more risks. There are a lot of
differences between powerful and powerless
people.
Physiologically,
there are also differences on two key
hormones,
testosterone, which is the dominant
hormone,
and cortisol, which is the stress hormone.
So what we find is that high -power alpha
males and primate hierarchies have high
testosterone and low cortisol,
and powerful and effective leaders also
have high testosterone and low cortisol.
So what does that mean?
When do you think about power, people
tended to think only about testosterone
because that was about dominance,
but really power is also about how you
react to stress.
So do you want the high -power leader
that's dominant, high on testosterone, but
really stress reactive?
Probably not, right? You want the person
who's powerful and assertive and dominant,
but not very stress reactive, the person
who's laid back.
So we know that in primate hierarchies,
if an alpha needs to take over,
if an individual needs to take over an
alpha role sort of suddenly,
within a few days, that individual's
testosterone has gone up significantly,
and his cortisol has dropped
significantly.
So we have this evidence, both that the
body can shape the mind at least at the
facial level,
and also that role changes can shape the
mind. So what happens, okay, you take a
role change.
What happens if you do that at a really
minimal level, like this tiny
manipulation, this tiny intervention, for
two minutes you say, I want you to stand
like this, and it's going to make you feel
more powerful.
So this is what we did.
We decided to take a role change, and we
decided to take a role change, and we
decided to take
and run a little experiment,
and these people adopted for two
minutes...
high power poses or low power poses. And
I'm just going to show you five of the poses,
although they took on only two.
So here's one,
a couple more.
This one has been dubbed the Wonder Woman
by the media.
Here are a couple more.
So you can be standing or you can be
sitting.
And here are the low power poses. So
you're folding up, you're making yourself
small.
This one is very low power. When you're
touching your neck, you're really kind of
protecting yourself.
So this is what happens.
They come in, they spit into a vial.
We, for two minutes, say, you need to do
this or this.
They don't look at pictures of the poses.
We don't want to prime them with a concept
of power. We want them to be feeling
power, right? So two minutes they do this.
We then ask them how powerful do you feel
on a series of items? And then we give
them an opportunity to gamble.
And then we take another saliva sample.
That's it, that's the whole experiment.
So this is what we find. Risk tolerance,
which is the gambling.
What we find is that when you're in the
high power pose condition, 86 % of you
will gamble.
When you're in the low power pose
condition, only 60%. And that's a pretty
whopping significant difference.
Here's what we find on testosterone.
High -power people experience about a 20 %
increase,
and low -power people experience about a
10 % decrease.
So again, two minutes, and you get these
changes.
Here's what you get on cortisol.
High -power people experience about a 25 %
decrease.
increase,
and the low power people experience about
a 15 % increase.
So two minutes lead to these hormonal
changes that configure your brain to
basically be either assertive, confident,
and comfortable,
or really stress reactive,
and feeling sort of shut down. And we've
all had that feeling, right?
So it seems that our nonverbal do govern
how we think and feel about ourselves. So
it's not just others, but it's also
ourselves.
Also, our bodies change our minds.
But the next question, of course, is can
power posing for a few minutes really
change your life in meaningful ways? So
this is in the lab. It's this little task.
It's just a couple of minutes.
Where can you actually apply this, which
we cared about, of course?
And so we think it's really what matters,
and where you want to use this, is
evaluative situations like social threat
situations.
Where are you being evaluated, either by
your friends, like for teenagers at the
lunchroom table?
It could be, you know, for some people,
it's speaking at a school board meeting.
It might be giving a pitch, or giving a
talk like this, or doing a job interview.
We decided that the one that most people
could relate to, because most people had
been through, was the job interview.
So we published these findings, and the
media are all over it, and they say,
okay, so this is what you do when you go
in for the job interview, right?
So we were, of course, horrified, and
said, oh, my God, no, no, no, that's not
what we meant at all for numerous reasons,
no, no, no, don't do that. Again, this is
not about you talking to other people,
it's you talking to yourself. What do you
do before you go into a job interview? You
do this,
right? You're sitting down, you're looking
at your iPhone, or your Android, not
trying to leave anyone out.
You are,
you're looking at your notes, you're
hunching up, making yourself small, and
really what you should be doing, maybe, is
this, like in the bathroom,
right?
Do that, find two minutes. So that's what
we want to test, okay? So we bring people
into a lab,
and they do either hire low -power posters
again,
they go through a very stressful job
interview. It's five minutes long,
they are being recorded, they're being
judged also,
and the judges
are trained to give no nonverbal feedback.
So they look like this, like imagine this
is the person interviewing you.
So for five minutes, nothing.
And this is worse than being heckled.
People hate this. It's what Mary Ann
LaFrance calls standing in social
quicksand. So this really spikes your
cortisol.
So this is the job interview we put them
through, because we really wanted to see
what happened.
We then have these coders, look at these
tapes, four of them. They're blind to the
hypothesis,
they're blind to the conditions, they have
no idea who's been posing in what pose.
And they end up looking at these sets of
tapes and they say, oh, we want to hire
these people, all the high -power posters,
we don't want to hire these people.
We also evaluate these people much more
positively overall.
But what's driving it?
It's not about the content of the speech,
it's about the presence that they're
bringing to the speech. We also, because
we rate them on all these variables
related to sort of competence, like how
well-structured is the speech,
how good is it, what are their
qualifications,
no effect on those things. This is what's
affected,
these kinds of things.
People are bringing their true selves
basically, they're bringing themselves,
they bring their ideas but as themselves
with no residue over them.
So this is what's driving the effect or
mediating the effect.
So when I tell people about this,
that our bodies change our minds and our
minds can change our behavior and our
behavior can change our outcomes, they say
to me,
I don't, it feels fake, right? So I said,
fake it till you make it, like I don't,
it's not me,
like I don't want to get there and then
still feel like a fraud, I don't want to
feel like an imposter, I don't want to get
there only to feel like I'm not supposed
to be here.
And that really resonated with me because
I want to tell you a little story about
being an imposter and feeling like I'm not
supposed to be here.
When I was 19, I was in a terrible car
accident, I was thrown out of a car,
rolled several times I was thrown from the
car and I woke up in a head injury rehab
ward and I had been withdrawn from college
and I learned that my IQ had dropped by
two standard deviations
which was very traumatic,
I knew my IQ because I had identified with
being smart and I had been called gifted
as a child.
So I'm taken out of college, I keep trying
to go back, they say you're not going to
finish college, like just, you know,
there are other things for you to do but
that's not going to work out for you.
So I really struggled with this and I have
to say having your identity taken from
you, your core identity and for me, it was
being smart,
having that taken from you, there's
nothing that leaves you feeling more
powerless than that.
So I felt entirely powerless, I worked and
worked and worked and I got lucky and
worked and got lucky and worked.
Eventually I graduated from college,
took me four years longer than my peers
and I convinced someone, my angel advisor,
Susan Fisk, to take me on, and so I ended
up at Princeton, and I was like, I am not
supposed to be here, I am an imposter.
And the night before my first year
talking, the first year talk at Princeton
is a 20-minute talk to 20 people, that's
it.
I was so afraid of being found out the
next day that I called her and said, I'm
quitting.
She was like, you are not quitting because
I took a gamble on you, and you're staying,
you're going to stay and this is what
you're going to do,
you're going to fake it,
you're going to take, you're going to do
every talk that you ever get asked to do,
you're just going to do it and do it and
do it even if you're terrified and just
paralyzed and having an out of body
experience until you have this moment
where you say,
oh my God.
I have become this, I am actually doing
this. So that's what I did, five years in
grad school.
A few years, I'm at Northwestern, I moved
to Harvard.
I'm at Harvard, I'm not really thinking
about it anymore,
but for a long time I had been thinking,
not supposed to be here, not supposed to
be here.
So the end of my first year at Harvard,
a student who had not
the entire semester who I had said, look,
you have to participate or else you're gonna
fail,
came into my office, I really didn't know
her at all.
And she said,
she came in totally defeated and she said,
I'm not supposed to be here.
And that was the moment for me because two
things happened. One was that I realized,
oh my gosh, I don't feel like that
anymore, you know?
I don't feel that anymore, but she does
and I get that feeling. And the second was
she is supposed to be here.
Like she can fake it, she can become it.
So I was like, yes you are. You are
supposed to be here and tomorrow you're
going to fake it, you're going to make yourself
powerful and, you know.
go to the classroom and you are going to
give the best comment ever,
you know, and she gave the best comment
ever. And people turned around and they
were like, oh my God, I didn't even notice
her sitting there, you know.
She comes back to me months later and I
realized that she had not just faked it
till she made it, she had actually faked
it till she became it. So she had changed.
And so I want to say to you, don't fake it
till you make it, fake it till you become
it.
You know, it's not done it enough until you
actually become it and internalize. The
last thing I'm going to leave you with is
this,
tiny tweaks can lead to big changes.
So this is two minutes,
two minutes, two minutes, two minutes.
Before you go into the next stressful,
evaluative situation for two minutes, try
doing this in the elevator in a bathroom
stall at your desk behind closed doors.
That's what you want to do. Get, configure
your brain to cope the best in that
situation. Get your testosterone up, get
your cortisol down.
Don't leave that situation feeling like,
oh, I didn't show them who I am.
Leave that situation feeling like, oh, I
really feel like I got to say who I am and
show who I am.
So I want to ask you first,
you know,
both to try power posing and also I want
to
the science because this is simple.
I don't have ego involved in this.
Give it away. Like share it with people
because the people who can use it the most
are the ones with no resources and no
technology and no status and no power.
Give it to them because they can do it in
private. They need their bodies, privacy
and two minutes and it can significantly
change the outcomes of their life.
Thank you.
You