So in college,
I was a government major, which means I
had to write a lot of papers.
Now when a normal student writes a paper,
they might spread the work-out a little
like this.
So, you know,
you get started maybe a little slowly, but
you get enough done in the first week that
with some heavier days later on,
everything gets done and things stay
civil.
And I would want to do that like that.
That would be the plan.
I would have it all ready to go, but then
actually the paper would come along and
then I would kind of do this.
And that would happen in every single
paper.
But then came my 90 -page senior thesis,
a paper you're supposed to spend a year
on.
I knew for a paper like that, my normal
workflow was not an option, it was way too
big a project. So I planned things out and
I decided I kind of had to go something
like this.
This is how the year would go. So I'd
start off light and I'd bump it up in the
middle months and then at the end, I would
kick it up into high gear, just like a
little staircase.
How hard could it be to just walk up the
stairs?
No big deal, right?
But then, the funniest thing happened, those
first few months,
they came and went and I couldn't quite do
stuff.
So we had an awesome new revised plan.
And then those middle months actually went
by and I didn't really write words and so
we were here.
And then two months turned into one month,
turned into two weeks.
And one day I woke up with three days
until the deadline,
still not having written a word
and so I did the only thing I could.
I wrote 90 pages over 72 hours, pulling
not one but two all-nighters, humans are
not supposed to pull two all-nighters,
sprinted across campus,
dove in slow motion and got it in just at
the deadline.
I thought that was the end of everything.
But a week later, I get a call.
It's a school.
And they say, is this Tim Urban? And I
say, yeah.
And they say, we need to talk about your
thesis.
And I say, OK.
And they say,
that's the best one we've ever seen.
That did not.
It was a very, very bad thesis.
I just wanted to enjoy that one moment
when all of you thought, this guy is
amazing.
No, no, it was very, very bad.
Anyway,
today I'm a writer,
blogger, guy.
I write the blog, Wait But Why.
And a couple of years ago, I decided to
write about procrastination.
My behavior has always perplexed the non
-procrastinators around me, and I wanted
to explain to the non -procrastinators of
the world what goes on in the heads of
procrastinators and why we are the way we
are. Now, I had a hypothesis that the
brains of procrastinators were actually
different from the brains of other people.
And to test this, I found an MRI lab that
actually let me scan both my brain and the
brain of a proven non -procrastinator.
And so I could compare them, and I
actually brought them here to show you
today, and I want you to take a look
carefully to see if you can notice a
difference. And I know that if you're not
a trained brain expert, it's not that
obvious, but just take a look, okay?
So here's the brain of a non
-procrastinator.
Now, here's my brain.
There is a difference.
Both brains have a rational decision
-maker in them, but the procrastinator's
brain also has an instant gratification
monkey. Now, what does this mean for the
procrastinator? Well,
it means everything's fine until this
happens.
So the rational decision -maker will make
the rational decision to do something
productive, but the monkey doesn't like
that plan.
So he actually takes the wheel and he
says, actually, let's read the entire
Wikipedia page of the Nancy Kerri and
Tanya Harding scandal because I just
remember that that happened.
Then...
Then we're going to go over to the fridge.
We're going to see if there's anything new
in there since 10 minutes ago.
After that, we're going to go on a YouTube
spiral that starts with videos of Richard
Feynman talking about magnets and ends
much, much later with us watching
interviews with Justin Bieber's mom.
All of that's going to take a while, so
we're not going to really have room on the
schedule for any work today, sorry.
Now, what is going on here?
The instant gratification monkey does not
seem like a guy you want behind the wheel.
He lives entirely in the present moment.
He has no memory of the past, no knowledge
of the future, and he only cares about two
things,
easy and fun.
Now, in the animal world,
that works fine.
If you're a dog and you spend your whole
life doing nothing other than easy and fun
things, you're a huge success.
And to the monkey,
humans are just another animal. An animal
species has to keep well slept, well-fed,
and propagating into the next generation,
which in tribal times might have worked
okay. But if you haven't noticed, now
we're not in tribal times, we're in an
advanced civilization and the monkey does
not know what that is, which is why we
have another guy in our brain,
the rational decision maker,
who gives us the ability to do things no
other animal can do. We can visualize the
future, we can see the big picture,
we can make long -term plans, and he wants
to take all of that into account,
and he wants to just have us do whatever
makes sense to be doing right now.
Now, sometimes it makes sense to be doing
things that are easy and fun, like when
you're having dinner or going to bed or
enjoying well-earned leisure time, that's
why there's an overlap.
Sometimes they agree.
But other times, it makes much more sense
to be doing things that are harder and
less pleasant for the sake of the big
picture, and that's when we have a
conflict. And for the procrastinator, that
conflict tends to end a certain way every
time, leaving him spending a lot of time
in this orange zone,
an easy and fun place that's entirely out
of the makes -sense circle. I call it the
dark playground.
LAUGHTER
Now,
the dark playground is a place that all of
you procrastinators out their know very
well.
It's where leisure activities happen at
times when leisure activities are not
supposed to be happening. The fun you have
in the dark playground isn't actually fun
because it's completely unearned
and the air is filled with guilt, dread,
anxiety, self-hatred, all those good
procrastinator feelings.
And the question is, in this situation,
with the monkey behind the wheel, how does
the procrastinator ever gets himself over
here to this blue zone,
a less pleasant place, but where really
important things happen?
Well,
it turns out that the procrastinator has a
guardian angel, someone who's always
looking down on him and watching over him,
in his darkest moments, someone called the
Panic Monster.
LAUGHTER
Now,
the Panic Monster is dormant most of the
time, but he suddenly wakes up.
Any time a deadline gets too close or
there's danger of public embarrassment, a
career disaster or some other scary
consequence. And importantly, he's the
only thing that the monkey is terrified
of. Now, he became very relevant in my
life pretty recently
because people of TED reached out to me
about six months ago and invited me to do
a TED talk.
LAUGHTER
Now, of course,
I said, yes, it's always been a dream of
mine to have done a TED talk in the past.
LAUGHTER
But in the middle of all this excitement,
the rational decision -makers seemed to
have something else in his mind. He was
saying,
are we clear on what we just accepted?
Do we get what's going to be now happening
one day in the future? We need to sit down
and work on this right now. And the monkey
said, totally agree, but also let's just
open Google Earth and let's zoom into the
bottom of India, like 200 feet above the
ground, and we're going to scroll up two
and a half hours until we get to the top
of the country so we can get a better feel
for India.
So that's what we did that day.
As six months turned into four, and then
two, and then one, the people of TED
decided to release the speakers. And I
opened up the website, and there was my
face staring right back at me, and guess
who woke up?
So the panic monster starts losing his
mind, and a few seconds later, the whole
system's in mayhem.
And the monkey, who remember, he's
terrified of the panic monster. Boom, he's
up the tree.
And finally,
finally,
the rational decision -maker can take the
wheel, and I can start working on the
talk. Now,
the panic monster explains all kinds of
pretty insane procrastinator behavior,
like how someone like me could spend two
weeks unable to start the opening sentence
of a paper and then miraculously find the
unbelievable work ethic to stay up all
night and write eight pages.
And this entire situation with the three
characters, this is the procrastinator's
system.
And it works.
And this is what I decided to write about
on the blog just a couple of years ago.
Now, when I did,
I was amazed by the response.
Literally thousands of emails came in from
all different kinds of people, from all
over the world, doing all different kinds
of things.
These were people who were nurses and
bankers and painters and engineers and
lots and lots of PhD students.
And they were all writing, saying the same
thing. I have this problem, too.
But what struck me was the contrast
between the light tone of the post
and the heaviness of these emails.
These people were writing with intense
frustration about what procrastination had
done to their lives, about what this
monkey had done to them.
And I thought about this, and I said, if
the procrastinator system works, then
what's going on? Why are all these people
in such a dark place? Well,
it turns out that there are two kinds of
procrastination.
Everything I've talked about today, the
examples I've given, they all have
deadlines. And when there's deadlines,
the effects of procrastination are
contained.
To the short term, because the panic
monster gets involved, but there's a
second kind of procrastination that
happens in situations when there is no
deadline.
So if you want to have a career where you
want to be a self-starter, something in
the arts, something entrepreneurial,
there's no deadlines on those things at
first, because nothing's happening at
first, not until you've gone out and done
the hard work to get some momentum to get
things going. There's also all kinds of
important things outside your career
that don't involve any deadlines, like
seeing your family or exercising and
taking care of your health,
working on your relationship or getting
out of a relationship that isn't working.
Now, if the procrastinator's only
mechanism
of doing these hard things is the panic
monster, that's a problem, because in all
of these non -deadline situations,
the panic monster doesn't show up, he has
nothing to wake up for, so the effects of
procrastination, they're not contained,
they just extend outward forever.
And it's this long -term kind of
procrastination
that's much less visible and much less
talked about than the funnier short -term
deadline -based kind. It's usually
suffered quietly and privately,
and it can be the source of a huge amount
of long -term unhappiness and regrets.
And I thought, you know, that's why these
people are emailing,
and that's why they're in such a bad
place.
It's not that they're cramming for some
project, it's that long -term
procrastination has made them feel like a
spectator at times in their own lives.
You know, the frustration was not that
they couldn't achieve their dreams, it's
that they weren't even able to start
chasing them.
So I read these emails, and I had a little
a bit of an epiphany,
that I don't think non -procrastinators
exist.
That's right,
I think all of you are procrastinators.
Now, you might not all be a mess,
like some of us,
and some of you may have a healthy
relationship with deadlines.
But remember, the monkey's sneakiest trick
is when the deadlines aren't there.
Now, I want to show you one last thing.
I call this a life calendar.
That's one box for every week.
Of a 90 -year life.
That's not that many boxes, especially
since we've already used a bunch of those.
So I think we need to all take a long,
hard look at that calendar.
And we need to think about what we're
really procrastinating on, because
everyone is procrastinating on something
in life.
We need to stay aware of the instant
gratification monkey.
That's a job for all of us.
And because there's not that many boxes on
there, it's a job that should probably
start today.
What?
Maybe not today,
but...
audience laughs
You know,
sometimes soon.
Thank you. Thank you.