Thank you for watching!
I grew up to study the brain because I
have a brother who has been diagnosed with
a brain disorder schizophrenia.
And as a sister and later as a scientist,
I wanted to understand why is it that I
can take my dreams,
I can connect them to my reality, and I
can make my dreams come true. What is it
about my brother's brain and his
schizophrenia that he cannot connect his
dreams to a common and shared reality so
they instead become delusion?
So I dedicated my career to research into
the severe mental illnesses and I moved
from my home state of Indiana to Boston
where I was working in the lab of Dr.
Francine Bene's
And in the lab, we were asking the
question,
what are the biological differences
between the brains of individuals who
would be diagnosed as normal control,
as compared with the brains of individuals
diagnosed with schizophrenia,
schizoaffective, or bipolar disorder?
So we were essentially mapping the
microcircuitry of the brain, which cells
are communicating with which cells, with
which chemicals,
and then in what quantities of those
chemicals.
So there was a lot of meaning in my life
because I was performing this type of
research during the day, but then in the
evenings and on the weekends, I traveled
as an advocate for NAME, the National
Alliance on Mental Illness.
But on the morning of December 10, 1996, I
woke up to discover that I had a brain
disorder of my own.
A blood vessel exploded in the left half
of my brain.
And in the course of four hours, I watched
my brain completely
deteriorate in its ability to process all
information.
On the morning of the hemorrhage, I could
not walk,
talk,
read,
write, or recall any of my life.
I essentially became an infant in a
woman's body.
If you've ever seen a human brain,
it's
Demo spheres are completely separate from
one another and I have brought for you a
real human brain
So this is a real human brain
This is the front of the brain the back of
the brain with a spinal cord hanging down
And this is how it would be positioned
inside of my head and
When you look at the brain, it's obvious
that the two cerebral courtesies are
completely separate from one another
For those of you who understand computers
our right hemisphere functions like a
parallel processor While our left
hemisphere functions like a serial
processor
The two hemispheres do communicate with
one another through the corpus callosum,
which is made up of some 300 million
axonal fibers, but other than that the two
hemispheres are completely separate
Because they process information
differently each of our hemisphere think
about different things They care about
different things and dare I say they have
very different personalities
Excuse me, thank you.
It's been a joy
Our right human hemisphere is all about
this present moment It's all about right
here right now our right hemisphere It
thinks in pictures and it learns
kinesthetically through the movement of
our bodies
Information in the form of energy streams
in simultaneously through all of our
systems and then it explodes into this
enormous collage of what this present
moment looks like,
what this present moment smells like and
tastes like,
what it feels like, and what it sounds
like.
I am an energy being connected to the
energy all around me through the
consciousness of my right hemisphere.
We are energy beings connected to one
another through the consciousness of our
right hemispheres as one human family.
And right here, right now,
we are brothers and sisters on this planet
here to make the world a better place. And
at this moment, we are perfect,
we are whole,
and we are beautiful.
My left hemisphere, our left hemisphere,
is a very different place.
Our left hemisphere thinks linearly and
methodically.
Our left hemisphere is all about the past
and it's all about the future.
Our left hemisphere is designed to take
that enormous collage of the present
moment and start picking out details,
details,
and more details about those details.
It then categorizes and organizes all that
information,
associates it with everything in the past
we've ever learned, and projects into the
future all of our possibilities.
And our left hemisphere thinks in
language.
It's that ongoing brain chatter that
connects me and my internal world to my
external world.
It's that little voice that says to me,
hey,
you've got to remember to pick up bananas
on your way home.
I need them in the morning.
It's that calculating intelligence that
knows, that reminds me, when I have to do
my laundry.
But perhaps most important,
it's that little voice that says to me,
I am,
I am.
And as soon as my left hemisphere says to
me, I am.
separate I become a single solid
individual separate from the energy flow
around me and separate from you and this
is the portion of my brain that I lost on
the morning of my stroke in the morning of
the stroke I woke up to a pounding pain
behind my left eye and it was the kind of
pain caustic pain that you get when you
bite into ice cream
it just gripped me,
and then it released me.
And then it just gripped me, and then it
released me.
And it was very unusual for me to ever
experience any kind of pain, so I thought,
okay, I'll just start my normal routine.
So I got up and I jumped onto my cardio
glider, which is a full body, full
exercise machine.
And I'm jamming away on this thing, and
I'm realizing that my hands look like
primitive claws grasping onto the bar.
And I thought that's very peculiar, and I
looked down at my body, and I thought,
whoa, I'm a weird looking thing.
And it was as though my consciousness had
shifted away from my normal perception of
reality, where I'm the person on the
machine having the experience to some
esoteric space where I'm witnessing myself
having this experience.
And it was all very peculiar, and my
headache was just getting worse, so I get
off the machine, and I'm walking across my
living room floor, and I realize that
everything inside my body has slowed
way down,
and every step is very rigid and very
deliberate. There's no fluidity to my
pace, and there's this constriction into
my area of perception, so I'm just focused
on internal systems.
And I'm standing in my bathroom, getting
ready to step into the shower, and I could
actually hear the dialogue inside my
body. I heard a little voice saying, okay,
you muscles, you have to contract, and you
muscles, you relax. And then I lost my
balance, and I'm propped up against the
wall,
and I looked down at my arm,
and I realized that I can no longer define
the boundaries of my body.
I can't define where I begin and where I
end, because the atoms and the molecules
of my arm blended with the atoms.
molecules of the wall and all I could
detect was this energy, energy and I'm
asking myself what is wrong with me, what
is going on and at that moment my brain
chatter, my left hemisphere brain chatter
went totally silent just like someone took
a remote control and pushed the mute
button,
total silence and at first I was shocked
to find myself inside a silent mind but
then I was immediately captivated by the
magnificence of the energy around me and
because I could no longer identify the
boundaries of my body I felt enormous and
expansive,
I felt at one with all the energy that was
and it was beautiful there and then all of
a sudden my left hemisphere comes back
online and it says to me, hey we got a
problem
We've got to get some help, and I'm going,
oh, I've got a problem, I've got a
problem.
I got a problem, but then I immediately
drifted right back out into the
consciousness,
and I affectionately refer to this space
as La La Land.
But it was beautiful there. Imagine what
it would be like to be totally
disconnected from your brain chatter that
connects you to the external world.
So here I am in this space, and my job,
and any stress related to my job, it was
gone. And I felt lighter in my body.
And imagine all the relationships in
the external world, and any stressors
related to any of those, they were gone.
And I felt this sense of peacefulness.
And imagine what it would feel like to
lose 37 years of emotional baggage.
Oh,
I felt euphoria,
euphoria.
It was beautiful there. And then again, my
left hemisphere comes online.
to pay attention.
We've got to get help and I'm thinking
I've got to get help. I've got to focus.
So I get out of the shower and I'm
mechanically dressed and I'm walking
around my apartment and I'm thinking I've
got to get to work. I've got to get to
work.
Can I drive?
Can I drive? And at that moment my right
arm went totally paralyzed by my side.
Then I realize, oh my gosh, I'm having a
stroke.
I'm having a stroke. And then the next
thing my brain says to me is,
wow,
this is so cool.
This is so cool.
How many brain scientists have the
opportunity to study their own brain from
the inside out?
But I'm a very busy woman
to strong from happening so I'll do this
for a week or two and then I'll get back
to my routine.
I got to call work. I could remember the
number at work. So I remembered in my
office I had a business card with my
number on it. So I go into my business
room and pull out a three -inch stack of
business cards and I'm looking at the card
on top and even though I could see clearly
in my mind's eye what my business card
looked like, I couldn't tell if this was
my card or not because all I could see
were pixels and the pixels of the words
blended with the pixels of the background
and the pixels of the symbols and I just
couldn't tell and then I would wait for
what I call a wave of clarity and in that
moment I would be able to reattach to
normal reality and I could tell that's not
the card, that's not the card, that's not
the card. It took me 45 minutes to get one
inch down inside that stack of cards.
In the meantime for 45 minutes the
hemorrhage is getting bigger in my left
hemisphere. I do not understand numbers. I
do not understand a telephone but it's the
only plan I have so I take the phone pad
and I put it right here. I take the
business card and I put it right here and
I'm matching the shape of the squiggles on
the card to the shape of the squiggles on
the phone pad but then I would drift back
out into La La Land and not remember when
I come back if I had already dialed those
numbers.
So I had to wield my paralyzed arm like a
stump and cover the numbers as I went
along and pushed them so that as I would
come back to normal reality I'd be able to
tell,
yes I've already dialed that number.
Eventually the whole number gets dialed
and I'm listening to the phone and my
colleague picks up the phone and he says
to me,
woo woo woo.
myself,
oh my gosh, he sounds like a golden
retriever.
And so I say to him, clear in my mind, I
say to him, this is Jill, I need help. And
what comes out of my voice is,
woo, woo, woo, woo, woo,
they think oh my gosh, I sound like a
golden retriever. So I couldn't know, I
didn't know that I couldn't speak or
understand language until I tried.
So he recognizes that I need help and he
gets me help. And a little while later,
I'm writing in an ambulance from one
hospital across Boston to Mass General
Hospital.
And I curl up into a little fetal ball.
And just like a balloon with the last bit
of air just right out of the balloon, I
just felt my energy lift and just I felt
my spirit surrender.
And at that moment, I knew that I was no
longer the choreographer of my life.
And either the doctors rescue my body and
give me a second chance at life, or this
was perhaps my moment of transition.
When I woke later that afternoon, I was
shocked to discover that I was still
alive.
When I felt my spirit surrender, I said
goodbye to my life. And my mind was now
suspended between two very opposite planes
of reality.
Stimulation coming in through my sensory
system felt like pure pain.
Light burned my brain like wildfire and
sounds were so loud and chaotic that I
could not pick a voice out from the
background noise. And I just wanted to
escape because I could not identify the
position of my body in space.
I felt enormous and expansive,
like a genie just liberated from her
bottle.
And my spirit soared free like a great
whale gliding through a sea of silent
euphoria,
nirvana.
I found nirvana.
And I remember thinking there's no way I
would ever be able to squeeze the
enormousness of myself back inside this
tiny little body.
But then I realized,
but I'm still alive.
I'm still alive. And I have found nirvana.
And if I have found nirvana and I'm still
alive, then everyone who is alive can find
nirvana.
And I pictured a world filled with
beautiful,
peaceful,
compassionate, loving people who knew that
they could come to this space at any time
and that they could purposely choose to
step to the right of their left
hemispheres and find this peace.
And then I realized what a tremendous gift
this experience could be. What a stroke of
insight this could be to how we live our
lives.
And it motivated me to recover.
Two and a half weeks after the hemorrhage,
the surgeons went in and they removed a
blood clot the size of a golf ball that
was pushing on my language centers. Here I
am with my mama,
who's a true angel in my life.
It took me eight years to completely
recover.
So who are we?
We are the life force power of the
universe with manual dexterity and two
cognitive minds.
And we have the power to choose moment by
moment who and how we want to be in the
world.
I can step into the consciousness of my
right hemisphere,
where we are
I am the life force power of the universe.
I am the life force power of the 50
trillion beautiful molecular geniuses that
make up my form. And one, with all that
is,
or I can choose to step into the
consciousness of my left hemisphere where
I become a single individual,
a solid, separate from the flow,
separate from you.
I am Dr. Jill Baltic Taylor, intellectual,
neural anatomist.
These are the inside of me.
Which would you choose?
Which do you choose and when?
I believe that the more time we spend
choosing to run the deep inner peace
circuitry of our right hemispheres,
the more peace we will project into the
world
and the more peaceful our planet will be.
And I thought that was an idea worth
spreading.
You