About a year ago, I asked my YouTube
followers to play a simple computer
programming puzzle that I made with a
buddy. The object of the puzzle was to get
your car across the maze by arranging
these code blocks that represent typical
computer programming operations such as
IFL statements and while loops.
Once you thought you had a good code, you
would hit run, and your car would move
based on the commands you had in the
program.
I asked my YouTube followers to play it
because I said I wanted to prove that
anyone from any background could learn to
code.
50, 000 of them took the challenge and
attempted the puzzle.
The truth was that I didn't actually care
about proving that anyone could learn to
code.
What they didn't know is that we actually
randomly served up two slightly different
versions of the puzzle.
In one version, if you hit run and you
weren't successful, you didn't lose any of
you're starting 200 points.
We showed you this message.
However, in the other version, if you hit
run and again, you weren't successful,
we showed this slightly different message
stating that you lost five points from
you're starting 200 points.
That was the only difference.
In one version, if you failed, we simply
took away five.
No value in the real world. No one will
ever see these completely meaningless fake
internet points.
That minor difference is crucial to keep
in mind for the results I'm about to show
you from the 50, 000 data points we
collected.
For those who were penalized for failed
attempts,
their success rate was around 52%.
For those who were not penalized, their
success rate was 68%.
That statistically significant delta of 16
% was astounding and almost seemed
too hard to believe until we looked at
another piece of data that we collected,
which was attempts to solve before finding
success.
It's shown in orange right here. So those
who didn't see failing in a negative light
nearly had two and a half times more
attempts to solve the puzzle.
As a result, naturally, they saw more
success and therefore learned more.
So if you think about that and sort of
unpack these results,
the trick to learning more and having more
success is finding the right way to frame
the learning process.
And this observation seemed really
profound to me.
It made me wonder what if you just framed
the learning process in such a way that
you didn't concern yourself with failure?
How much more successful could you be? How
much more could you learn?
And the next thought was that if this is a
real effect, clearly there must be some
evidence for this in real life. It made me
think of toddlers.
It's like, oh boy, I helped make that.
They are constantly trying new things and
they certainly aren't concerned with
failure. When my son learned to walk, he
didn't think about how dumb he might look
if he fell down.
And as his parents, we didn't punish him
if he wasn't successful either.
The focus was always on the end goal and
we celebrated the successes with him.
As a result of constantly failing and
trying and discovering new things during
that phase of our life, we discover so
many more new capabilities within
ourselves and it's not even close to any
other time in our life.
But maybe using a toddler is sort of
cheating because their brains are
different from ours.
To make the case that perhaps they aren't
that different from us, I'd like to tell
you about a plumber I first met when I was
eight years old. He was Italian.
When Super Mario Brothers came out, my
friends and I became obsessed.
Like we wanted to get to the castle and
rescue the beautiful Princess Peach from
the evil Bowser. We get to school and ask
each other, like, dude, what level did you
make it to? Did you pass the game?
We never asked each other about details on
all the different ways we might have died.
When it comes to games like this, no one
ever picks up the controller for the first
time and then after jumping into a pit
thinks I'm so ashamed that was such a
failure and they never want to try again,
right? What really happens is they think,
oh, I've got to remember, there's a pit
right there. So I think next time I'm
going to come out with a little more
speed, I'm going to jump a little bit
later.
The focus and obsession is about beating
the game, not how dumb you might look if
you get hit by a sliding green shell. And
as a direct result of that attitude of
learning from but not being focused on the
failures,
we got perfect and we learned a ton in
a very short amount of time. We were the
right side of this graph.
This is what I call the Super Mario
Effect,
focusing on the princess and not the pits
to stick with the task and to learn more.
This caused me to reflect and realize that
there were lots of other examples from my
own personal experience where this
attitude of life gamification,
this Super Mario Effect led to more
success and therefore more learning.
So I have a science YouTube channel where
I will sometimes use my engineering skills
to build things such as the world's
largest super soaker or the Guinness World
Record world's largest Nerf gun.
Or maybe this snow ball machine gun.
Yes! This is fashion from a leaf blower.
That's my niece.
Those are my nephews,
I think I figured it out, but when it
comes to me, their uncle, they seem to
have some trust issues.
So these builds usually take me about two
to three months, but there was one that
took me three years.
Basically I wanted to make a dart board
where you could get a bullseye every time.
The idea was that if you throw a dart, we
could like track it through the air, and
then we'd move the board to sort of like
catch a bullseye.
And so once we did the math, we realized
that if we wanted to track the dart for a
typical like game of darts, typical
velocity,
we would basically have to both track the
dart and to move the board the same amount
of time, it takes for a human to blink
once.
No big deal, right?
So I'm not going to bore you with all the
details and the failures and the setbacks
from a lot of metaphorical sliding green
shales and those pesky hammerhead bros,
but eventually we figured out it would
take something that looks like this, which
is six stepper motors and motion
controllers,
a Icon motion capture system with six
cameras,
and just a ton of tweaking and rewriting
the code. But finally, eventually we
arrived here.
what's interesting is when I look back on
that process like I can honestly say my
attitude towards that was the same
attitude I had toward like rescuing the
princess from Bowser like of course each
failure and setback sucked it's stung but
it was no different from like falling in
that pit on level 81 they're like ah you
got to go back to the level and try again
like it was always like okay that sucked
but what did we learn from that like what
can we do next for let's hit it again and
this concept of life gamification is more
than just like have a positive attitude
right or never give up because those sort
of imply you're having to endure against
your true desire to quit I feel like when
you frame a challenge or a learning
process in the way I'm describing you
actually want to do it is feels natural to
ignore the failures and try again in the
same way a toddler will want to get up and
try and walk again or in the same way you
want to keep playing Super Mario Brothers
or in the same way the group on the right
had a desire to stick with that puzzle two
and a half time longer they weren't
getting paid to do that nobody was forcing
them or watching them it was just them on
their computer alone in their house their
outlook made it so they wanted to keep
trying and learning and the icing on the
cake for the dartboard was I took it on
Jimmy Kimmel and challenged him to a game
of darts, and I'll just set this clip up by
saying two things the first is we also had
a mode on the board where if your buddy
had it and through a dart the board would
move the other way and the second is that
we couldn't get this thing working during
rehearsal and it was just barely kind of
creeping along I get up to stand in the
elevator which is the door that moves up
before you go down out on stage I look to
the right all six cameras had failed so my
buddy John is feverishly like restarting
all the cameras as I'm going out on the
stage knowing this and there's like four
things and bits and I work up to the
dartboard as the sort of grand finale so
just keep that in mind as this clip starts
like that's where my headspace is three
freaking years and it comes down to this
moment what you're going to do is you're
going to give this start to your buddy okay
challenge him just to like to hit the board
just try to hit the board yeah okay all
right
all right and so then I step up
automatically that's right and you built
this that's right yeah I step up here we
go
Fake it till you make it.
I will say, in all of our testing,
literally, we never had a dead center
bullseye as much as that one right there.
And so, like, after that, I haven't even
touched the board since. I'm like, I'm so
done with it.
And I really believe that if you reframe,
like, the challenges, it can make all the
difference. I have a simple thought
experiment to sort of showcase this. Let's
say I gave you a test and it had
instructions on it that you would carry
out. And to do that, it had sort of
buttons like this.
And the instructions would say something
like, push button three for five seconds,
and then push button six for one seconds,
then push buttons three and five for six
seconds, and so on.
And unless you carried out the
instructions on page one exactly, you
couldn't see the other 32 pages of the
test.
How much would I have to pay you to take
that test for an hour?
Now, suppose I changed the word test here
to game
and I rotated this.
And for the input device,
I shrunk the buttons and moved them here,
and I gave it a cool paint job.
And maybe different button styles.
And then instead of using words, I
represented the tasks you needed to
accomplish visually like this.
Note the output is the exact same.
You have to push these buttons in a very
specific manner to move on to the next
page or level as it were.
Now picture it's 1986.
How much would you pay me to take this
test just for an hour? If you have a very
bad imagination,
here's a hint to the right answer. I know
I was there.
Nintendo!
Thank you.
Oh, don't come at me, don't play with it.
That has to be the greatest YouTube clip
of all time.
So as a science YouTuber, sometimes I feel
people have framed the act of learning
science negatively. It's been
taught poorly, so it feels scary to them.
It feels something more like this.
And my approach is to take the same
physics lessons you might have hated,
and to try and sort of trick you into
learning something through something cool.
Basically to go from this to this.
So for example, in this video I made a hot
tub with liquefied sand.
And this is another one of my nephews with
unexplained trust issues.
I explained in the video that it's a
fluidized bed. And then we talk about the
principle of buoyancy and how it makes the
whole thing work. And I use several
examples,
like the blow-dryer with a ping pong ball
like this.
I like to think my approach to science is
similar to velociraptor hunting patterns.
So I get people to come in with something
cool and amazing, like the sand hot tub.
And then when they least expect it,
clever girl.
Admittedly the analogy breaks down a
a little bit right there at the end.
But by reframing the learning process and
focusing on the cool end goal,
the fear of failure is often taken off the
table and learning just comes more
naturally.
I'll close with this thought.
Someone came up with this cartoon and I
totally love it.
This is so true, but often in life we tell
ourselves
that the top version is what we want.
That's what we expect.
But then something happens. Maybe it's a
really bad grade on a test or a meeting
with a client that goes for a Luring.
Maybe it's a bad breakup.
Maybe we miss a wide open shot. Some kind
of green shell hits you.
And so at that first setback or sign of
failure, doubt creeps in. We tell
ourselves we're not good enough or we're
not smart enough.
And yet if the bottom rectangle here is a
game where now your bike's crashed and you
have to get your bike across to the flag,
it's not, oh, I hit these rocks, I'm just
going to leave my bike here. I'm not good
enough and you quit and walk away. You see
that flag to the right and you're like,
nah, like what did I just learn? You're
like, okay, next time I think I'm gonna
come out with more speed and I'm gonna
lift the front of my bike up. You wanna
try it again. You're immediately excited
to go for it again.
We sort of tell ourselves we want our
life's challenges to look like the top
one, but that's boring.
If that were a real video game or a book
or a movie, that went out to the market.
It would be a total failure.
Nobody would buy it. Where's the risk and
the reward?
Where's the challenge? There's no feeling
of satisfaction.
The bottom picture is real life and that's
not a bug.
That's a feature.
Think about anything that means anything
to you in life, whether it's a degree, a
relationship with a friend or someone in
your family, maybe professional
accomplishment.
I can guarantee you it came from something
that looks like the bottom and not the
top. Failing and failing and failing and
eventually succeeding to the point that it
now holds value. Just like the most
meaningful high-fives of my adolescence
were those when I said, dude, I finally
beat Bowser last night.
I feel like a lot of the successes in my
life have come down to the Super Mario
effect. And while framing challenges like
this has worked for me, of course results
may vary. Everyone is going to be
different and I don't know exactly what it
looks like for you to take this principle
and map it into your life. But if we got
these very real results from a very
different cross -section of unique
people,
clearly I'm not alone.
There's some universal principle at play
here.
By shifting your focus to the princess and
treating your life's challenges like video
games, you can trick your brain and
actually learn more and see more success.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you.