The human voice, it's the instrument we
all play.
It's the most powerful sound in the world,
probably it's the only one that can start
a war or say, I love you.
And yet many people have the experience
that when they speak, people don't listen
to them.
Why is that? How can we speak powerfully
to make change in the world?
What I'd like to suggest there are a
number of habits that we need to move away
from. I've assembled for your pleasure
here seven deadly sins of speaking.
I'm not pretending this is an exhaustive
list, but these seven I think are pretty
large.
Habits that we can all fall into.
First,
gossip,
speaking ill of somebody who's not
present.
Not a nice habit and we know perfectly
well the person gossiping five minutes
later will be gossiping about us.
Second, judging.
We know people who are like this in
conversation and it's very hard to listen
to somebody if you know that you're being
judged and found wanting at the same time.
Third, negativity.
You can fall into this. My mother in the
last years of her life became very, very
negative and it's hard to listen. I
remember one day I said to her,
it's October the first today and she said,
I know, isn't it dreadful?
It's hard to listen when somebody's that
negative.
And another form of negativity,
complaining.
Well, this is the national art of the UK.
It's our national sport. We complain about
the weather, about sport, about politics,
about everything.
But actually complaining is viral misery.
It's not spreading sunshine and lightness
in the world.
Excuses.
We've all met this guy. Maybe we've all
been this guy. Some people have a blame
-thrower.
They just pass it on to everybody else and
don't take responsibility for their
actions. And again, hard to listen to
somebody who's being like that.
Penultimate, the sixth of the seven,
embroidery,
exaggeration.
It demeans our language actually
sometimes.
For example, if I see something that
really is awesome,
what do I call it?
And then of course this exaggeration
becomes lying, out-and-out lying and we
don't want to listen to people we know are
lying to us.
And finally,
dogmatism.
The confusion of facts with opinions.
When those two things get conflated,
you're listening into the wind. You know,
somebody is bombarding you with their
opinions. As if they were true,
it's difficult to listen to that.
So here they are,
seven deadly sins of speaking. These are
things I think we need to avoid.
But is there a positive way to think about
this?
Yes, there is.
I'd like to suggest that there are four
really powerful cornerstones, foundations,
that we can stand on if we want our speech
to be powerful and to make change in the
world.
Fortunately, these things spell a word.
The word is hail and it has a great
definition as well. I'm not talking about
the stuff that falls from the sky and hits
you on the head.
I'm talking about this definition, too
greet or acclaim enthusiastically, which
does I think how our words will be received
if we stand on these four things. So what
do they stand for?
See if you can guess.
The H,
honesty, of course.
Being true in what you say, being straight
and clear.
The A is authenticity,
just being yourself.
A friend of mine described it as standing
in your own truth, which I think is a
lovely way to put it.
The is integrity,
being your word, actually doing what you
say and being somebody people can trust.
And the L is love.
I don't mean romantic love,
but I do mean wishing people well.
For two reasons. First, I think
absolute honesty may not be what we want.
I mean, my goodness, you look ugly this
morning.
Perhaps that's not necessary.
Tempered with love, of course, honesty is
a great thing. But also, if you're really
wishing somebody well,
it's very hard to judge them at the same
time.
I'm not even sure you can do those two
things simultaneously.
So Hale.
Also, now that's what you say, and it's
like the old song, it is what you say,
it's also the way that you say it.
You have an amazing toolbox. This
instrument is incredible.
And yet this is a toolbox that very few
people have ever opened.
I'd like to have a little rummage in there
with you now. And just pull a few tools
out that you might like to take away and
play with, which will increase the power
of your speaking.
Register, for example.
Now, falsetto register may not be very
useful most of the time. But there's a
register in between.
I'm not going to get very technical about
this for any of you who are voice coaches.
You can locate your voice, however.
So if I talk up here in my nose, you can
hear the difference if I go down here in
my throat, which is where most of us speak
from most of the time.
But if you want weight,
you need to go down here to the chest.
You hear the difference?
We vote for politicians with lower voices.
It's true, because we associate depth with
power and with authority.
That's register.
And we have timbre.
It's the way your voice feels.
Again, the research shows that we prefer
voices which are rich,
smooth,
warm,
like hot chocolate.
Well, if that's not you, that's not the
end of the world. Because you can train.
Go get a voice coach.
And there are amazing things you can do
with breathing, with posture,
and with exercises to improve the timbre
of your voice.
Then prosody. I love prosody. This is the
sing-song, the meta -language that we use
in order to impart meaning. It's Route 1
for meaning in conversation.
People who speak all on one note are
really quite hard to listen to if they
don't have any prosody at all.
That's where the word monotonic comes
from, or monotonous, monotone.
Also, we have repetitive prosody now
coming in, where every sentence ends as if
it were a question, when it's actually not
a question, it's a statement.
And if you repeat that one over and over,
it's actually restricting your ability to
communicate through prosody, which I think
is a shame.
So let's try and break that habit.
Pace. I can get very, very excited by
saying something really, really quickly,
or I can slow right down to emphasize.
And at the end of that, of course, is our
old friend silence.
It's nothing wrong with a bit of silence
in a talk, is there?
We don't have to fill it with UMS and RS.
It can be very powerful.
Of course, pitch often goes along with
pace to indicate a arousal, but you can do
it just with pitch.
Where did you leave my keys?
It's a slightly different meaning in those
two deliveries.
And finally, volume.
I can get really excited
by using volume, sorry about that, if I
startled anybody,
or I can have you really pay attention by
getting very quiet.
Some people broadcast the whole time, try
not to do that. That's called podcasting.
Imposing your sound on people around you
carelessly and inconsiderately, not nice.
Of course, where this all comes into play,
most of all, is when you've got something
really important to do. It might be
standing on a stage like this and giving a
talk to people. It might be proposing
marriage,
asking for a raise,
a wedding speech, whatever it is.
If it's really important, you owe it to
yourself to look at this toolbox and the
engine that it's going to work on, and no
engine works well without being warmed up,
warm up your voice.
Actually,
let me show you how to do that. Would you
all like to stand up for a moment?
I'm going to show you the six vocal warm
-up exercises that I do before every talk
I ever do.
Any time you're going to talk to anybody
important, do these. First, arms up.
Deep breath in and sigh out like that. One
more time.
Very good.
Now we're going to warm up our lips, and
we're going to go bop, bop, bop,
bop, bop, bop, bop, bop. Very good.
And now...
Just like when you were a kid.
Now your lips should be coming alive.
We're going to do the tongue next with
exaggerated la, la, la.
La, la, la, la. Beautiful! You're getting
really good at this, and then roll an R.
That's like champagne for the tongue.
Finally, and if I can only do one,
the prose called this the siren, it's
really good. It starts with we and goes to
or. The are high, the or is low. So we
go whee!
Fantastic!
Give yourselves a round of applause. Thank
you.
Next time you speak do those in advance.
Now let me just put this in context to
close.
This is a serious point here.
This is where we are now, right? We speak
not very well into people who simply
aren't listening in an environment that's
all about noise and bad acoustics. I have
talked about that on this stage in
different phases.
What would the world be like if we were
speaking powerfully to people who are
listening consciously in environments
which were actually fit for purpose or to
make that a bit larger?
What would the world be like if we were
creating sound consciously and consuming
sound consciously and designing all our
environments consciously for sound? That
would be a world that does sound beautiful
and one where understanding would be the
norm and that is an idea worth spreading.
Thank you.
You