Ladies and gentlemen please welcome Mr.
Tim Minchin.
In darker days,
I did a corporate gig at a conference for
this big company who made and sold
accounting software.
In a bid, I presumed to inspire their
salespeople to greater heights. They'd
forked out 12 grand for an inspirational
speaker who was this extreme sports guy
who had a couple of his limbs frozen
off when he got stuck on a ledge on some
mountain.
It was weird.
Software salespeople, I think, need to
hear from someone who has had a long,
successful and happy career in software
sales, not from an overly optimistic ex
-mountaineer.
Some poor guy who had arrived in the
morning hoping to learn more about sales
techniques ended up going home worried
about the blood flow to his extremities.
It's not inspirational, it's confusing.
And if the mountain was meant to be a
symbol of life's challenges and the loss
of limbs and metaphor for sacrifice,
the software guy is not going to get it,
is he? Because he didn't do an art
degree, did he?
He should have. Arts degrees are awesome,
and they help you find meaning where there
is none.
And let me assure you,
there is none.
Don't go looking for it. Searching for
meaning is like searching for a rhyme
scheme in a cookbook.
You won't find it, and it'll bugger up
your souffle.
If you didn't like that metaphor, you
won't like the rest of it.
Point being, I'm not an inspirational
speaker. I've never lost a limb on a
mountainside metaphorically or otherwise,
and I'm certainly not here to give career
advice because,
well, I've never really had what most
would consider a job.
However, I have had large groups of people
listening to what I say for quite a few
years now, and it's given me an inflated
sense of self-importance.
So I will now, at the ripe old age of 37
.9,
bestow upon you nine life lessons.
To echo, of course, the nine lessons of
carols of the traditional Christmas
service,
which is also pretty obscure.
You might find some of this stuff
inspiring. You will definitely find some
of it boring, and you will definitely
forget all of it within a week.
And be warned, there will be lots of hokey
similes and obscure aphorisms which start
well but end up making no sense.
So listen up, or you'll get lost, like a
blind man clapping in a pharmacy trying to
echo locate the contact lens fluid.
It's looking for my old poetry teacher.
Here we go.
Ready?
You don't have to have a dream.
Americans on talent shows always talk
about their dreams. Fine, if you have
something you've always wanted to do,
dreamed of, like in your heart, go for it.
After all, it's something to do with your
time, chasing a dream.
And if it's a big enough one,
it'll take you most of your life to
achieve, so by the time you get to it, and
are staring into the abyss of the
meaninglessness of your achievement,
you'll be almost dead, so it won't matter.
I never really had one of these dreams,
and so I advocate passionate dedication to
the pursuit of short -term goals.
Be micro -ambitious. Put your head down
and work with pride on whatever is in
front of you. You never know where you
might end up. Just be aware the next
worthy pursuit will probably appear in
your periphery, which is why you should be
careful of long -term dreams. If you focus
too far in front of you, you won't see the
shiny thing out the corner of your eye.
Right?
Good.
Advice, metaphor.
Look at me go. Two,
don't seek happiness. Happiness is like an
orgasm.
If you think about it too much, it goes
away.
LAUGHTER
Keep busy and aim to make someone else
happy, and you might find you get some as
a side effect. We didn't evolve to be
constantly content.
Contented Homo erectus got eaten before
passing on their genes.
Three,
remember it's all luck.
You are lucky to be here. You are
incalculably lucky to be born, and
incredibly lucky to be brought up by a
nice family that helped you get educated
and encouraged you to go to uni.
Or if you're born into a horrible family,
that's unlucky and you have my sympathy,
but you're still lucky.
happened to be made of the sort of DNA
that went on to make the sort of brain
which, when placed in a horrible childhood
environment, would make decisions that
meant you ended up eventually graduating
uni.
Well done, you, for dragging yourself up
by your shoelaces, but you were lucky. You
didn't create the bit of you that dragged
you up, they're not even your shoelaces.
Now, suppose I worked hard to achieve
whatever dubious achievements I've
achieved, but I didn't make the bit of me
that works hard,
and more than,
any more than I made the bit of me that
ate too many burgers instead of attending
lectures when I was here at UWA.
Understanding that you can't truly take
credit for your successes, nor truly blame
others for their failures, will humble you
and make you more compassionate.
Empathy is intuitive, but it's also
something you can work on intellectually.
Four,
exercise.
I'm sorry you pasty -pale, smoking
philosophy grads, arching your eyebrows
into a Cartesian curve as you watch the
human movement mob winding their way
through them, the miniature traffic cones
of their existence.
You are wrong and they are right.
Well, you're half right. You think
therefore you are, but also you jog,
therefore you sleep, therefore you're not
overwhelmed by existential angst. You
can't be can't, and you don't want to be.
Play a sport, do yoga, pump high and run,
whatever, but take care of your body.
You're going to need it. Most of you mob
are going to live to nearly 100, and even
the poorest of you will achieve a level of
wealth that most humans throughout history
could not have dreamed of.
And this long, luxurious life ahead of you
is going to make you depressed.
But don't despair, there is an inverse
correlation between depression and
exercise.
Do it, run, my beautiful intellectuals,
run.
on your opinions.
A famous Bon Motto asserts that opinions
are like assholes and that everyone has
one.
There is great wisdom in this, but I would
add that opinions differ significantly
from assholes and that yours should be
constantly and thoroughly examined.
I used to do exams in here.
It's revenge.
We must think critically and not just
about the ideas of others. Be hard on your
beliefs, take them out onto the verandah
and hit them with a cricket bat.
Be intellectually rigorous, identify your
biases, your prejudices, your privileges.
Most of society's arguments are kept alive
by a failure to acknowledge nuance.
We tend to generate false dichotomies and
then try to argue one point using two
entirely different sets of assumptions,
like two tennis players trying to win a
match by hitting beautifully executed
shots from either end of separate tennis
courts.
By the way, while I have science and arts
graduates in front of me, please don't
make the mistake of thinking the arts and
sciences are at odds with one another.
That is a recent, stupid and damaging
idea.
You don't have to be unscientific to make
beautiful art to write beautiful things.
If you need proof,
Twain, Douglas Adams, Vonnegut, McEwan,
Sagan, Shakespeare, Dickens for a start.
You don't need to be superstitious to be a
poet. You don't need to hate GM technology
to care about the beauty of the planet.
You don't have to claim a soul to promote
compassion.
Science is not a body of knowledge nor a
belief system. It is just a term which
describes humankind's incremental
acquisition of understanding through
observation.
Science is awesome.
The arts and sciences need to work
together to improve how knowledge is
communicated.
The idea that many Australians, including
our new PM and my distant cousin, Nick
Min chin,
believe that the science of anthropogenic
global warming is controversial is a
powerful indicator of the extent of our
failure to communicate.
The fact that 30 % of the people in this
room just bristled is further evidence
still.
The fact that bristling is more to do
with politics than science is even more
despairing.
Six.
Be a teacher, please,
please, please be a teacher.
Teachers are the most admirable and
important people in the world. You don't
have to do it forever, but if you're in
doubt about what to do, be an amazing
teacher.
Just fear 20s. Be a teacher. Be a primary
school teacher, especially if you're a
bloke. We need male primary school
teachers.
Even if you're not a teacher,
be a teacher.
Share your ideas. Don't take for granted
your education. Rejoice in what you learn
and spray it.
Seven.
Define yourself by what you love.
I found myself doing this thing a bit
recently where if someone asked me what
sort of music I like, I say, well, I don't
listen to the radio because pop song
lyrics annoy me. Or if someone asked me
what food I like, I say, I think truffle
oil is overused and slightly obnoxious.
And I see it all the time online. People
whose idea of being part of a subculture
is to hate Coldplay or football or
feminists or the liberal party.
We have a tendency to define ourselves in
opposition to stuff. As a comedian, I make
my living out of it.
But try to also express your passion for
things you love.
Be demonstrative and generous in your
praise of those you admire.
Send thank you cards and give standing
ovations. Be pro stuff, not just anti
stuff.
Eight.
Respect people with less power than you.
I have in the past made important
decisions about people I work with, agents
and producers, big decisions based largely
on how they treat the weight stuff in the
restaurants we're having the meeting in.
I don't care if you're the most powerful
cat in the room. I will judge you on how
you treat the least powerful.
So there.
Nine.
Finally, don't rush.
You don't need to already know what you're
going to do with the rest of your life.
I'm not saying sit around smoking cones
all day, but also don't panic.
Most people I know who were sure of their
career path at 20 are having midlife
crises now.
I said at the beginning of this ramble,
which is already three and a half minutes
long, that life is meaningless.
It was not a flippant assertion. I think
it's absurd the idea of seeking meaning in
the set of circumstances that happens to
exist after 13 .8 billion years worth of
unguided events.
Leave it to humans to think the universe
has a purpose for them.
However, I'm no nihilist. I'm not even a
cynic. I am actually rather romantic.
And here's my idea of romance.
You will soon be dead.
Life will sometimes seem long and tough
and God, it's tiring.
And you will sometimes be happy and
sometimes sad. And then you'll be old and
then you'll be dead.
There is only one sensible thing to do
with this empty existence. And that is
fill it.
Not fill it.
Fill it.
And in my opinion, until I change it,
life is best filled by learning as much as
you can about as much as you can, taking
pride in whatever you're doing, having
compassion, sharing ideas,
running,
being enthusiastic.
And then there's love and travel and wine
and sex and art and kids and giving and
mountain climbing.
But you know all that stuff already.
It's an incredibly exciting thing,
this one
meaningless life of yours.
Good luck and thank you for indulging me.
Chancellor, Tim Minchin is an Australian
musician,
composer,
songwriter,
actor,
comedian,
and writer.
This understated description from Tim's
self -pend profile sits in modest contrast
to the comments of Tim Arthur, editor of
Time Out, who wrote,
Tim Minchin is a genius,
pure and simple.
He is to musical comedy what Charles
Darwin was to evolution and what Einstein
was to physics and mustaches.
You'd be hard pushed to find a more
sublimely talented comedian,
handsome,
hysterical,
and divinely musically gifted.
Originally from Perth in WA, Tim, his wife
Sarah, and their two children now live in
London.
He's part of a large and close-knit family
and has always enjoyed their full support.
Tim is an alumnus of Christchurch Grammar
School and the University of Western
Australia.
He graduated from UWA in 1996 with a
Bachelor of Arts in English and Theatre.
In 1997,
he was accepted into the West Australian
Academy of Performing Arts,
graduating with an advanced diploma of
contemporary music in 1998.
Tim tells us that his career as a composer
had its origins at Midnight Youth Theatre
Company, where he wrote scores for several
shows in his late teens.
He also worked with WA Youth Theatre
Company and wrote music and acted with the
University Dramatic Society.
He has been performing his unique brand of
musical comedy in front of ever-growing
audiences since starting out in South
Melbourne's Butterfly Club in 2005.
He won the Directors Award at the
Melbourne International Comedy Festival
for his breakout show, Dark Side,
and followed this later the same year with
one of the most successful debut acts ever
at the Edinburgh Fringe, winning the
Perrier Award for Best Newcomer.
Several awards have followed over the
years, most recently the Best Supporting
Actor in the 2013 Watson Stage Awards for
his role in Jesus Christ Superstar.
Rock and Roll Nerd,
a documentary about Tim's life as he rose
from obscurity to celebrity between 2005
and 2006,
premiered at the Melbourne International
Film Festival in July 2008 and was
released on DVD in 2009.
It was shown at the Australian Film
Festival at the Barbican London in the
same year.
In 2010,
Tim and Dennis Kelly were commissioned by
the Royal Shakespeare Company to write
Matilda the Musical,
based on Roald Dahl's famous children's
story.
The show continues to run in London and
New York and has won critical acclaim and
a record seven Olivier Awards.
Tim has recently starred as drug -addled
nudist Atticus Fetch in season six of
Californification,
as a furious Judas in the arena tour of
Lloyd Webber's Jesus Christ Superstar,
and as a befuddled Rosencrantz in the
Sydney Theatre Company's production of Tom
Stoppard's, Rosencrantz and Guildenstern
Are Dead.
He's currently writing a new stage musical
and will soon start work on a musical
feature film for DreamWorks Animation.
Arguably, Tim is the best -known
Australian live comedian in the world,
having performed as a soloist at the Royal
Albert Hall and at New York Town Hall.
In Australia, he's performed sell -out
shows at the Sydney Opera House, the
Brisbane Powerhouse and His Majesty's
Theatre Perth, and has performed at the
Adelaide Fringe, the Adelaide Cabaret
Festival, the Melbourne International
Comedy Festival and the Big Laugh Festival
in Sydney.
Tim has released four live comedy albums,
five DVDs, and his television and radio
credits in the UK and Australia and the
United States are numerous.
His celebrated nine -minute beat poem,
Storm,
has been animated and premiered in London
in October 2010. Made available to all on
YouTube, the following year it has
recorded in excess of two million hits.
In 2010, Tim narrated Sean Tan's Oscar
-winning film, The Lost Thing,
an animated 15 -minute short,
based on the children's book of the same
name.
Tim is an outspoken advocate of critical
thinking,
can't read music,
as we heard, likes running,
and cries if he watches movies on
Airplanes.
He's patron of WA Youth Theatre Company,
the Prince's Foundation for Children and
the Arts,
and Roald Dahl's Marvelous Children's
Charity.
A record of Tim Minchin's achievements
would not be complete without this tribute
from the Melbourne Age.
Simultaneously, an excellent stand -up
comedian,
a purveyor of physical comedy,
an accomplished musician,
and a lyricist of diabolical ingenuity.
Witty, smart,
and unabashedly offensive.
Chancellor,
it is my privilege to present to you for
conferral of the honorary degree of Doctor
of Letters,
Mr Tim Minchin.
On behalf of this university, I confer the
honorary degree of Doctor of Letters upon
Timothy David Min chin.