So if you want to make six figures, you
can't just be talking about you want to
make six figures. You hear what I'm saying
to you tonight?
If you do the three things I tell you to
do tonight, I guarantee you whatever it is
you want to do in life, you'll be able to
do.
You will be able to accomplish whatever
you want to academically, financially,
relationally, whatever. So three things.
All right, I'm going to tell you this
story. I got to get out of here. And the
story is about, you guys have probably
heard about this before. It was a young
man who, you know, he wanted to make a lot
of money and so he went to this guru,
right?
And he told the guru, you know, I want to
be on the same level you are. And so the
guru said, if you want to be on the same
level I'm on, I'll meet you tomorrow at
the beach at 4 AM.
He liked the beach.
I said, I want to make money. I don't want
to swim.
Guru said, if you want to make money, I'll
meet you tomorrow at 4 AM.
So the young man got there at 4 AM. He is all
raided rock and roll, got on the suit,
should have worn shorts.
The old man grabs his hands and said, how
bad do you want to be successful? He said,
real bad. He said, walk on out in the
water.
So he walks out into the water. Watch
this. When he walks out into the water, it
goes waist deep.
So he's like, this guy crazy.
He's like, I want to make money. He got
me. I just swim.
I didn't ask to be a lifeguard.
I want to make money. He got me in. So he
said, come out a little further. Walked
out a little further. Then he had it right
around this area.
It's still the area.
So this old man crazy. He's making money,
but he is crazy.
He said, come on out a little further. He
came out a little further.
He was right at his mouth. My man like,
I'm about to go back in here. This guy is
mine.
So the old man said, I thought you said
you wanted to be successful. He said, I
do. He said, walk a little further. He
came, dropped his head in, held him down,
hold him down. My man getting scratched
and holding him down. I got you. I know
you brushed it out, but I got you. He had
him held down. I need you for
illustration.
He had him held down just before my man
was about to pass out. He raised him up.
He said, I got a question for you.
Somebody answered the question for me. He
said, when you were underwater, what did
you want to do?
Lee, I'm looking for a different word
though. What's that word?
He said, I wanted to breathe.
He told the guy,
he said, when you want to succeed,
as bad as you want to breathe, then you'll
be successful.
I don't know how many of y 'all got asthma
in here today, but if you ever had an
asthma attack before,
you sure to breath.
That's so big.
Shortness of breath. You're wheezing.
The only thing you're trying to do is get
some air.
You don't care about no basketball game.
You don't care what's on TV. You don't
care about nobody calling you. You don't
care about a party.
The only thing you care about when you're
trying to breathe is to get some fresh
air. That's it.
And when you get to the point where all
you want to do is be successful, as bad as
you want to breathe, then you'll be
successful.
And I'm here to tell you, number one, that
most of you say you want to be successful,
but you don't want it badly. You just kind
of want, it.
You don't want it worse than you want to
party. You don't want it as much as you
want to be cool.
Most of you don't want success as much as
you want to sleep.
Some of you love sleep more than you love
success. And I'm here to tell you today,
if you're going to be successful, you've
got to be willing to give up sleep.
You've got to be willing to live up to
three hours of sleep, two hours. If you
really want to be successful, someday
you'll have to stay up three days in a
row.
Because if you go to sleep, you might miss
the opportunity to be successful. That's
how bad you've got to want it. You've got
to go days without listening to me. You've
got to want to be successful so bad that
you forget to eat.
Beyoncé said, one, she was on the set
doing her thing. Three days had gone by.
She forgot she didn't eat.
Because she was engaged. I'll never forget
when 50 Cent was doing his movie. I did a
little research on 50. And 50 said that
when he wasn't doing the movie, he was
doing the soundtrack.
And they said, when do you sleep, 50?
Sleep, he said sleep. Sleep is for those
people who are broke.
I don't sleep.
So I got an opportunity to make a dream
become a reality.
Football players. How many footballs
players?
Got anybody like football in here? Raise
your hand. Anybody like football?
Image Smith. I used to be a cowboy fan.
Before they did my boy Tom Landry wrong. I
used to be a cowboy fan. And watch this.
There was a commercial. Image Smith had
won his first soup bowl. And he had this
commercial. And he was lifting weights.
All of you saw the commercial. He was
lifting. And he said,
Image said, you know what? I won the soup
bowl. So I can rest now.
He was doing his bench press. So he said,
I won the soup bowl. So I can rest now. So
he throws up about 325.
Boom.
And he rests for about two seconds.
And he.
Boom.
Boom. Boom. Boom. Did you see that?
He had already won a soup bowl. He said, I
think I'm going to take a rest. And he
rests for how long? One second. Most of
you won't be successful. Because when
you're studying and you get tired, you
quit.
And I'm here to tell you today, if you got
it, somebody came on off the other day
crying.
I said, look, don't cry to give up. Cry to
keep going.
Don't cry to quit.
You already in pain. You already hurt. Get
a reward from it.
Don't go to sleep until you succeed.
Listen to me. I'm here to tell you today
that you can come here. You can jump up.
You can do flips. You can be excited when
we give away money. But listen to me.
You'll never be successful until I don't
have to give you a dime to do what you do.
You won't be successful until you say, I
don't need that money.
Because I got it in here.
Listen to me. Emmett Smith said this at
the end of the commercial. Emmett Smith
said, all men are created equal. Some work
harder in three seasons.
I'm going to say it again because you
might have missed it. All men are created
equal.
Some work harder in three seasons.
So that means that there are some people
who are going to see the professor,
going to see the TA. And even when the
professor says, I don't meet with you. My
TA meets with you. You say, I don't want
to talk to your TA.
I don't pay the TA.
I pay you to teach me.
So you're going to have to find some time
to meet me. If I got to meet you at the
mall, if I got to meet you at your house,
you are going to see me.
Listen to me. All men are created equal.
Some work harder in three seasons. When I
went to college, guys were way smarter
than me. 4 .0's, 3 .0's, they went to the
Ivy League high schools, came to Oakwood
from these great high schools. Most of
them are not doing what I'm doing. Why?
Because it's not about where you come
from. It's about heart.
You come to a place where, you know, being
smart ain't enough.
You've got to have heart.
That's number one. Watch number two.
Number two. Catch number two. I wrote a
dime. I want to make sure you got it. It
says to be, watch this. Watch this. We're
talking about sacrifice now.
The important thing is this. You're right.
You know what I'm saying? Because I only
have about three more minutes. Listen to
me. The most important thing is this. To
be able at any moment to sacrifice what
you are for what you will become.
That's the number two thing. You've got to
catch that one.
To be able to listen to me at any moment.
Some of you, you can make sacrifices when
Monday Night Football is not on. You can
make a sacrifice. But when the game come
on, for some reason, you just attach to
it.
For some of you, when your favorite show
come on, you can make sacrifices on
Sunday. Well, they ain't going on.
But when your favorite show comes on
Monday Night Football, some of you, you
focus into the phone with it. And you got
to answer it. If I don't answer the phone,
I'm going to die.
I'm saying to you today that there are
some of you, if you give up your cell
phone, you would be successful.
But your cell phone is more important to
you than your success.
I'm going to say it again, I'm going to
hurt somebody.
I'm going to hurt somebody.
Some of you need to give up your cell
phone because the time you spend on your
cell phone could be used for your success.
The time you could be using to be
successful,
you're using it on the cell. And the cell
phone is not bringing you anything but a
bill.
And somebody has told you, you couldn't
live without it. I'm talking about going
deep now, giving up stuff. Watch what it
says.
To be able at any moment to sacrifice what
we are for what we can be. I don't do well
than math. You're right.
You ain't never studied.
I'm not good at writing because you have
never written before.
But I dare you to fail in writing for a
whole year to see if you can get to the
end.
I dare you to fail.
I dare you to take that same class over
and over again. I dare you to stop
dropping classes like you saw.
Always want to give up. I'm dropping. Why
are you dropping?
I'm so grateful that the slaves didn't
drop and quit. Say, I'm just going to
stop. I'm a slave. I'm just going to be a
slave.
I'm going to quit. Listen to me. The
slaves said, we will live because one day
we will become.
We won't always be slaves.
So today, although we're slaves, we're
going to act like we free. And one day our
children will be free. If the slaves would
have just said, we quit, we give up. We
would have died in the middle passage.
But some slaves said, I don't care what we
go through. We're going to survive this.
400 years of slavery. We're going to get
through this. And you can't get through an
1825.
You can't get through a writing class. And
you got tutor after tutor, resource after
resource.
The problem is you ain't never felt no
pain before. You're soft.
It's a soft generation.
You quit on everything.
Our people did not quit.
Harry and Tubman not only made it. She
went back and got some more.
She said, you know what? I made it. But
I'm going to walk all the way. Listen to
me. Shh. Not ride the bus. I'm going to
walk all the way back now to the south to
get some more. And you quit on 1825.
Now watch this. You quit after you listen
to me. You get a sleeping bag and you wait
for them.
You wait for the first WRA instructor to
come in. And you come out you're sleeping
bag. I need help.
You quit after you do that.
You quit after you had. Listen to me. A
WRA party.
I'm having a party. Everybody come over. I
got food and everything. And let them get
over there. Let it be all the best riders.
All right. I'm food job. I want to have a
writing party.
I'm serious.
You quit and you ain't even tried yet.
Last one. I'm sorry. Last one.
Listen to me. Pain is temporary.
It may last for a minute or an hour or a
day or even a year.
But eventually it will subside.
And something else will take its place.
If I quit, however,
it will last forever.
Listen to me. I'm telling you as I leave
you.
I'm telling you as I leave you. I was
homeless for two and a half years.
And apart from most of you, you never felt
no pain before. Y 'all spoiled.
Y 'all spoiled. Some of y 'all spoiled.
Just bottom line.
Your parents have done everything for you.
You never had to do nothing for yourself.
You spoiled. We don't keep it real
tonight. Some of you are spoiled brats.
Every time you ever got in trouble,
somebody in your house got you out of it.
Every time you've done something you're
not supposed to do. People say, your
mother's a tyrant. You're right. She
kicked me out. You're right. She's mean.
But she developed a man. Because she put
me out there and said, you're going to
have to grow up. And some of you have
never learned to grow up.
And so every time something gets hard, you
quit. You call mama. I dare you to take a
little pain.
I dare you.
I dare you not to go home.
Somebody said, I have to go home. I feel
bad. Go through it.
You ain't going to die at the end of pain
and success.
You're not going to die because you're
feeling a little pain.
I'm not eating like I eat at home. That's
why you're about to go to the next level.
Because if you keep eating like you ate at
home, you'll keep being a boy or a girl.
It's time to become man woman.
So don't worry about a little pain.
My greatest asset is I was homeless.
So I can't feel a lot of pain.
I've already been alone.
There's not a lot of hurt I can
feel.
On a little paper.
On a little test. So I leave you. I leave
you. Listen to me.
We have gotten to a point where it's
midterms and we're moving forward.
The days of you getting money. I'm not
saying we're quitting. But I'm saying the day
has got to go from external to internal.
You have to give it everything you got. No
more TV. No more parties. No more plans.
If you have a 4 .0, what you need to be
doing is studying.
Get off the phone.
I'm sorry. I'm not available until the end
of this year.
No, I'm for real. You reached the right
number but you called me at the wrong
time.
Call me back January 1st.
I'm about to get busy now.
Huh?
I want you to have a countdown of your
own.
And say when the countdown is over, with a
real, shh, watch me. Because when I was
homeless, I knew something was wrong. I
knew that wasn't the best of me. One day I
said, will the real Eric Thomas please
stand up?
Will the real Eric Thomas please stand up?
Stop being this high school dropout. Stop
giving up. Stop sweeping on the street.
Stop walking up and down FICO Avenue like
you ain't got nothing. And get your GED.
Stop being afraid to take a test.
Stop being afraid to go to college because
your daddy didn't go, and your mama didn't
go. Stop being afraid and be the best Eric
Thomas you can be. But listen to me. It's
going to be hard. It took me 12 years to
get a four-year degree. But I got it. And
guess what? On a degree, they don't have
dates.
So if it took you four, it took me 12,
they don't show up nowhere.
But I'm exactly where I wanted to be.
Because I realized,
I got to commit my very being to this
thing. I got to breathe it. I got to feel
it. I got to sleep it. And until you get
there, you'll never be successful in life.
But once you get there, I guarantee you
the world is yours.
So work hard. And you can have whatever it
does you want? Thank you guys for your time.
Thank you.