I'm going to tell you a little bit about
my TEDx Houston talk.
I woke up the morning after I gave that
talk with the worst vulnerability hangover
of my life.
And I actually didn't leave my house for
about three days.
The first time I left was to meet a friend
for lunch.
And when I walked in, she was already at
the table and I sat down and she said,
God, you look like hell.
I said, thanks,
I feel really,
I'm not functioning. And she said, what's
going on? And I said, I just told 500
people that I became a researcher to avoid
vulnerability
and that when being vulnerable emerged
from my data as absolutely essential to a
wholehearted living,
I told these 500 people that I had a
breakdown.
I had a slide that said breakdown. At what
point did I think that was a good idea?
And she said, I saw your talk live
streamed. It was not really you, it was a
little different from what you usually do,
but it was great.
And I said,
this can't happen,
YouTube, they're putting this thing on
YouTube and we're going to be talking
about 600,
700 people.
And she said, well,
I think it's too late. And I said,
let me ask you something.
She said, yeah. And I said,
do you remember when we were in college
and really wild and kind of dumb?
She said, yeah. And I said, remember when
we leave a terrible message on our ex
-boyfriend's answering machine?
Then we'd have to break into his dorm room
and then erase the tape.
And she goes,
no.
So, of course, the only thing I could
think of to say at that point was, yeah,
me neither.
Yeah, me neither.
And I'm thinking to myself,
Brent, what are you doing? What are you
doing? Why did you bring this up?
Have you lost your mind?
Your sisters would be perfect for this.
So I look back up and she said,
are you really going to try to break in
and steal the video before they put it on
YouTube?
And I said,
I'm just thinking about it a little bit.
She said,
you're like the worst vulnerability role
model ever.
And then I looked at her and I said
something that at the time felt a little
dramatic but ended up being more prophetic
than dramatic. I said,
if 500 turns into 1, 000 or 2, 000,
my life is over.
I had no contingency plan for four
a million.
And my life did end when that happened.
And maybe the hardest part about my life
ending is that I learned something hard
about myself and that was that as much as
I would be frustrated about not being able
to get my work out to the world, there was
a part of me that was working very hard to
engineer staying small,
staying right under the radar.
But I want to talk about what I've
learned. There are two things that I've
learned in the last year.
The first is vulnerability is not
weakness.
And that myth is profoundly dangerous.
Let me ask you honestly,
and I'll give you this warning. I'm
trained as a therapist, so I can outweigh
you uncomfortably.
So if you could just raise your hand, that
would be awesome.
How many of you honestly, when you're
thinking about doing something vulnerable
or saying something vulnerable,
thank God, vulnerability is weakness. This
is weakness. How many of you think of
vulnerability and weakness synonymously?
The majority of people.
Now let me ask you this question. This
past week at TED,
how many of you when you saw vulnerability
up here thought it was pure courage?
Vulnerability is not weakness.
I define vulnerability as emotional risk,
exposure,
uncertainty.
It fuels our daily lives.
And I've come to the belief, this is my
12th year doing this research,
that vulnerability is our most accurate
measurement of courage.
To be vulnerable, to let ourselves be
seen, to be honest.
One of the weird things that's happened is
after the TED explosion, I got a lot of
offers to speak all over the country.
Everyone from schools and parent meetings
to Fortune 500 companies,
and so many of the calls went like this,
hey Dr. Brown, we love your TED talk, we'd
like you to come in and speak.
We'd appreciate it if you wouldn't mention
vulnerability or shame.
What would you like for me to talk about?
There are three big answers.
This is mostly, to be honest with you,
from the business sector.
Innovation,
creativity,
and change.
So let me go on the record and say,
vulnerability is the birthplace of
innovation,
creativity,
and change.
to create is to make something that has
never existed before.
There's nothing more vulnerable than that.
Adaptability to change is all about
vulnerability.
The second thing, in addition to really
finally understanding the relationship
between vulnerability and courage, the
second thing I learned is this.
We have to talk about shame.
And I'm going to be really honest with
you. When I became a vulnerability
researcher,
and that became the focus because of the
TED talk, and I'm not kidding that.
I'll give you an example. About three
months ago, I was in a sporting good
store, buying goggles and shin guards and
all the things that parents buy at the
sporting goods store.
About from 100 feet away, this is what I
hear.
Vulnerability TED, vulnerability TED.
I'm a fifth generation Texan.
Our family motto is lock and load.
vulnerability researcher.
So I'm like,
just keep walking, she's on my six.
And then I hear, vulnerability Ted!
I turn around, I go,
hi,
she's right here. And she said,
you're the shame researcher who had the
breakdown.
At this point,
parents are like pulling their children
close,
look away.
And I'm so worn out at this point in my
life. I look at her and I actually say, it
was a fricking spiritual awakening.
And she looks back and does this.
I know.
And she said,
we watched your Ted talk in my book club.
Then we read your book and we renamed
ourselves the breakdown babes.
And she said, our tagline is, we're
falling apart and it feels fantastic.
You can only imagine what it's like for me
in a faculty meeting.
So when I became vulnerability Ted, like
an action figure,
like Ninja Barbie, but I'm vulnerability
Ted,
I thought I'm going to leave that shame
stuff behind because I spent six years
studying shame before I really started
writing and talking about vulnerability.
And I thought, thank God, because shame is
this horrible topic,
no one wants to talk about it. It's the
best way to shut people down on an
airplane.
What do you do? I study shame. Oh, and I
see you.
But in surviving this last year,
I was reminded of a cardinal rule,
not a research rule,
but a moral imperative from my upbringing.
You got to dance with the one who brought
you.
And I did not learn about vulnerability
and courage and creativity and innovation
from studying vulnerability.
I learned about these things from studying
shame.
And so I want to walk you in to shame.
Union analysts call shame the swamp land
of the soul.
And we're going to walk in. And the
purpose is not to walk in and, you know,
construct a home and live there.
It is to put on some galoshes and walk
through and find our way around.
Here's why.
We heard the most compelling call ever to
have a conversation in this country
and I think globally around race, right?
Yes, we heard that.
Yes.
Cannot have that conversation without
shame.
Because you cannot talk about race without
talking about privilege and when people
start talking about privilege, they get
paralyzed by shame.
We heard a brilliant simple solution to
not killing people in surgery, which is
have a checklist.
You can't fix that problem without
addressing shame because when they teach
those folks how to suture,
they also teach them how to stitch their
self-worth to being all -powerful.
And all -powerful folks don't need
checklists.
And I had to write down the name of this
Ted Fellow, so I didn't mess it up here.
Michigan Ingo ale.
I hope I did right by you.
I saw the Ted Fellow my first day here and
he got up and he explained how he was
driven to create some technology to help
test for anemia because people were dying
unnecessarily.
And he said, I saw this need, so you know
what I did? I made it.
And everybody just burst into applause and
they were like, yes. And he said,
and it didn't work.
And then I made it 32 more times.
And then it worked.
You know what the big secret about Ted is?
I can't wait to tell people this. I guess
I'm doing it right now.
This is like the failure conference.
No, it is.
You know why this place is amazing?
Because very few people here are afraid to
fail.
And no one that gets on the stage so far
that I've seen has not failed.
I have failed miserably
many times. I don't think the world
understands that because of shame.
There's a great quote that saved me this
past year by Theodore Roosevelt.
A lot of people refer to it as a man in
the arena. And it goes like this. It is
not the critic who counts.
It is not the man who sits and points out
how the doer of deeds could have done
things better and how he falls and
stumbles.
The credit goes to the man in the arena
whose face is marred with dust and blood
and sweat.
But when he's in the arena at best, he
wins.
And at worst, he loses.
But when he fails, when he loses,
he does so daring greatly.
And that's what this conference to me is
about.
That's what life is about, about daring
greatly, about being in the arena.
When you walk up to that arena and you put
your hand on the door and you think I'm
going in and I'm going to try this,
shame is the gremlin who says,
uh -uh,
you're not good enough.
You never finished that MBA.
Your wife left you.
I know your dad really wasn't in
Luxembourg. He was in Sing.
I know those things that happen to you
growing up.
I know you don't think that you're pretty
enough or smart enough or talented enough
or powerful enough.
I know your dad never paid attention even
when you made CFO.
Shame is that thing.
And then if we can quiet it down and walk
in and say, I'm going to do this,
we look up and the critic that we see
pointing and laughing,
99 % of the time is who?
Us.
Shame drives two big tapes, never good
enough.
And if you can talk it out of that one,
who do you think you are?
The thing to understand about shame is
it's not guilt.
Shame is a focus on self. Guilt is a focus
on behavior.
Shame is I am bad. Guilt is I did
something bad.
How many of you, if you did something that
was hurtful to me, would be willing to
say, I'm sorry, I made a mistake?
How many of you would be willing to say
that?
Guilt,
I'm sorry, I made a mistake.
Shame,
I'm sorry, I am a mistake.
There is a huge difference between shame
and guilt. And here's what you need to
know.
Shame is highly, highly correlated with
addiction, depression,
violence, aggression,
bullying,
suicide,
eating disorders.
And here's what you need to know more.
Guilt,
inversely correlated with those things.
The ability to hold something we've done
or failed to do up against who we want to
be is incredibly adaptive.
It's uncomfortable,
but it's adaptive.
The other thing you need to know about
shame is it's absolutely organized by
gender.
If shame washes over me and washes over
Chris,
it's going to feel the same.
Everyone sitting in here knows the warm
wash of shame.
We're pretty sure that the only people who
don't experience shame are people who have
no capacity for connection or empathy.
Which means, yes, I have a little shame,
no, I'm a sociopath,
so I would opt for, yes, you have a little
shame.
Shame feels the same for men and women,
but it's organized by gender.
For women,
the best example I can give you is Anjali,
who
is the commercial.
I can put the wash on the line, pack the
lunches, hand out the kisses and be work
at five to nine.
I can bring home the bacon, fry it up in
the pan, and never let you forget you're a
man.
For women, shame is do it all, do it
perfectly, and never let them see you
sweat.
I don't know how much perfume that
commercial sold, but I guarantee you, it
moved a lot of anti -depressants and anti
-anxiety meds.
Shame for women is this web of
unattainable,
conflicting, competing expectations about
who we're supposed to be.
And it's a straight jacket.
For men, shame is not a bunch of
competing, conflicting expectations.
Shame is one.
Do not be perceived as what?
Weak.
I did not interview men for the first four
years of my study, and it wasn't until a
man looked at me one day after a book
signing and said, I love what you have to
say about shame.
I'm curious why you didn't mention men,
and I said, I don't study men.
And he said, that's convenient.
And I said, why? And he said, because you
say to reach out, tell our story,
be vulnerable.
But you see those books you just signed
for my wife and my three daughters?
I said, yeah.
They'd rather me die on top of my white
horse than watch me fall down.
When we reach out and be vulnerable,
we get the shit beat out of us.
And don't tell me it's from the guys and
the coaches and the dads.
Because the women in my life are harder on
me than anyone else.
So I started interviewing men and asking
questions.
And what I learned is this.
You show me a woman who can actually sit
with a man in real vulnerability and fear.
I'll show you a woman who's done
incredible work.
You show me a man who can sit with a woman
who's just had it. She can't do it all
anymore.
And his first response is not, I unloaded
the dishwasher.
But he really listens.
Because that's all we need.
I'll show you a guy who's done a lot of
work.
Shame is an epidemic in our culture.
And to get out from underneath it.
To find our way back to each other, we
have to understand how it affects us and
how it affects the way we're parenting,
the way we're working, the way we're
looking at each other.
Very quickly, some research by Mahler at
Boston College.
He asked, what do women need to do to
conform to female norms? The top answers
in this country?
Nice, thin, modest and use all available
resources for parents.
When they asked about men, what do men in
this country need to do to conform with
male norms? The answers were,
always show emotional control,
work as first,
pursue status,
and violence.
If we're going to find our way back to
each other, we have to understand and know
empathy. Because empathy is the antidote
to shame.
If you put shame in a Petra dish,
it needs three things to grow
exponentially.
Secrecy, silence, and judgment.
If you put the same amount of shame in a
Petra dish and douse it with empathy, it
can't survive.
The two most powerful words when we're in
struggle,
me too.
And so I'll leave you with this thought.
If we're going to find our way back to
each other,
vulnerability is going to be that path.
And I know it's seductive to stand outside
the arena because I think I did it my
whole life. And thanks to myself, I'm going
to go in there and kick some ass when I'm
bulletproof and when I'm perfect.
And that is seductive. But the truth is,
that never happens.
And even if you got as perfect as you
could in as bulletproof as you could
possibly muster when you got in there,
that's not what we want to see.
We want you to go in.
We want to be with you and across from
you.
And we just want for ourselves and the
people we care about and the people we
work with to dare greatly.
So thank y 'all very much. I really
appreciate it.
Thank you.
You