In 1901,
this ancient Greek artifact was discovered
in a shipwreck off the island of
Antikythera.
3D x-ray scans have revealed it contains
37 interlocking bronze gears,
allowing it to model the motions of the
sun and moon,
and predict eclipses decades in advance.
Constructed around 100 or 200 BC,
the Antikythera mechanism represents a
sophisticated early computer, the likes of
which would not be seen again for at least
a thousand years.
Now, of course, this computer didn't work
like modern digital computers.
It works by analogy.
The gears were constructed in such a way
that the motions of certain dials are
analogous to the motion of the sun and
moon.
It is an analog computer.
Here is a simple analog computer for
adding two numbers together.
If you turn the black wheel some amount,
and then turn this white wheel a different
amount,
the gray wheel shows the sum of the two
rotations.
In contrast,
this is a digital mechanical computer
where you can add two single bit numbers.
So 0 plus 0 equals 0,
0 plus 1 equals 1,
and 1 plus 1 equals 2.
These two devices illustrate the
differences between analog and digital
computers.
Analog computers have a continuous range
of inputs and outputs,
whereas digital only works with discrete
values.
With analog computers, the quantities of
interest are actually represented by
something physical, like the amount a
wheel has turned,
whereas digital computers work on symbols
like 0s and 1s. If the answer is say 2,
there is nothing in the computer that is
twice as much as a 1.
In analog computers, there is.
For thousands of years, people used analog
devices like the anti -Kitara mechanism or
slide rules alongside digital devices like
abacuses, and up until the 1960s, the most
powerful computers on the planet were
actually analog.
Digital computers exploded onto the scene
with the advent of solid state
transistors, and now almost everything is
digital. Most people have never even heard
of analog computers.
But today,
that may all be changing.
Moore's law, the idea that you can double
the number of transistors on a chip every
two years,
it's reaching its limit because
transistors are nearly the same size as
atoms.
Simultaneously,
advancements in machine learning are
straining the capabilities of digital
computers.
The solution to these challenges may well
be a new generation of analog computers.
One of the most important problems humans
have faced for millennia is predicting the
tides.
Napoleon and his men nearly died crossing
the Red Sea due to a miscalculation of the
rising tide,
and sailors routinely needed to know the
tides to bring their ships into port
without running a ground.
Most coastal locations on earth experience
too high and too low tides per day,
but their exact timing varies as does
their magnitude,
and this is partly caused by local factors
like the depth of the seabed and the shape
of the shoreline.
In the late 1700s, to describe the tidal
flow of the oceans,
Pierre Kimono Labs derived a set of
complicated differential equations.
They had no analytical solution, so at the
time they were basically useless.
But in the process of deriving his
equations, Laplace made a key finding.
Tides are driven at only a few specifics
astronomical frequencies,
including the moon,
the sun,
and the eccentricity of the lunar orbit.
Each one of these factors contributes a
sine wave of a particular amplitude and
phase to the total tide curve.
If someone could figure out how to
correctly combine this frequency
components,
well the tides could finally be predicted.
It took nearly a century, but in the 1860s
William Thompson, later Lord Kelvin,
took up the challenge.
Having completed several voyages to lay
the first transatlantic telegraph cable,
he developed a fascination with the sea,
and subsequently he threw his full
scientific effort into measuring and
predicting the tides.
Tide gauges at the time used a buoy to
record the height of the sea onto a paper
roll.
Kelvin set out to determine how sine waves
with the frequencies identified by Laplace
could add together to produce the observed
tidal curve.
The key was to apply the work of French
mathematician Joseph Fourier,
who had shown how to decompose any
function into a sum of sine waves.
Most English scientists were skeptical of
the work, but Thompson was enthralled by
it. His first paper, published at 17,
was a defense of Fourier.
While it was straightforward to apply
Fourier's analysis to tidal curves,
the computation required was enormous.
First, divide the tide curve up into short
time intervals,
and for each interval, multiply the tide
level by a sine wave with the frequency of
interest.
Add up the area of all these rectangles
and divide by the total time,
and this gives you a single coefficient,
the amplitude of the sine wave with this
frequency.
Then you have to repeat the process for a
cosine function with the same frequency.
Kelvin found that to make accurate
predictions,
he actually needed 10 different frequency
components,
so that is a lot of multiplication and
addition to characterize the tides at just
one location.
For each additional location,
you have to perform this analysis all over
again.
And this is only half the problem.
Once you have the amplitudes and phases of
the sine functions,
you have to add them up to predict future
tides.
Lord Kelvin spent years analyzing and
predicting tides by hand.
Then he had a stroke of inspiration.
Could you design a machine to carry out
these calculations automatically?
In Kelvin's words to substitute brass for
brains,
the resulting analog computers were in use
for nearly a century.
They even played a critical role in the
outcome of World War II.
Kelvin started with the problem of
prediction,
adding the sine waves together, given you
know their amplitudes and phases.
He knew he could create sinusoidal motion
with a device called a Scotch yoke.
It extracts one dimension from uniform
circular motion.
But to make a tide prediction, he needed a
way to combine 10 sine waves together.
He needed a mechanical analog for
addition.
Stuck on this problem in 1872,
Kelvin boarded a train for a meeting with
the main sponsor of his title research,
the British Association.
On the train, Kelvin bumped into a friend,
inventor Beauchamp Tower,
to whom he explained his dilemma.
Tower suggested he use Wheatstone's plan
of a chain passing round a number of
pulleys.
And this was exactly the addition
mechanism Kelvin was looking for.
By attaching a pulley to each Scotch yoke
and running a weighted cord around them,
he could mechanically add all of their
contributions at once.
He scribbled down the entire plan for this
predictor machine by the end of the train
ride.
He pitched it to the British Association
and secured funding to build it all before
he returned home.
If you knew the relative contributions of
different frequency components,
Kelvin now had a machine to automate the
tedious task of predicting future tides.
This was a great leap forward.
Four hours of cranking the handle yielded
a full year of tidal predictions.
But for many years, the harder half of the
problem was still done by hand,
breaking apart an existing tide curve into
its component frequencies.
To automate this step, Kelvin needed a
machine capable of multiplying the tide
curve times a sine wave and then taking
its integral.
What would such a device even look like?
With his older brother James Thompson,
Kelvin came up with a mechanical
integrator.
It consists of a ball on a rotating disc.
Due to the rotation of the disc, the
further the ball is from the center,
the faster it spins.
If the ball is at the very center of the
disc, it doesn't turn at all.
And if it's on the left side, it turns in
the opposite direction.
Now the motion of the ball is converted
into an output via a roller, which moves a
pen up or down on the output graph paper.
So the way it works is you trace the
function you want to integrate with a
stylus.
And the stylus controls the position of
the ball on the disc, and hence its speed
of rotation.
This is transferred through the roller to
the output, which plots the integral of
the original function.
Now to decompose a tide curve, we don't
just want to integrate the function,
we first want to multiply it by a sine
wave of a particular frequency.
And the way to do this is to make the disc
rotate back and forth at that specific
frequency.
Now the rotation of the ball depends on not
only on where it is on the disc, but also
on how the disc is turning at that
instant.
You trace the tide curve with the stylus,
which moves the ball back and forth on the
oscillating disc, and the roller sums up
the integral of the tide curve times the
sine wave.
Simply divide by the total time to get the
coefficient.
Several of these ball and disc integrators
can be connected in parallel,
with each disc oscillating at a different
frequency,
to calculate the coefficients for multiple
frequency components at the same time.
Kelvin's analog computers revolutionized
our ability to predict tides.
Tidal curves from anywhere in the world
could be turned into a set of sinusoidal
coefficients using the ball and disc
harmonic analyzer,
and the resulting sinusoids could be added
together to predict future tides using his
Scotch -Yoke pulley machine.
Kelvin's harmonic analyzers were the basis
for a landmark analog computer called the
Differential Analyzer, and his tide
predicting machines were used well into
the 1960s.
In fact, they were later overhauled to
include 26 frequency components and used
to plan the Allied invasion on D-Day.
The Germans expected any invasion to come
at high tide to minimize the time Allied
soldiers would be exposed on the beaches,
so they installed millions of obstacles
that would be underwater by mid-tide,
many with explosive mines attached.
But the Allies spotted the obstacles and
changed tack. Instead, they planned to
begin the invasion at low tide.
This would allow demolition teams to first
clear channels through the obstacles.
Then the main forces could come through
those gaps as the water rose.
This would also give landing craft enough
time to depart without getting beached.
The low water times were different at the
five landing beaches by over an hour, so
the invasion times were staggered
according to the tide predictions.
This wasn't the only use of analog
computers in World War II.
Dive bomber aircraft would plummet out of
the sky directly toward their targets at
up to an 80-degree angle, and their rapid
descents made them very difficult to shoot
down.
So the US began searching for devices to
automatically aim guns at dive bombers.
Most of the proposed solutions fell into
one of two categories.
Some were analog machines like Lord
Kelvin's, others were essentially fast
calculators.
Mechanical calculating machines like the
Abacus had been around for millennia, but
they were far too slow to respond to dive
bombers. These new calculating machines
sped things up by using electrical pulses.
The committee considered naming these
devices after the pulses they used, but
member George Kibitz proposed a more
general name,
digital,
because these machines operated on numbers
themselves,
or digits.
And this is the origin of the term digital
computer.
But digital would have to wait. Of all the
proposals, an innovative analog machine
from David Parkinson went out.
At Bell Labs in New York, Parkinson had
been working on a device to chart
telephone data called an automatic level
recorder.
It used a variable resistor called a
potentiometer to control the motion of a
pen.
One night, after hearing reports of the
harrowing Allied evacuation of Dunkirk,
Parkinson had a dream that he was on the
front lines.
I found myself in a gun pit with an anti
-aircraft gun crew.
A gun there was firing occasionally, and
the impressive thing was that every shot
brought down an airplane.
After three or four shots, one of the men
in the crew smiled at me and beckoned me
to come closer to the gun.
When I drew near, he pointed to the
exposed end of the left trunnion.
Mounted there was the control
potentiometer of my level recorder.
When he woke up, Parkinson realized the
device he was building to control a pen
could be scaled up to control an anti
-aircraft gun.
He shared this idea with his supervisor,
and after receiving approval from the
military,
they set out to make Parkinson's dream a
reality.
Researchers at Bell Labs had recently
invented an analog electrical device
called an operational amplifier or op
-amp.
It could perform mathematical operations
with voltages like addition and
multiplication.
They used these op -amps to create an
analog computer that could solve the
ballistics equations for anti-aircraft
guns.
Using radar and optical sights to obtain
the speed, altitude, and direction of
enemy planes,
the M9 gun director, as the computer was
called,
could rapidly calculate the correct
trajectory and fuse setting.
Potentiometers were used to ascertain the
direction the gun was pointing.
This was not the first electric analog
computer, but it was an important one.
In World War I, it took an average of 17
, 000 rounds to take down a single
airplane.
In 1943, after the invention of the M9, it
took an average of only 90.
During the war, the US invested big in
analog computers.
If you break down their total military
budget, the third-largest single expense
was the development and production of an
incredibly complex mechanical analog
computer called the Borden bomb site.
Unfortunately,
they didn't get their money's worth.
Designed by the eccentric Dutch engineer
Carlo Nordio, the Borden bomb site was built
to enable high precision airborne bombing.
It implemented 64 different simultaneous
algorithms,
including one that compensated for the
rotation of the earth as the bomb fell.
The Borden was one of the most closely
guarded secrets of the war.
To prevent the technology from falling
into enemy hands,
American bombardiers carried handguns
specifically to destroy it in the event of
a crash.
But despite its hype and funding,
the Borden didn't work as advertised.
With over 2, 000 fine parts,
it required extreme precision to
manufacture.
The problem with analog computers is that
the physical device is a model for the
real world, so any inaccuracy in the
components translates into inaccuracy of
the computation.
And since there will always be some slop
in the connections between parts,
if you run the same calculation twice,
you won't get the exact same answer.
In the American campaign against Japan,
bomber crews using the bomb site were
unable to destroy critical Japanese war
infrastructure.
And ultimately,
the US abandoned its precision bombing
approach and instead blanketed whole
Japanese cities in napalm.
As the war progressed, digital computers
gained traction.
The digital and electronic colossus
machines of Bletchley Park in the UK were
critical to breaking German codes.
In the United States, the military
invested in an enormously complex and
expensive digital machine known as ENIAC.
It was designed to speed up the
calculation of land artillery firing
tables.
At the time, these were computed using
differential analyzers, the analog
mechanical computers based on Kelvin's
harmonic analyzer.
Although not finished until after the war,
ENIAC demonstrated the power of digital
computers.
It's considered by many to be the first
modern computer.
What really opened the door to this
digital revolution was the discovery made
by Claude Shannon in his 1936 master's
thesis.
He showed that any numerical operation can
be carried out using the basic building
blocks of Boolean algebra.
Two values, true or false, also notated as
one or zero,
and three operations,
and or and not.
This makes digital computers the ideal
versatile computing machines.
In contrast, each analog computer is an
analog for only one type of problem.
Furthermore, since digital computers
operate on ones and zeros,
they are more resilient in the face of
noise.
It would take a large error to mistake a
one for a zero or vice versa,
whereas even small errors in analog
computers can grow and ultimately swamp
the signal.
So these days, everything is digital. Our
phones, computers,
and internet data centers, even TV and
radio is now being broadcast as digital.
And the advantages are obvious.
Since digital devices operate on symbols,
usually zeros and ones,
they provide exact answers.
And repeat the calculation and you get the
same result.
They are robust to noise.
Plus, since only a few components are
required to perform virtually any
computation,
those components have been miniaturized
and optimized,
making digital computers the ideal
universal computing machines.
So you would think analog computers would
be long gone, a relic of the distant past,
but analog may now be making a comeback.
There are startups actively working on
analog computers.
Why is this happening? What could be the
benefit of analog?
I wanted to put all of this into one
video,
but the story is too good to bury 20
minutes in. So that is coming up in part
two. Be sure you're subscribed to the
channel to be notified when that comes
out.
I'll give you a hint about the sequel in
this section of the video, which is
sponsored by Brilliant.
Brilliant is a website and app that uses
interactivity to help you learn STEM
concepts. For the sequel to this video, it
would be a good idea to brush up on
artificial intelligence, which you can do
with Brilliant's courses on neural
networks.
Here you can analyze how a neural network
decodes your handwriting.
I also recommend their calculus courses,
which are highly interactive.
What's great about Brilliant is how it
gets you to step through topics, answering
questions as you go,
and that way you can't trick yourself into
thinking you already understand
everything, because you're constantly
putting your knowledge to the test.
Personally, I find their courses
challenging, which they should be in order
for you to learn anything.
But if you ever get stuck, there's always
a helpful hint close at hand, and more in
-depth explanations are available if you
want them.
As the holiday season is upon us, an
annual subscription to Brilliant makes an
awesome gift for any curious learners in
your life.
And whether it's for you or someone else,
Brilliant is offering 20 % off an annual
subscription to the first 200 people to
sign up. Just go to Brilliant .org slash
Verulamium. I'll put that link down in the
description.
So I want to thank Brilliant for
supporting Verulamium, and I want to thank
you for watching.