Imagine a future where your toaster
anticipates what kind of toast you want.
During the day, it scans the internet for
new and exciting types of toast.
Maybe it asks you about your day and wants
to chat about new achievements in toast
technology.
At what level would it become a person?
At which point will you ask yourself if
your toaster has feelings?
If it did,
would unplugging it be murder?
And would you still own it?
Will we someday be forced to give our
machines rights?
AI is already all around you.
It makes sure discounters are stocked with
enough snacks,
it serves you up just the right internet
ad, and you may have even read a new story
written entirely by a machine.
Right now, we look at chatbots like Siri
and laugh at their primitive simulated
emotions,
but it's likely that we will have to deal
with beings that make it hard to draw the
line between real and simulated humanity.
Are there any machines in existence that
deserve rights?
Most likely, not yet.
But if they come, we are not prepared for
it.
Much of the philosophy of rights is ill
-equipped to deal with the case of
artificial intelligence. Most claims for
rights, whether human or animal, are
centered around the question of
consciousness.
Unfortunately,
nobody knows what consciousness is.
Some think that it's immaterial,
others say it's a state of matter, like
gas or liquid.
Regardless of the precise definition,
we have an intuitive knowledge of
consciousness because we experience it.
We're aware of ourselves and our
surroundings and know what unconsciousness
feels like.
Some neuroscientists believe that any
sufficiently advanced system can generate
consciousness.
So if your toaster's hardware was powerful
enough, it may become self-aware.
If it does,
would it deserve rights?
Well, not so fast.
Would what we define as rights make sense
to it?
Consciousness entitles begins to have
rights because it gives a being the
ability to suffer. It means the ability to
not only feel pain, but to be aware of it.
Robots don't suffer,
and they probably won't unless we program
them too.
Without pain or pleasure,
there's no preference,
and rights are meaningless.
Our human rights are deeply tied to our
own programming.
For example, we dislike pain because our
brains evolved to keep us alive, to stop
us from touching a hot fire or to make us
run away from predators.
So we came up with rights that protect us
from infringements that cause us pain.
Even more abstract rights like freedom are
rooted in the way our brains are wired to
detect what is fair and unfair.
Would a toaster that is unable to move
mind being locked in a cage?
Would it mind being dismantled if it had
no fear of death? Would it mind being
insulted if it had no need for self
-esteem?
But what if we programmed a robot to feel
pain and emotions?
To prefer justice to injustice,
pleasure over pain, and be aware of it?
Would that make them sufficiently human?
Many technologists believe that an
explosion in technology will occur when
artificial intelligence can learn and
create their own artificial intelligences
even smarter than themselves.
At this point, the question of how robots
are programmed will be largely out of our
control.
What if artificial intelligence found
it necessary to program the ability to
feel pain just as evolutionary biology
found it necessary in most living
creatures?
Do robots deserve those rights?
But maybe we should be less worried about
the risk that super-intelligent robots
pose to us and more worried about the
danger we pose to them.
Our whole human identity is based on the
idea of human exceptionalism that we are
special, unique snowflakes entitled to
dominate the natural world.
Humans have a history of denying that
other beings are capable of suffering as
they do.
In the midst of the scientific revolution,
many Descartes argued that animals were
mere automata, robots if you will.
As such, injuring a rabbit was about as
morally repugnant as punching a stuffed
animal. And many of the greatest crimes
against humanity were justified by their
perpetrators on the grounds that the
victims were more animal than civilized
human.
Even more problematic is that we have an
economic interest in denying robot rights.
If we can coerce a sentient AI possibly
through programmed torture into doing as
we please,
the economic potential is unlimited.
We've done it before, after all.
Violence has been used to force our fellow
humans into working and we've never had
trouble coming up with ideological
justifications.
Slave owners argued that slavery benefited
the slaves.
It put a roof over their head and taught
them Christianity.
Men who were against women voting argued
that it was in women's own interest to
leave the hard decisions to men.
Farmers argued that looking after animals
and feeding them justifies their early
death for our dietary preferences.
If robots become sentient,
there will be no shortage of arguments for
those who say that they should remain
without rights, especially from those who
stand to profit from it.
Artificial intelligence raises serious
questions about philosophical boundaries.
While we may ask if sentient robots are
conscious or deserving of rights, it
forces us to pose basic questions like,
what makes us human?
What makes us deserving of rights?
Regardless of what we think, the question
might need to be resolved in the near
future.
What are we going to do if robots start
demanding their own rights?
What can robots demanding rights teach us
about ourselves? Our friends at Wisecrack
made a video exploring this very question
using the philosophy of West world.
Wisecrack dissects pop culture in a unique
and philosophical way.
Click here to check out their video and
subscribe to their channel.