What's the millennial question? Apparently
millennials as a generation, which is a
group of people who were born
approximately
1984 and after,
are tough to manage.
And they're accused of being entitled and
narcissistic and self-interested,
unfocused,
lazy,
but entitled as the big one.
And because they confound leadership so
much,
what's happening is leaders are asking the
millennials, what do you want? And
millennials are saying,
we want to work in a place with purpose,
love that.
We want to make an impact, you know,
whatever that means.
We want free food and bean bags.
And so somebody articulates some sort of
purpose, there's lots of free food and
there's bean bags, and yet for some reason
they are still not happy.
And that's because there's a missing
piece.
What I've learned is that I can break it
down into four pieces, right? There are
four things, four characteristics.
One is parenting,
the other one is technology,
the third is impatience, and the fourth is
environment.
The generation that we call the
millennials, too many of them grew up
subject to, not my words,
failed parenting strategies,
you know,
where for example they were told that they
were special all the time.
They were told that they can have anything
they want in life, just because they want
it.
They were told,
some of them got into honors classes, not
because they deserved it, but because
their parents complained,
and some of them got A's not because they
earned them, but because the teachers
didn't want to deal with the parents. Some
kids got participation medals,
they got a medal for coming in last,
right?
Which the science we know is pretty clear,
which is it devaluing the medal and the
reward for those who actually work hard,
and that actually makes the person who
comes in last feel embarrassed because
they know they didn't deserve it, so it
actually makes them feel worse, right?
So you take this group of people and they
graduate school and they get a job and
they're thrust into the real world, and in
an instant they find out they're not
special,
their moms can't get them a promotion,
that you get nothing for coming in last,
and by the way you can't just have it
because you want it,
right? And in an instant their entire self
-image is shattered,
and so you have an entire generation
that's growing up with lower self-esteem
than previous generations.
The other problem to compound it is we're
growing up in a Facebook, Instagram world,
in other words we're good at putting
filters on things, we're good at showing
people that life is amazing even though
I'm depressed,
right?
And so everybody sounds tough, and
everybody sounds like they got it all
figured out, and the reality is there being
very little toughness and most people
don't have it figured out, and so when the
more senior people say, well what should
we do, they sound like this is what you
gotta do, and they have no clue,
right?
So you have an entire generation growing
up with lower self-esteem than previous
generations, right?
Through no fault of their own, through no
fault of their own, right? They were dealt
a bad hand,
right? Now let's add in technology.
We know that engagement with social media
and our cell phones releases a chemical
called dopamine. That's why when you get a
text, it feels good, right? So you know
we've all had it where you're feeling a
a little bit down or feeling a bit lonely,
and so you send out 10 texts to 10
friends, you know, high, high, high, high,
high,
because it feels good when you get a
response, right?
Right?
It's why we count the likes, it's why we
go back 10 times to see if, and if it's
going, my Instagram is growing slower, I
do something wrong, do they not like me
anymore, right?
The trauma for young kids to be
unfriended, right?
Because we know when you get it, you get
hit a dopamine, which feels good. It's why
we like it, it's why we keep going back to
it.
Dopamine is the exact same chemical that
makes us feel good when we smoke, when we
drink,
and when we gamble.
In other words, it's highly, highly
addictive,
right?
We have age restrictions on smoking,
gambling,
and alcohol,
and we have no age restrictions on social
media and cell phones, which is the
equivalent of opening up the liquor
cabinet and saying to our teenagers,
hey, by the way, this adolescence thing,
if it gets you down,
But that's basically what's happening.
That's basically what's happening, right?
That's basically what happened. You have
an entire generation that has access to an
addictive,
numbing chemical codopamine through social
media and cell phones as they're going
through the high stress of adolescence.
Why is this important?
Almost every alcoholic discovered alcohol
when they were teenagers.
When we're very, very young, the only
approval we need is the approval of our
parents.
And as we go through adolescence, we make
this transition where we now need the
approval of our peers.
Very frustrating for our parents. Very
important for us. It allows us to
acculturate outside our immediate
families into the broader tribe, right?
It's a highly, highly stressful and
anxious period of our lives. And we're
supposed to learn to rely on our friends.
Some people, quite by accident, discover
alcohol and numbing effects of dopamine to
help them cope with the stresses and
anxieties of adolescence. Unfortunately,
that becomes hardwired in their brains.
And for the rest of their lives, when they
suffer significant stress, they will not
turn to a person, they will turn to the
bottle.
Social stress, financial stress, career
stress. That's pretty much the primary
reasons why an alcoholic drinks, right?
What's happening is because we're allowing
unfettered access to this dopamine
producing devices and media,
basically it's becoming hardwired. And
what we're seeing is as they grow older,
they too many kids don't know how to form
deep meaningful relationships.
Their words, not mine. They will admit
that many of their friendships are
superficial.
They will admit that their friends, that
they don't count on their friends, they
don't rely on their friends, they have fun
with their friends.
But they also know that their friends will
cancel on them if something better comes
along. Deep meaningful relationships are
not there because they never practice the
skill set. And worse,
they don't have the coping mechanisms to
deal with stress. So when significant
stress starts to show up in their lives,
they're not turning to a person,
they're turning to a device,
they're turning to social media,
they're turning to these things which
offer temporary relief. We know, the
science is clear, we know that people who
spend more time on Facebook suffer higher
rates of depression than people who spend
less time on Facebook.
These things balance, alcohol is not bad,
too much alcohol is bad. Gambling is fun,
too much gambling is dangerous.
There's nothing wrong with social media
and cell phones. It's the imbalance.
If you're sitting at dinner with your
friends
and you're texting somebody who's not
there,
that's a problem, that's an addiction.
If you're sitting in a meeting
with people, you're supposed to be
listening to and speaking and you put your
phone on the table,
face up or face down, I don't care,
that sends a subconscious message to the
room that you're just not that important
to me right now.
That's what happens.
And the fact that you cannot put it away
is because you are addicted.
If you wake up and you check your phone
before you say good morning to your
girlfriend, boyfriend or spouse, you have
an addiction.
And like all addiction, in time, it'll
destroy relationships,
it'll cost time and it'll cost money and
it'll make your life worse,
right?
So you have a generation growing up with
lower self-esteem that doesn't have the
coping mechanisms to do with stress,
right? Now you add in the sense of
impatience,
right? They've grown up in a world of
instant gratification.
You want to buy something, you go on Amazon,
it arrives the next day.
You want to watch a movie? Log on and watch
a movie, you don't check movie times. You
want to watch a TV show? Binge, you don't
even have to wait week to week,
right?
I know people who skip seasons just so
they can binge at the end of the season,
right?
Instant gratification.
Instant gratification. You want to go on a
date?
You don't even have to learn how to be
like, hey.
Hey.
You don't even have to learn and pray.
You don't have to be the uncomfortable on
what's his yes when you mean no and says
no, when you mean no, but yes when you, you
don't have to swipe right. Bang, I'm a
stud.
Right? You don't have to learn
the social coping mechanisms, right?
Everything you want, you can have
instantaneously.
Everything you want.
Instant gratification.
Except job satisfaction
and strength of relationships,
there ain't no app for that. They are
slow,
meandering, uncomfortable, messy
processes.
And so I keep meeting these wonderful,
fantastic, idealistic, hard -working,
smart kids. They've just graduated from school.
They're in their entry -level job. I sit
down with them when I go, how's it going?
They go, I think I'm going to quit.
I'm like, why?
They're like, I'm not making an impact.
I'm like, you've been here eight months.
You know?
It's as if they're standing at the foot of
a mountain
and they have this abstract concept called
impact that they want to have in the world,
which is the summit. What they don't see
is the mountain.
I don't care if you go up the mountain
quickly or slowly, but there's still a
mountain.
And so what this young generation needs to
learn is patience.
That some things that really, really
matter,
like love or job fulfillment,
joy,
love of life, self-confidence,
a skill set, any of these things, all of
these things take time.
Sometimes you can expedite pieces of it,
but the overall journey is arduous and
long and difficult.
And if you don't ask for help and learn
that skill set,
you will fall off the mountain, or you
will, the worst case scenario, the worst
case scenario, and we're already seeing
it. The worst case scenario is we're
seeing increase in suicide rates.
We're seeing an increase in this
generation. We're seeing an increase in
accidental deaths due to drug overdoses.
We're seeing more and more kids drop out
of school or take leaves of absence due to
depression,
unheard of.
This is terrible.
The best case scenario,
those are all bad cases, right?
The best case scenario is you'll have an
entire population
growing up and going through life and just
never really finding joy.
They'll never really find deep, deep
fulfillment in work or in life. They'll
just waft through life and it'll be just,
it's fine.
How's your job?
It's fine,
same as yesterday.
How's your relationship? It's fine.
Like that's the best case scenario, which
leads me to the fourth point, which is
environment, which are we're taking this
amazing group of young, fantastic kids who
are just dealt a bad hand. It's no fault
of their own.
And we put them in corporate environments
that care more about the numbers than they
do about the kids.
They care more about the short -term gains
than the long -term life of this young
human being. We care more about the year
than the lifetime,
right? And so we are putting them in
corporate environments that aren't helping
them build their confidence, that aren't
helping them learn the skills of
cooperation,
that aren't helping them overcome the
challenges of a digital world and finding
more balance
that isn't helping them overcome the need
to have instant gratification and teach
them the joys and impact and the
fulfillment you get from working hard on
something for a long time that cannot be
done in a month or even in a year.
And so we're thrusting them in corporate
environments and the worst part about it
does they think it's them?
They blame themselves.
They think it's them who can't deal.
And so it makes it all worse.
It's not, I'm here to tell them, it's not
them.
It's the corporations, it's the corporate
environments. It's the total lack of good
leadership in our world today that is
making them feel the way they do.
They would deal a bad hand, and it's, and
I hate to say it, but it's the company's
responsibility. Sucks to be you, like we
have no choice, right? This is what we got
and I wish that society and their parents
did a better job, they didn't. So we're
getting them in our companies and we now
have to pick up the slack. We have to work
extra hard to figure out the ways that we
build their confidence. We have to work
extra hard to find ways to teach them the
social skills that they're missing out on.
There should be no cell phones in
conference rooms.
None, zero.
And I don't mean the kind of like sitting
outside waiting to text. I mean like when
you're sitting and waiting for a meeting
to start,
nobody go, this is what we all do. We all
sit here and wait for the meeting to
start.
Meeting starting, okay,
and we start the meeting. No, that's not
how relationships are formed. Remember we
talked about it's the little things?
Relationships are formed this way. We're
waiting for a meeting to start and we go,
how's your dad, I heard he was in the
hospital.
Oh, he's perfect, thanks for asking.
He's actually at home now. Oh, I'm really
glad, that was really amazing.
I know it was terrifying for a while.
That's how you form relationships.
Hey, did you ever get that report on, oh
my God, no I didn't. I'll help you out, I
totally, can I help you out with that?
Really?
That's how trust forms.
Trust doesn't form at an event in a day.
Even bad times don't form trust
immediately. It's the slow, steady
consistency.
And we have to create mechanisms where we
allow
for those little innocuous interactions to
happen. But when we allow cell phones in
conference rooms, we just, okay, have the
meeting.
And then my favorite is when there's a
cell phone there and you go like this, you
go,
it rings and you go,
I'm not going to answer that.
Mr. Magnanimous, you know?
When you're out for dinner with your
friends, like,
I do this with my friends. When we're
going out for dinner and we're leaving
together,
we'll leave our cell phones at home.
Who are we calling? Maybe one of us will
bring a phone in case we need to call an
Uber or take a picture of our meal.
I mean, I'm not, I'm an idealist, but I'm
not insane, you know,
how to even,
I mean, it looked perfect.
We'll take one phone.
And so it's like an alcoholic. The reason
you take the alcohol out of the house is
because we cannot trust our willpower.
We're just not strong enough. But when you
remove the temptation,
it actually makes it a lot easier.
And so when you just say, don't check your
phone, people literally will go like this,
and somebody will go to the bathroom and
what's the first thing we do?
Because I wouldn't want to look around the
restaurant for a minute and a half, you
know? But if you don't have the phone, you
just kind of enjoy the world. And that's
where ideas happen.
The constant, constant, constant
engagement is not where you have
innovation and ideas.
Ideas happen when our minds wander and we
go,
and you see something, I bet they could do
that.
That's called innovation,
right? But we're taking away all those
little moments,
right?
You should not, and none of us, none of us
should charge our phones by our beds. We
should be charging our phones in the
living rooms,
right?
Remove the temptation. You wake up in the
middle of the night because you can't
sleep.
You won't check your phone, which makes it
worse.
But if it's in the living room,
it's relaxed. It's fine.
But it's my alarm clock.
Buy an alarm clock.
It costs eight dollars.
I'll buy you an alarm clock.