So I was on a roll.
I was an executive with a nice salary,
annual bonuses and stock options, all the
perks.
Everything was on track.
And on Monday,
January 7th, 2008,
at three o 'clock in the afternoon in a
small conference room on the top floor of
our building, the president of the company
wanted to have a quick meeting with me,
which wasn't unusual since he was my boss.
But the meeting turned out to be even more
briefer than expected.
He fired me.
And I'll never forget how his words just
sucked the breath right out of me.
And I left the conference room in a dazed
state, and I went home and curled up my
bed in the fetal position for three hours.
And while I could go on in detail about
how I felt, what I did to my self-esteem,
my finances, and so on,
what I now realize is while that event
created the greatest amount of discomfort
I had to depart.
that forever changed it for the better.
You see friends,
what makes you comfortable can ruin you.
What makes you uncomfortable is the only
way to grow.
Let me say that again, what makes you
comfortable can ruin you and only in a
state of discomfort can you continually
grow.
Now I suppose on January 8th somebody come
up and said, gee buddy,
getting fired's a good thing because now
you're really going to grow.
I probably want to smack them,
but pretty quickly I became motivated to
start a new journey and after a couple
years of work with my new team and a PhD
friend at the University of Nebraska, we
had this epiphany on how to illustrate and
apply the science of discomfort and
growth.
We called the concept the growth rings.
The growth rings represent living
environments that promote or hinder growth
and that includes everything from your
place of work to even a fishbowl. You see
what dictates the size of goldfish is its
environment and while this goldfish lives
in a very safe environment, it's also very
limiting in almost every way and when placed
in a more robust environment like say a
small pond,
this can be the result.
Now it also means he could be eaten,
but friends,
this is you.
The environments in which you work,
live, and play, they're all a proverbial
fishbowl that dictates your growth.
So the first growth ring represents a low
performing, low growth environment called
stagnation.
Stagnation is understood by having to
follow too many steps and permissions of
minutiae that stifle creativity,
independent thought,
and action.
To imagine an environment such as this,
think no further than our state and
federal governments.
Now the antithesis of stagnation is chaos,
also low growth and low performing.
Chaos can be caused by internal or
external events or conditions.
We see chaos occur at times in business
mergers,
natural disasters,
and horrific events like 9 -11.
Chaos is having zero predictability or
control over inputs and outcomes.
Coming back down the growth rings next to
stagnation is the most desirable
environment,
order.
Order is knowing that what you do or what
is happening in your environment needs to
a predictable outcome and in
predictability comfort is found.
But comfort is also what makes order so
dangerous because science shows that any
time you continually do something or even
think about something the same way,
you'll eventually stop growing.
And this applies to every living thing,
even our dog.
You see, if Aspen had a chance,
she'd choose comfort six days a week and
twice on Sundays.
But too much growth limiting order would
have prevented her from becoming a therapy
dog.
Think of the lives this gentle soul would
not be touching today.
So before your order continues to limit
the way you think and act, remember what I
said earlier,
growth only occurs in a state of
discomfort. Now think about the power of
that phrase,
growth only occurs in a state of
discomfort.
I can unequivocally state I wouldn't be
standing on this stage today without my
uncomfortable order disrupting day nine
years ago.
By the way, I'm not recommending you go
get fired to see if it leads to a TED
talk, but when you feel discomfort hit,
that means you've entered the complexity
ring.
Complexity is nothing more than changed
order, but when your order is changed,
outcomes are no longer predictable and
it's unpredictability that makes you
uncomfortable.
And when most times your visceral response
to discomfort is not just no but hell no,
you can actually learn how empowering it
is to consciously acknowledge discomfort
and then when appropriate choose
complexity over order. And I know seeking
discomfort sounds odd and not many people
do it, but you have to learn to embrace it
because it's the only environment
sustained or exponential growth can occur.
Okay,
to weave high growth complexity
into the fabric of your lives, there are
three primary ways it can be triggered.
Complexity trigger number one
is it can be forced upon you.
When I got fired,
I didn't have a chance to stay in order.
Complexity was selected for me. And when
this happens,
how much you grow?
Now you respond to it. Now I could have
remained angry,
I could have used it as an excuse.
But what I actually learned is that I suck
as an employee and I'm much better off
accepting the risks of running my own
company.
Complexity trigger number two,
someone can help you get there.
This is the role of parents,
teachers,
coaches,
and bosses because left on their own
people will consciously or subconsciously
select the comfort of order.
And they then need to be pushed into
complexity in order to continue growing.
My youngest daughter spent most of her
high school life training to play tennis.
And her coach was pretty familiar with our
work on complexity and the growth rings.
So I called him up one day to check on
Maddie's progress and I was able to phrase
my question like this. I said, hey, Lee,
how long has been since Maddie's been
pushed deep into complexity?
Lee's response.
Hmm. Funny you'd ask, Bill.
We got there yesterday.
She broke down into tears on the tennis
court.
Well,
knowing how tough my daughter is and the
fact that she never cries told me she was
deep into complexity.
But friends,
this is where critical developmental
decisions are made because the old bill,
the pre -growth ring bill, would have
intervened and wanted to know what was
making her so uncomfortable that I would
have done everything I could to try and
get her happy again.
What I really would have been doing is
removing the complexity and putting her in
order.
I actually would have been stifling her
development. But the new post -growth ring
bill relished in his daughter's
discomfort.
And it was the coach's next words that
told me everything I needed to hear. He
said, but Billy, I got to tell you,
it took a heck of a lot more to get her to
the limits of complexity this month than
it did last month.
Discomfort was causing her growth.
Okay, but what if you're not lucky enough
to live or work in a robust high -growth
environment? What if you're stuck in
order, even worse, stagnation?
Well, the great news is everyone can
trigger complexity at any time.
So complexity trigger number three,
trigger it yourself.
Take a journey with me back to Montgomery,
Alabama in the 1950s. Imagine if you will
a young girl whose black and she attends
an all -black high school. And she takes a
city bus to get there and home, which
wasn't unusual in that era.
And on March 2, 1955, she boards a bus to
come home from school and she sits near
the back in the first row of seats where
blacks were allowed to sit.
And as the bus continues to fill with
white people,
there's eventually no more room in the
front of the bus.
And according to local law,
she needed to move further back to create
room for white people to sit.
You see,
Montgomery had an order in place that one
followed, led to a very predictable
outcome.
Repression of people with little conflict.
The 15 -year -old Claudette Colvin had just
spent the last month in high school
studying black history. And she was
understandably fed up with the historic
and existing atrocities. And so on this
day,
she decided she didn't like Montgomery's
order.
And by refusing to give up her seat,
she sent a community,
our laws, and our entire country into
complexity.
Yes,
nine months before Rosa Parks made her
famous decision to stay put,
it was a 15 -year -old girl that was
handcuffed, dragged from the bus, and
taken to prison.
It was Ms. Colvin, not Rosa Parks who
first fought the law, and by the way,
was also the star plaintiff to testify in
the famous lawsuit that went all the way
to the U. S. Supreme Court.
So,
I use Claudette's actions not to heighten
awareness of race issues,
although that's not necessarily bad.
But I use it as an example of every issue,
of every situation in an ordered
environment. It's a real and perfect
example.
people, our communities, and our courts
into discomfort,
and the downstream impact that can occur
anytime someone elects to move from order.
Dr.
Serene Jones, in a recent book, summarizes
this concept very eloquently.
She said,
the constant facade of order hides the
wilderness that is craving to seep out and
teach us that life wasn't created to be
what we think it is.
Beyond words, we must experience the
wilderness to be taught what cannot be
otherwise known.
So friends,
it's not the discomfort of losing a job.
It's not having a child breakdown on the
tennis courts, but it's order you should
fear the most because it is a threat.
And order disrupting people like Jesus,
Galileo, Claudia Colvin,
Aspen's trainer,
and maybe even a few of you have already
proven, and I think about this,
it's not the complexity triggering
individuals or events you should fear the
most, but it's your own willingness to
accept or seek discomfort that will
dictate the growth of not just you, but
our entire world.
Thank you very much for allowing me to be
a part of this.
Thank you.