エ ンデ ィ ング
Good morning.
How are you?
It's been great, hasn't it?
I've been blown away by the whole thing.
In fact, I'm leaving.
There have been three themes, haven't
there, running through the conference,
which are relevant to what I want to talk
about. One is the extraordinary
evidence of human creativity in all the
presentations that we've had and in all
the people here.
Just the variety of it and the range of
it.
The second is that it's put us in a place
where we have no idea what's going to
happen in terms of the future.
No idea how this may play out.
I have an interest in education.
Actually, what I find is everybody has an
interest in education,
don't you?
I find this very interesting. If you're at
a dinner party and you say you work in
education,
actually, you're not often at dinner
parties, frankly.
Six 'r died.
If you're working education, you're not
asked, you know. And you're never asked
back curiously, that's the thing that
strikes me.
But if you are,
and you say to somebody,
what do you do, and you say you're working
education, you can see the blood run from
their face. They think, oh my God, you
know why me?
My one night out all week,
but if you ask people about their
education they pin you to the wall,
because it's one of those things that goes
deep with people, am I right,
like religion and money and other things.
So I have a big interest in education and
I think we all do,
we have a huge vested interest in it,
partly because it's education.
OND we 'n call a was.
If you think of it, children's starting
school this year
will be retiring in 2065.
Nobody has a clue,
despite all the expertise that's been on
parade for the past four days,
what the world will look like in five
years time
and yet we're meant to be educating them
for it.
So the unpredictability, I think, is
extraordinary.
The third part of this is that we've all
agreed nonetheless on the really
extraordinary capacities that children
have,
the capacities for innovation.
I mean Serena last night was a marvel,
wasn't she, just seeing what she could do?
And she's exceptional,
but I think she's not,
so to speak,
exceptional in the whole of childhood.
What you have there is a person of
extraordinary dedication who found a
talent.
And my contention is all kids have
tremendous talents and we squander them
pretty ruthlessly.
So I want to talk about education and I
want to talk about creativity.
My contention is that creativity now is as
important in education as literacy.
And we should treat it with the same
status.
Thank you.
That was it. Thank you very much.
So 15 minutes left.
Well, I was born. No, the...
I had a great story recently,
I love telling it, of a little girl who
was in a drawing lesson, she was six and
she was at the back drawing and the
teacher said this little girl hardly ever
paid attention and in this drawing lesson
she did, and the teacher was fascinated,
she went over to and she said what are you
drawing and the girl said I'm drawing a
picture of God and the teacher said but
nobody knows what God looks like and the
girl said they will in a minute.
When my son was four in England,
actually he was four everywhere to be
honest. I mean,
for being strict about it wherever he went
he was four there but he was in the
nativity play.
Do you remember the story?
No, it's big. It's a big story.
Mel Gibson at the sequel. You may have
seen it.
Nativity 2.
But James got the part of Joseph, which we
were thrilled about, we considered this to
be one of the lead parts.
We had the place crammed full of agents
and t -shirts, you know, James Robinson is
Joseph, we had.
He didn't have to speak, but do you know
the bit where the three kings come in?
Now they come in bearing gifts and they
bring gold, frankincense and metal. This
really happened, we were sitting there and
they, I think, just went out of sequence.
Because we talked to the little boy
afterward and said, you know, are you
okay with that? And they said, yeah, why
was that wrong?
They just switched, I think that was it.
Anyway, the three boys came in,
little foyers with tea towns on their
heads, and they put these boxes down and
the first boy said,
I bring you gold.
And the second boy said, I bring you mare.
And the third boy said, Frank sent this.
Ha, ha,
ha, ha, ha.
What these things have in common is that
kids will take a chance.
If they don't know,
they'll have a go.
Am I right?
They're not frightened of being wrong.
Now, I don't mean to say that being wrong
is the same thing as being creative.
What we do know is if you're not prepared
to be wrong,
you will never come up with anything
original.
If you're not prepared to be wrong,
and by the time they get to be adults,
most kids have lost that capacity.
They have become frightened of being
wrong. And we run our companies, this, by
the way, we stigmatize mistakes.
And we're now running national education
systems where mistakes are the worst thing
you can make.
And the result is that we are educating
people out of their creative capacities.
Picasso once said this, he said that all
children are born artists.
The problem is to remain an artist as we
grow up.
I believe this passionately that we don't
grow into creativity,
we grow out of it,
or rather we get educated out of it.
So why is this?
I lived in Stratford on Avon until about
five years ago. In fact, we moved from
Stratford to Los Angeles.
So you can imagine what a seamless
transition this was from.
Actually, we lived in a place called
Satterfield just outside Stratford,
which is where Shakespeare's father was
born.
Are you struck by a new thought I was?
You don't think of Shakespeare having a
father, do you?
Do you?
Because you don't think of Shakespeare
being a child.
Do you? Shakespeare being seven.
I never thought of it.
I mean, he was seven at some point, he was
in somebody's English class, wasn't he?
How annoying would that be?
break
must try harder
by
being sent to bad by Centre Shakespeare
and go to bed now to William Shakespeare
and put the pencil down and stop speaking
like that
It's confusing everybody.
Anyway, we moved from Stratford to Los
Angeles, and I just want to say a word
about the transition. My son didn't want
to come, I've got two kids, he's 21 now
and my daughter's 16. He didn't want to
come to Los Angeles, he loved it, but he
had a girlfriend in England.
This was the love of his life,
Sarah, he'd known her for a month.
Mind you, they'd had their fourth
anniversary,
because it's a long time when you're 16.
Anyway, he was really upset on the plane,
he said, I'll never find another girl like
Sarah.
And we were rather pleased about that,
frankly,
because...
Shew's the main reason we're leaving the
country.
But something strikes you when you move to
America and when you travel around the
world, every education system on Earth has
the same hierarchy of subjects.
Everyone doesn't matter where you go, you
think it would be otherwise but it isn't.
At the top are mathematics and languages,
then the humanity is in the bottom of the
arts, everywhere on Earth.
And in pretty much every system too,
there's a hierarchy within the arts.
Art and music are normally given a higher
status in schools than drama and dance.
There isn't an education system on the
planet that teaches dance every day to
children the way we teach them
mathematics.
Why?
Why not?
I think this is rather important.
I think math is very important but so is
dance. Children dance all the time if
they're allowed to, we all do. We all have
bodies, don't we?
Did I miss a meeting? I mean I think...
Truth be what happens is as children grow
up we start to educate them progressively
from the waist up.
And then we focus on their heads and
slightly to one side.
If you were to visit education as an alien
and say what's it for public education,
I think you'd have to conclude if you look
at the output.
Who really succeeds by this? Who does
everything they should?
Who gets all the brownie points?
Who are the winners?
I think you'd have to conclude the whole
purpose of public education throughout the
world is to produce university professors.
Isn't it? They're the people who come out
the top and now I used to be one.
So there.
And I like university professors but we
shouldn't hold them up as the high water
mark of all human achievement. They're
just a form of life.
Another form of life.
But they're rather curious and I say this
out of affection for them.
There's something curious about professors
in my experience, not all of them but
typically they live in their heads.
They live up there and slightly to one
side.
They're disembodied in a kind of literal
way. They look upon their body as a form
of transport for their heads.
Don't they?
It's a way of getting their head to
meetings.
If you want real evidence of out -of -body
experiences, by the way, get yourself
along to a residential conference for
senior academics and pop into the
discotheque on the final night.
There you will see it, grown men and women
writhing uncontrollably.
Off the beat
Wait until it ends so that you can go home
and write a paper about it.
Now, our education system is predicated on
the idea of academic ability.
And there's a reason.
The whole system was invented around the
world. There were no public systems of
education really before the 19th century.
They all came into being to meet the needs
of industrialism.
So the hierarchy is written on two ideas.
Number one,
that the most useful subjects for work are
at the top.
So you were probably steered benignly away
from things at school. When you were a
kid, things you liked on the ground, you
would never get a job doing that.
Is that right?
Don't do music, you're not going to be a
musician. Don't do art, you won't be an
artist.
Benign advice,
now profoundly mistaken.
The whole world is engulfed in a
revolution.
And the second is academic ability, which
has really come to dominate our view of
intelligence because the universities
designed the system in their image.
If you think about it, the whole system of
public education around the world is a
protracted process of university entrance.
And the consequence is that many highly
talented, brilliant, created people think
they're not.
Because the thing they were good at
school wasn't valued or was actually
Stigmatized.
And I think we can't afford to go on that
way.
In the next 30 years, according to UNESCO,
more people worldwide will be graduating
through education than since the beginning
of history.
More people.
And it's the combination of all the things
we've talked about, technology and its
transformation effect on work and
demography and the huge explosion in
population.
Suddenly, degrees aren't worth anything.
Isn't that true?
When I was a student,
if you had a degree, you had a job. If you
didn't have a job, it's because you didn't
want one.
And I didn't want one, frankly.
But now kids with degrees are often
heading home to carry on playing video
games because you need an MA, where the
previous job required a BA and now you
need a PhD for the other. It's a process
of academic inflation and it indicates the
whole structure of education is shifting
beneath our feet.
We need to radically rethink our view of
intelligence.
We know three things about intelligence.
One, it's diverse.
We think about the world in all the ways
that we experience it. We think visually,
we think in sound, we think
kinesthetically,
we think in abstract terms, we think in
movement.
Secondly,
intelligence is dynamic.
If you look at the interactions of a human
brain, as we heard yesterday from a number
of presentations,
intelligence is wonderfully interactive.
The brain isn't divided into compartments.
In fact, creativity, which I define as the
process of having original ideas that have
value,
more often than not, comes about through
the interaction of different disciplinary
ways of seeing things.
The brain is intentional. By the way,
there's a shaft of nerves that joins the
brain,
called the corpus callosum. It's thicker
in women.
Following on from Helen yesterday, I think
this is probably why women are better at
multitasking.
Because you are, aren't you? There's a
raft of research,
but I know of my personal life.
If my wife is cooking a meal at home,
which is not often,
thankfully,
you know, if she's...
no make 'n gobeitadol. On dos psych in
Change, make ES in gall mangos
receiver felly chi 'n died make 'n beach
In mangos bob y main new 'n tiki, make
In gall 'n mangos bob y main new 'n
Ill make 'n gall 'n. DWI 'n gyfrwyscaf
Going yes medley.
OND make 'n medley i 'r fired, make 'r tad
In y fool, make 'n gyfrwyscaf, make 'r
Front 'r which a 'r Lee a gnathic, make 'n
Goal in. Rwy 'n gnathic, Very please, I'm
trying to fry an egg in here, you know.
Thank you.
Give me a break?
Do you know that old philosophical thing?
If a tree falls in a forest and nobody
hears it, did it happen?
Remember that old chestnut?
I saw a great t -shirt really recently
which said,
if a man speaks his mind in a forest and
no woman hears him, is he still wrong?
And the third thing about intelligence is
it's distinct.
I'm doing a new book at the moment called
Epiphany, which is based on a series of
interviews with people about how they
discovered their talent.
I'm fascinated by how people got to be
there.
It's really prompted by a conversation I
had with a wonderful woman who most people
have never heard of. She's called Gillian
Lynn. Have you heard of her?
Some have.
She's a choreographer and everybody knows
her work. She did Cat and Phantom of the
Opera. She's wonderful. I used to be on
the board of the Royal Ballet in England,
as you can see.
Anyway,
Gillian had lunch on that. I said, how'd
you get to be a dancer?
And she said it was interesting. When she
was at school, she was really hopeless.
The school in the 30s wrote to her parents
and said, we think Gillian has a learning
disorder.
You couldn't concentrate. She was
fidgeting. I think now they say she had
ADHD.
Wouldn't you?
But this was the 1930s and ADHD hadn't
been invented at this point. So it wasn't
an available condition. People weren't
aware they could have that.
Anyway, she went to see this specialist.
She said this oak panel room and she was
there with her mother. She was led and sat
on this chair at the end. She sat on her
hands for 20 minutes while this man talked
to her mother about all the problems
Gillian was having at school.
At the end of it,
because she was disturbing, people at home
work was always late and so on, a little
kid of eight,
in the end the doctor went and sat next to
Gillian and said, Gillian, I've listened
to all these things that your mother's
told me. I need to speak to her privately.
So she said,
wait here, we'll be back. We won't be very
long and they went and left her.
But as they went out of the room, he
turned on the radio that was sitting on
his desk.
When they got out of the room, he said to
her mother, just stand and watch her.
And the minute they left the room,
she said she was on her feet, moving to
the music.
And they watched for a few minutes and he
turned to her mother and he said, you
know, Mrs Lynn,
Gillian isn't sick,
she's a dancer.
Take her to a dance school.
I said, what happened?
He said she did.
I can't tell you how wonderful it was. We
walked in this room and it was full of
people like me.
People who couldn't sit still.
People who had to move to think.
Who had to move to think?
They did ballet,
they did tap, they did jazz, they did
modern, they did contemporary. She was
eventually auditioned for the Royal Ballet
School.
She became a soloist. She had a wonderful
career at the Royal Ballet.
She eventually graduated from the Royal
Ballet School, found her own company, the
Gillian Dance Company,
met Andrew Lloyd Webber. She's been
responsible for some of the successful
musical theater productions in history.
She's given pleasure to millions and she's
a multimillionaire.
Somebody else might have put on medication
and told it to calm down.
Ac make 'n good Hanna 'n gyred i 'w
Medal i 'r need MA. Yr moon Cyril
Dawn o sick o 'r each cyanide i 'r moon
gwirionedd MA
SY 'n Cyril dawn o Rachael Carson.
Felly, Rwy 'n medal i 'r Ford YM Maya,
YW 'n medal i 'w medal i 'r each
Cyril i 'r biathlon Cyril. Mae 'n
Medal i 'n medal i 'r medal i 'r
Biathlon Cyril i 'r held. ymyfyrdd
ymyfyrdd GYD 'r Lyford.
Mae 'n Lyford MA AR y synodal. A 'r
Storied in a fyrd.
Mae 'n Lyford ymlaenwyr day new 'n
Gnathic 'r Cullen ffrindiau OND make 'r
Han YW 'r cyfrifiadau.
In y CWP ddiweddai 'r unshy YW 'r
ysgrifennu, YW AR 50 yrs amaranth o 'n
Amaranth. y gallon.
If all human beings disappeared from the
earth,
within 50 years, all forms of life would
flourish.
And he's right.
What Ted celebrates is the gift of the
human imagination.
We have to be careful now that we use this
gift wisely
and that we avert some of the scenarios
that we've talked about. And the only way
we'll do it is by seeing our creative
capacities for the richness they are
and seeing our children for the hope that
they are.
And our task is to educate their whole
being so they can face this future. By the
way, we may not see this future,
but they will.
And our job is to help them make something
of it.
Thank you very much.
What if great ideas weren't cherished?
What if they carried no importance?
Or held no value?
There is a place where artistic vision is
protected, where inspired design ideas
live on to become ultimate driving
machines.