Hi, everyone.
Two years ago,
my life changed forever.
My wife, Kelsey, and I welcomed our
daughter, Leila, into the world.
Now becoming a parent is an amazing,
amazing experience. Your whole world
changes overnight, and all of your
priorities change immediately. So fast
that it makes it really difficult to
process sometimes.
Now, you also have to learn a tremendous
amount about being a parent. Like, for
example,
how to dress your child.
This was new to me.
This is an actual outfit. I thought this
was a good idea.
And even Leila knows that it's not a good
idea.
So there was so much to learn and so much
craziness all at once.
And to add to the craziness,
Kelsey and I both work from home. We're
entrepreneurs. We run our own businesses.
So Kelsey develops courses online for yoga
teachers.
I'm an author.
And so I'm working for home. Kelsey's
working for home. We have an infant.
And we're trying to make sure that
everything gets done, that needs to be done.
And life is really, really, really busy.
And a couple of weeks into this amazing
experience, when the sleep deprivation
really kicked in, like around week eight,
I had this thought.
And it was the same thought that parents
crossed the ages internationally.
Everybody has had this thought, which is,
I am never going to have free time ever
again.
And somebody said it's true.
Yeah, it's not exactly true, but it feels
really, really true at that moment.
And this was really disconcerting to me
because one of the things that I enjoy
more than anything else is learning new
things.
Getting curious about something and diving
in and fiddling around and learning
through trial and error and eventually
becoming pretty good at something.
And without this free time,
I didn't know how I was ever going to do
that ever again.
And so I'm a big geek.
I want to keep learning things. I want to
keep growing.
And so what I decided to do was go to the
library and go to the bookstore. And look
at what research says about how we learn
and how we learn quickly.
And I read a bunch of books.
I read a bunch of websites.
And trying to answer this question, how
long does it take to acquire a new skill?
You know what I found?
Ten thousand hours.
Anybody ever heard this?
Ten thousand. It takes ten thousand hours.
If you want to learn something new, if you
want to be good at it, it's going to take
ten thousand hours to get there. And I
read this in book after book and website
after website.
And my mental experience of reading all of
this stuff was like, no!
I don't have time. I don't have ten
a thousand hours.
I am never going to be able to learn
anything new ever again.
But that's not true. So ten thousand hours
just to give you a rough order of
magnitude. Ten thousand hours is a full
time job for five years.
That's a long time.
And we've all had the experience of
learning something new. And it didn't take
us anywhere close to that amount of time,
right?
So what's up? There's something kind of
funky going on here. What the research
says and what we expect and have
experiences,
they don't match up.
And what I found,
here's the wrinkle. The ten thousand hours
rule came out of studies of expert level
performance.
There was a professor at Florida State
University. His name is Kaye Anders
Erickson. He's the originator of the ten
thousand-hour rule.
And where that came from is he studied
professional athletes,
world-class musicians,
chess grandmasters, all of these ultra
competitive folks in ultra-high performing
fields. And he tried to figure out how
long does it take to get to the top of
those kinds of fields. And what he found
is the more deliberate practice, the more
time that those individuals spent
practicing the elements, whatever it is
that they do,
the more time you spend, the better you
get. And the folks at the hippy top of
their fields put in around ten thousand
hours of practice.
Now, we're talking about the game of
telephone a little bit earlier.
Here's what happened.
An author by the name of Malcolm Gladwell
wrote a book in 2007 called Outliers, the
story of success.
And the centerpiece of that book was the
ten thousand-hour rule.
Practice a lot, practice well,
and you will do extremely well. You reach
the top of your field.
So the message, what Dr.
Erickson was actually saying is it takes
ten thousand hours to get to the top of an
ultra competitive field in a very narrow
subject.
That's what that means.
But here's what happened. Ever since
Outliers came out,
immediately came out, reached the top of
the bestseller list, stayed there for
three solid months.
All of a sudden the ten thousand-hour rule
was everywhere.
And a society wide game of telephone
started to be played.
So this message, it takes ten thousand
hours to reach the top of an ultra
competitive field became,
it takes ten thousand hours to become an
expert at something.
Which became, it takes ten thousand hours
to become good at something. Which became,
it takes ten thousand hours to learn
something.
But that last statement, it takes ten
a thousand hours to learn something,
it's not true.
It's not true.
So,
what the research actually says, if I
spent a lot of time here at the CSU
library in the cognitive psychology stacks
because I'm a geek,
and when you actually look at the studies
of skill acquisition,
you see over and over and over a graph
like this.
Now, researchers, whether they're studying
a motor skill,
something you do physically or a mental
skill,
they like to study things that they can
time,
because you can quantify that, right?
So, they'll give research participants a
little task, something that requires
physical arrangement or something that
requires learning a little mental trick,
and they'll time how long a participant
takes to complete the skill.
And here's what this graph says. When you
start, so when researchers gave
participants a task, it took them a really
long time because it was new and they were
horrible.
With a little bit of practice,
they get better and better and better, and
that early part of practice is really,
really efficient. People get good at
things with just a little bit of practice.
Now, what's interesting to note is that
if, you know, we don't really, for skills
that we want to learn for ourselves,
we don't care so much about time, right?
We just care about how good we are,
whatever good happens to mean.
So, if we relabel performance time to how
good you are,
the graph flips,
and you get this famous and widely known,
this is the learning curve.
And the story of the learning curve is
when you start,
you're grossly incompetent and you know
it,
right?
With a little bit of practice,
you get perfect really quick, so that
early level of improvement is really fast.
And then at a certain point, you reach a
plateau and the subsequent gains become
much harder to get. They take more time to
get.
Now,
my question is, I want that,
right?
How long does it take from starting
something and being grossly incompetent
and knowing it to being reasonably good in
hopefully a short period of time as
possible?
So how long does that take?
Here's what my research says,
20 hours,
that's it.
You can go from knowing nothing about any
skill that you can think of.
Want to learn a language?
Want to learn how to draw?
Want to learn how to juggle flaming
chainsaws?
If you put 20 hours of focused, deliberate
practice into that thing, you will be
astounded,
astounded at how good you are.
20 hours is doable, that's about 45
minutes a day for about a month, even
skipping a couple of days here and there. 20
hours aren't that hard to accumulate.
Now, there's a method to doing this,
because it's not like you can just start
fiddling around for about 20 hours and
expect these massive improvements. There's
a way to practice intelligently.
There's a way to practice efficiently that
will make sure that you invest those 20
hours
in the most effective way that you
possibly can.
And here's the method, it applies to
anything.
The first is to deconstruct the skill,
decide exactly what you want to be able to
do when you're done,
and then look into the skill and break it
down into smaller and smaller pieces.
Most of the things that we think of as
skills are actually big bundles of skills
that require all sorts of different
things. The more you can break apart the
skill,
the more you're able to decide what are
the parts of the skill that will actually
help me get to what I want,
and then you can practice those first.
And if you practice the most important
things first, you'll be able to improve
your performance
in the least amount of time possible.
The second is learned enough to self
-correct.
So get three to five resources about what
it is you're trying to learn, could be
books, could be DVDs, courses, could be
anything,
but don't use those as a way to
procrastinate on practice. I know I do
this, right?
Get like 20 books about the topic, it's
like, I'm going to start learning how to
program
a computer when I complete these 20 books.
No,
that's procrastination.
What you want to do is learn just enough
that you can actually practice and self
-correct
or self -edit as you practice.
So the learning becomes a way of getting
better at noticing when you're making a
mistake and then doing something a little
different.
The third is to remove barriers to
practice,
distractions,
television,
internet,
all of these things that get in the way of
you're actually sitting down and doing the
work.
And the more you're able to use just a
a little bit of willpower to remove the
distractions that are keeping you from
practicing,
the more likely you are to actually sit
down and practice.
And the fourth is to practice for at least
20 hours.
Now, most skills have what I call a
frustration barrier,
you know, the grossly incompetent knowing
its part,
that's really, really frustrating. We
don't like to feel stupid.
And feeling stupid is a barrier to us
actually sitting down and doing the work.
So by pre -committing to practicing
whatever it is that you want to do for at
least 20 hours,
you will be able to overcome that initial
frustration barrier and stick with the
practice long enough to actually reap the
rewards,
right? That's it. It's not rocket science.
It's four very simple steps that you can
use to learn anything.
Now, this is easier to talk about in
theory,
but it's more fun to talk about in
practice.
So one of the things that I've wanted to
learn how to do for a long time is play
the ukulele.
As anybody seeing Jake Shimabukuro's TED
Talk where he plays the ukulele and makes
it sounds like he's like a ukulele god.
It's amazing.
It's like, I saw that. It's like, that is
so cool. It's such a neat instrument. I
would really like to learn how to play.
And so I decided that to test this theory,
I wanted to put 20 hours into practicing
the ukulele and see where we got.
And so the first thing about playing the
ukulele is in order to practice,
you have to have one,
right?
So I got a ukulele and my lovely
assistant.
Thank you, sir.
I think I need the cord here.
It's not just a ukulele. It's an electric
ukulele,
yeah.
So the first couple of hours are just like
the first couple of hours of anything. You
have to get the tools that you're using to
practice. You have to make sure that
they're available.
My ukulele didn't come with strings
attached. I had to figure out how to put
those on. Like, that's kind of important,
right?
And learning how to tune and learning how
to make sure that all the things that
need to be done in order to start
practicing get done, right?
Now, one of the things when I was ready to
actually start practicing was I looked in
online databases and song books for how to
play songs. And they say, okay,
ukuleles, you can play more than one
string at a time, so you can play chords.
That's cool. You're accompanying yourself.
Yeah, you.
And when I started looking at songs,
I had a ukulele chord book. They had like
hundreds of chords. It was like looking at
the same thing, like, whoa, that's
intimidating.
But when you look at the actual songs,
you see the same chords over and over,
right?
As it turns out,
playing the ukulele is kind of like doing
anything. There's a very small set of
things that are really important and
techniques that you'll use all the time.
And so in most songs, you'll use four,
maybe five chords, and that's it. That's
the song. You don't have to know the
hundreds as long as you know the four or
the five.
So while I was doing my research, I found
a wonderful little medley of pop songs by
a band called Axis of Awesome.
And somebody knows it.
And what Axis of Awesome says is that you
can learn or you can play pretty much any
pop song of the past five decades if you
know four chords. And those chords are G,
D,
D minor,
C.
Four chords pump out every pop song ever,
right?
So I thought this is cool. I would like to
play every pop song ever. So that was the
first song I decided to learn and would
like to actually share it with you. Ready?
All right.
Just a small town girl living in a lonely
world.
She took a midnight train going anywhere.
I heard that you settled down,
that you found a girl, that you're married
now.
Every night in my dreams, I see you, I
feel you. That's just how I know we'll go
on.
I won't hesitate any more, no more, it's
cannot wait, I'm yours, because you are
amazing.
We did amazing things, if I could,
then I would go wherever you were.
Can you feel the love tonight?
Live with or without you
When I find myself, find myself in times
of trouble Mother Mary comes to me
partner no woman no crap I'm on the show
Lee is a dream I come from London under
once a jolly swag man cams by a billabong
hey I just met you and this is crazy
here's my number
Hey
Len he hop, hop, hop, hop long Kai
Long Kai Alright, I'm done
Say goodbye
Closing time
Every new beginning comes from some other
beginnings and
I love that song.
And I have a secret to share with you.
So by playing that song for you,
I just hit my 20th hour of practicing the
ukulele.
Thank you.
And so it's amazing, pretty much anything
that you can think of.
What do you want to do?
The major barrier to learning something
new is not intellectual.
It's not the process of you learning a
bunch of little tips or tricks or things.
The major barrier is emotional.
We're scared.
Feeling stupid doesn't feel good in the
beginning of learning anything new. You
feel really stupid.
So the major barrier is not intellectual.
It's emotional.
But put 20 hours into anything.
Doesn't matter. What do you want to learn?
You want to learn language?
You want to learn how to cook?
You want to learn how to draw?
What turns you on? What lights you up?
Go out and do that thing. It only takes 20
hours.
Have fun.
Great job.