Today I want to tell you three stories
from my life. That's it. No big deal.
Just three stories.
The first story is about connecting the
dots.
I dropped out of Reed College after the
first six months but then stayed around as
a drop -in for another 18 months or so
before I really quit.
So why'd I drop out?
It started before I was born.
My biological mother was a young unwed
graduate student and she decided to put me
up for adoption.
She felt very strongly that I should be
adopted by college graduates so everything
was all set for me to be adopted at birth
by a lawyer and his wife.
Except that when I popped out they decided
at the last minute that they really wanted
a girl.
So my parents who were on a waiting list
got a call in the middle of the night
asking,
we've got an unexpected baby boy. Do you
want him?
They said,
of course.
My biological mother found out later that
my mother had never graduated from college
and that my father had never graduated
from high school.
She refused to sign the final adoption
papers.
She only relented a few months later when
my parents promised that I would go to
college.
This was the start in my life.
And 17 years later I did go to college but
I naively chose a college that was almost
as expensive as Stanford and all of my
working class parents' savings were being
spent on my college tuition.
After six months I couldn't see the value
in it.
I had no idea what I wanted to do with my
life and no idea how college was going to
help me figure it out.
And here I was spending all the money my
parents had saved their entire life.
So I decided to drop out and trust that it
would all work out okay.
It was pretty scary at the time but
looking back it was one of the best
decisions I ever made.
The minute I dropped out I could stop
taking the required classes that didn't
interest me and begin dropping in on the
ones that looked far more interesting.
It wasn't all romantic.
I didn't have a dorm room, so I slept on
the floor in friends rooms.
I returned Coke bottles for the five cent
deposits to buy food with and I would walk
the seven miles across town every Sunday
night to get one good meal a week at the
Hard Krishna temple.
I loved it and much of what I stumbled
into by following my curiosity and
intuition turned out to be priceless later
on.
Let me give you one example.
Reed College at that time offered perhaps
the best calligraphy instruction in the
country.
Throughout the campus every poster every
label on every drawer was beautifully hand
Calligrapher.
Because I had dropped out and didn't have
to take the normal classes I decided to
take a calligraphy class to learn how to
do this.
I learned about serif and sans serif
typefaces about varying the amount of
space between different letter
combinations about what makes great
typography great.
It was beautiful historical artistically
subtle in a way that science can't capture
and I found it fascinating.
None of this had even a hope of any
practical application in my life.
But 10 years later when we were designing
the first Macintosh computer it all came
back to me and we designed it all into the
Mac.
It was the first computer with beautiful
typography.
If I had never dropped in on that single
course in college the Mac would have never
had multiple typefaces or proportionally
spaced fonts and since Windows just copied
the Mac it's likely that no personal
computer would have them.
If I had never dropped out I would have
never dropped in on that calligraphy class
and personal computers might not have the
wonderful typography that they do.
Of course, it was impossible to connect the
dots looking forward when I was in college
but it was very, very clear looking
backwards 10 years later.
Again you can't connect the dots looking
forward you can only connect them looking
backwards so you have to trust that the
dots will somehow connect in your future.
You have to trust in something your gut
destiny life karma whatever
because believing that the dots will
connect down the road will give you the
confidence to follow your heart even when
it leads you off the well-worn path and
that will make all the difference.
My second story is about love and loss.
I was lucky I found what I love to do
early in life.
Was and I started Apple in my parents
garage when I was 20.
We worked hard and in 10 years Apple had
grown from just the two of us in a garage
into a two billion dollar company with
over four thousand employees.
We just released our finest creation the
Macintosh a year earlier and I just turned
and then I got fired.
How can you get fired from a company you
started?
Well as Apple grew we hired someone who I
thought was very talented to run the
company with me and for the first year or
so things went well but then our visions
of the future began to diverge and
eventually we had a falling out.
When we did our board of directors sided
with him and so at 30 I was out
and very publicly out.
What had been the focus of my entire adult
life was gone and it was devastating.
I really didn't know what to do for a few
months.
I felt that I had let the previous
generation of entrepreneurs down that I
had dropped the baton as it was being
passed to me.
I met with David Packard and Bob Noyce and
tried to apologize for screwing up so
badly.
I was a very public failure and I even
thought about running away from the valley
but something slowly began to dawn on me.
I still loved what I did.
The turn of events at Apple had not
changed that one bit.
I'd been rejected but I was still in love
and so I decided to start over.
I didn't see it then but it turned out
that getting fired from Apple was the best
thing that could have ever happened to me.
The heaviness of being successful was
replaced by the lightness of being a
beginner again less sure about everything.
It freed me to enter one of the most
creative periods of my life.
During the next five years I started a
company named NEXT another company named
Pixar and fell in love with an amazing
woman who would become my wife.
Pixar went on to create the world's first
computer animated feature film Toy Story
and is now the most successful animation
studio in the world.
In a remarkable turn of events Apple
bought NEXT and I returned to Apple and
the technology we developed at NEXT is at
the heart of Apple's current renaissance
and Doreen and I have a wonderful family
together.
I'm pretty sure none of this would have
happened if I hadn't been fired from
Apple.
It was awful tasting medicine but I guess
the patient needed it.
Sometimes life's going to
hit you in the head with a brick.
Don't lose faith.
I'm convinced that the only thing that
kept me going was that I loved what I did.
You've got to find what you love and that
is as true for work as it is for your
lovers.
Your work is going to fill a large part of
your life and the only way to be truly
satisfied is to do what you believe is
great work and the only way to do great
work is to love what you do.
If you haven't found it yet keep looking
and don't settle as with all matters of
the heart you'll know when you find it and
like any great relationship it just gets
better and better as the years roll on so
keep looking don't settle.
My third story is about death.
When I was 17 I read a quote that went
something like
if you live each day as if it was your
last someday you'll most certainly be
right.
It made an impression on me and since then
for the past 33 years I've looked in the
mirror every morning and asked myself if
today were the last day of my life what I
want to do what I am about to do today and
whenever the answer has been no for too
many days in a row
I know I need to change something
remembering that all be dead soon is the
most important tool I've ever encountered
to help me make the big choices in life
because almost everything
all external expectations all pride all
fear of embarrassment or failure these
things just fall away in the face of death
leaving only what is truly important
remembering that you are going to die is
the best way I know to avoid the trap of
thinking you have something to lose you
are already naked there is no reason not
to follow your heart no one wants to die
even people who want to go to heaven don't
want to die to get there and yet death is
the destination
share.
No one has ever escaped it.
And that is as it should be, because death
is very likely the single best invention
of life.
It's life's change agent. It clears out
the old to make way for the new.
Right now, the new is you.
But someday, not too long from now, you
will gradually become the old and be
cleared away.
Sorry to be so dramatic, but it's quite
true.
Your time is limited,
so don't waste it living someone else's
life.
Don't be trapped by dogma, which is living
with the results of other people's
thinking.
Don't let the noise of others' opinions
drown out your own inner voice.
And most important,
have the courage to follow your heart and
intuition.
They somehow already know what you truly
want to become.
Everything else is secondary.
Stay hungry.
Stay foolish.
Welcome, everyone. It's my pleasure to
welcome all of you to Professor David
Patterson's talk.
David Patterson probably needs no
introduction.
He's been a professor of computer science
at University of California Berkeley for
40 years now.
And he's made a lot of pioneering
contributions in computer systems, a lot
of which are technologies we use at Google
and elsewhere. So risk,
reduced instructions at computers,
RAID network of workstations and a lot
more.
He has a pretty long bio here.
I didn't realize he has won 35 awards, and
all of them are pretty prestigious.
National Academy of Engineering, National
Academy of Sciences, Silicon Valley
Engineering, all fame,
IEEE 1 -9 in medal.
And I'm sure I'm offending some
significant award by not saying that, but
he's had a very distinguished career.
And this talk today, in his own words,
collects advice that I wish had been given
when I started my career. And given how
distinguished that's been, I think it's
the talk we are all going to benefit from.
So welcome. Well,
this is what happened is I decided,
somebody wrote me these slides about how
to have a bad career been out there for a
long time. And they asked me if there was
a video of it, and I couldn't find one. I
actually figured out that I gave this talk
first 20 years ago, but I've given it over
the years. So I decided to record it at
Berkeley,
and it ended up, and I announced that my
plan is to retire two days before this. So
it got a lot of visibility, and it's fun
to come here.
As far as I can tell, all of my former
students are going to end up here
sometime.
I also have to ask them if they're leaving
where they are. I know where they're
ending up, and it feels like it's open
home week here.
As I said, this is the advice I wish I
would have had in my career.
This got started about 30 years ago.
I decided I wanted to give advice on talk,
so I wrote how to give a bad talk.
And that was a lot of fun, and about 10
years later, how to have a bad career.
And about a couple of years ago, I did how
to have a bad research center. So this is
my bad series.
Now,
I'm just going to put the
if you're interested,
these slides are certainly available as
well as the talk. And there's a lot of
papers and things that you can cite if you
want to read more about it. And I'd like
to thank a bunch of people for making
suggestions that I've incorporated or
their careers inspired them. One of those
two.
So the parts, there are two parts to the
talk. The kind of tongue -in -cheek, how
to have a bad career, and then how to
avoid a bad career. And then I'll open up
for questions and answers.
And then I'll wrap things up whenever we
have to wrap things up and take the last
five or ten minutes talking about my
story,
how I got here, and what works for me. So
you want to be a leader of the field,
especially if you're an academia.
So how can you do that? Well, invent a new
field is a perfect way to do that.
And you want to be the only person on that
field, so how can you invent a field and
be the only person?
Well, one way is, you know, different from
other fields, you want to be the lone
ranger. And the way you can be the lone
ranger, the only one that is there, is
your personality can help.
If you adopt the prima donna personality,
and some people don't know who a prima
Donna is, but if you adopt that
personality, nobody will want to work with
you, and you can drive people away and
then you'll be the world's leading expert
because you're the only one in that field.
In terms of the research horizons for your
new field, you might have a lot of
flexibility on success.
You know, you don't want to get too fine.
And if you say it's 20 years out, then,
you know, you've got 19 safe years, right?
And nobody's going to accuse you of doing
engineering work if it's 20 years out.
And, you know, stick to that topic for
your whole career. Now, if I'd only
followed that advice, my dissertation was
on microprogramming.
If I'd stuck to this, I would absolutely
be the world's expert in micro
-programming, partly because no one's
built a computer with microcode in 25
years.
And you kind of think of it like, it's
like fashion, you know, like skinny jeans
are popular now, or they were popular 25
years ago. If you just kept them, you
could reuse your own jeans. So, research
is like that. Wait,
I'll come back to you.
Okay,
let complexity be your guide.
Confuse my enemies.
The best thing you can say is so
complicated, I can't understand what
you're talking about. Now, that's, you've
done a good job.
One reason is it's easy to claim credit
for things. If somebody else has done some
work, you can say, well, that was in my
paper, and since they don't understand it,
how can they contradict you, right?
The other thing that's surprising is it's
really a lot easier to be complicated. You
read the first end papers, and then it's,
you figure out the next one, and people
publish it. It's really much harder to be
simpler than it'd be complicated, so
that's the easy way to do it.
And this sentence captures it, right? If
it's UN -simple, how could you send your
colleagues to departments around the
world, be possibly appreciative, and so on
and so on. There you go. That's the way to
speak and to talk.
Never be proven wrong. The first thing you
want to do is don't implement anything.
It's hard to prove you wrong if you don't
implement it. Now, if some other control
colleague builds something, then whatever
you do, don't run any quantitative
experiments.
If they're not quantitative, then you
can't be proven wrong.
You've got the intuition.
You can just kind of extrapolate with
results that are put that in without any
experiment.
And, you know, your job isn't to help the
critics. You know, that's their job to
figure out.
Don't help them out. Now,
another reason is that clearly the success
of the career is to publish as much as you
can, and it takes time to build and to
measure. So if you don't do that, you can
get more results and have a more
successful career.
If somebody does it, the last thing you
want to do is run any benchmarks because
then they can compare your results to
other things.
The advice of being that you've got those
safe years, and the benchmarks can just,
the way you get out of that is to say,
well, this computer is for future
programs, not for current programs, and
then these benchmarks are too antiquated
to run on my computer.
Now, the other thing that we do in
computer science is we eject all the past.
You know, we're a new field for both
science and engineering, so we're not
hidebound by old-fashioned things like
the scientific method. We have the
computer scientific method. Instead of a
hypothesis,
we have a hunch.
A sequence of experiments, we know that
sequential is slow, so what we do,
we change one experiment all the
parameters at once. That's much faster
than the sequential approach. Parallelism
is a good idea.
And rather than prove or disprove a
hypothesis,
we discard if it doesn't support the
hunch, you know?
There's lots of data, it's a big data,
throw away the data, there's still plenty
of data left.
And document for others to reproduce,
we've already done it. We'll have more
results in the field if we don't waste our
time trying to reproduce each other's
results. That's the computer scientific
method.
Don't be distracted by others, avoid
feedback.
You know, a big part of that is
conversation,
and if you don't say anything, people
might think you're not very smart, so the
corollary of that is loud as smart, okay?
So be loud in conversations, even when you
don't know what you're talking about.
People will think you know what you're
talking about.
If you're the words -eluding expert, you
don't really need to read other things,
because you're the expert, right?
And you don't have to be interacted with
others, because they're not as good as you
are.
In terms of doing reviews for paper, if
it's simple and obvious,
it'd be insult the prior authors if you
accepted something simple and obvious,
they probably thought of it so you should
reject it.
If they're quantitative results, and I've
gotten this review before, well I already
knew that, so there's no surprise to
reject it, and just, you know, everything
else you might as well just reject.
You know, they're kind of competitors to
you in some way, and if they don't get
published, then you win, so that's a good
guideline.
Now, publishing journals is technology
transfer. You're the leading person in the
world, you're the expert, all you have to
do is write in the journal. It's not your
job to make it understandable to others
and to ordinary engineers.
Going to conferences, just waste some of
your valuable time that you could be
coming up with new ideas,
and, you know, having to interact with
industry and things like that, that's the
time waste, you write the journals,
you're done.
Now, clearly the winner is the one with
the most papers at the end of the career,
so I've come up with this pyramid of
success for publication that follows the
rule of four.
And the guideline is the CPU, least
publishing unit, the CPU is good for you.
So you start off with one idea, then with
rule of four, you get four journal papers
out of that,
with the miracle of world processing, then
you can get 16 extended abstracts and 64
technical reports from what's a single
idea. That's 84 publications,
I guess that. And then in terms of getting
credit for it, my advice is to change your
name to the Swedish spelling of Anderson.
And then there's awkward time, oh, how are
we're going to put the office on the table?
You will say, well, I've always done it
alphabetically.
All my papers there. All right.
Writing commandments for a bad career.
Valschelt not defined terms, that's what
dictionaries are before, and explaining
things, that'll just insult the reader, so
you want to be a little bit more
mysterious than that.
Valschelt use,
replace I will build with I have been
built.
You know, probably by the time your paper
gets published in a journal, somebody will
have implemented it, so it's okay to kind
of do that.
Valschelt not mentioned drawbacks to your
report,
that's not your job, that's the job of the
critics to figure out drawbacks.
You know, if you hide that, they'll never
notice it.
Valschelt not reference any papers, again,
except for maybe your own, or your
institution, and if the papers were any
good, they'd be people at your
institution, so don't do that.
And then you should publish before
implementing, because that's when your
system is the fastest.
Okay,
talk commandments for a bad career, this
is my bad career talk.
Valschelt not be neat,
you know, why take the time to spend it on
your slides to fix spelling errors,
grammatical errors, you could spend that
time on research.
Valschelt not waste space, you know, you
use up a lot of slides, that's a lot of
kilobytes being wasted there, you can save
like 100 kilobytes a year, which saves
some money.
Valschelt not covet brevity, do you really
want to sustain
the stereotype that engineers can't write,
right? You want to show full paragraphs,
beautiful English, and read it aloud.
Valschelt cover the naked slides, I'll
show you what I mean by that later, but
you don't want to expose the whole slide
to everybody and shock them.
Valschelt not print large,
the important people sit in the front,
right?
So, who cares about the guys in the back?
Valschelt not use color,
use of color indicates,
you know, unfearful research, you're
emphasizing some words over others and
it's just to show a used color.
Valschelt not illustrate, Confucius says,
pictures worth 10, 000 words, who cares
about the wisdom of the ages, right?
And Valschelt not make eye contact, you
want to be humble, kind of pretend to be
humble, keep your eyes down, and you know,
try not to let anybody see you.
Valschelt not skip slides long talk, I
guarantee in this room somebody has done,
looked up, looked at their watch, see how
many slides they have, and their solution
is, I'll just talk faster, right? That's
what people do, you prepare the slides,
they want to see them all, and if you have
to, just cut off the conclusions, the last
couple of slides if you're out of time.
And then this is the golden rule, this one
can save you,
even if you violate the others, Valschelt
not practice. How can you be spontaneous
if you practice?
It'll feel practiced if you practice. So
don't do that, that's the last thing you
should do.
So here's an example of doing it, it
actually says PowerPoint, but it's using
Google Slides,
so try on these commandments.
So, put small.
Now these features, somebody, some
engineer at Google put these features in,
so you have to use them to be a good
Google employee.
So you want to hide your naked slides
there, that's some variety,
but again, no use of color.
There you go, that's another dramatic
entrance.
And then this last, the next one is just
my favorite, I'm glad somebody put the
time in to put this in, because it's very
useful.
There you go.
Okay, so that was the bad career advice,
let's talk about Alternatives Career.
This is taken from my career,
which spanned 40 years, so it's kind of an
academic, I hope it'll apply to you here.
It's in systems, not in theory.
And I'll go through these pieces one by
one. So advice to writing bad papers,
and I put some writing tips there, the
writing tips actually have some
grammatical errors in them following my
bad tradition, but you can go take a look.
So do the opposite of the bad paper
commandments.
Do define your terms, distinguish will do
from have done. If you're writing for
critical review, reviewers are very
skeptical people, they're going to assume
the worst.
They are much more impressed if you point
out the drawbacks rather than they have to
discover them.
And you have to measure performance and
reference the work to be a scholar.
And the good news is, you guys build a
wonderful service to make that much easier
to do these days and help the scholar.
The best piece of advice I ever got was to
read Struck and White.
Struck believed in brevity so much, he
cherished brevity so much, he couldn't
write a long book.
The book itself is maybe 80 pages or so,
and it's chock-full of good advice.
Then we do this, the advice is basically
you go kind of top down.
You write a one-page outline with a
tentative title
with budgets, how much you need to write,
a lot of writing, that saves a lot of
writing if you don't have to do it.
Then a paragraph map, which is a topic
sentence,
as it goes the way through,
and it includes figures and captions. Even
today in 2016, it takes forever on a
computer to draw a figure.
And since you might throw that, you'll
probably throw that figure right here,
change it. The best technology to do that
today is gone to a whiteboard, you can have
colored pens, take a little cell phone
picture and stick that in your document,
that'll take you one tenth of the time as
trying to do something on a computer,
because you might throw it away.
And then we write the draft.
I like the Scientific American style,
which has really long captions, not
everybody does that, but you can move text
in there and associate with the figure. I
think that works well. I really like
tables a lot, there's a lot of dreary
facts, I love putting them into tables,
that works well for me.
Then in terms of when you're starting to
polish the text, read aloud. Your ear is
better than your eyes. When I start
reading a document, and I forget and I
stop saying it out loud, I lose track, but
if you hear the word, you can hear
terrible sentences and grammatical errors,
if you hear it.
There's technology.
In fact, I just learned about this thing.
It was from an English professor who
taught a massive open -op line course at
Berkeley. He said, why aren't you using a
grammar checker? And she said, this is the
world's best one, Pearson writer.
And it costs you a whole $20 a year and
it'll prevent terrible grammatical errors
and it'll even help style. In fact, I was
thinking,
you guys should buy this.
It's one of the things you're missing from
Google Documents. And this is the world's
best one.
I'm impressed that they can pull this off.
And then you get feedbacks and friends. Of
course, to get feedbacks and friends, if
you're writing to a deadline, you actually
have to get it done early,
which seems to be science fiction for
graduate students at least.
But you get it done early, then it gives
you time to give your friends feedback.
You can iterate.
And if you don't do that, if you're
writing something for review, then who's
your reviewer? It's the program committee.
What I've seen sitting on program
committees is a lot of the times the paper
gets rejected, not because you didn't do
something, it's because the program
committee didn't understand what you did.
And if you interact with outsiders, you've
got this chance of clearing that up.
As opposed to if you just look at it
yourself.
Okay.
Not to write bad papers, bad talks,
basically do the opposite of bad
commandments.
There's two parts, preparation and
practice.
Most people take about two minutes of
slide. For some reason, I take one minute
of slide, and I don't know why.
You should plan on that a minute or minute
and a half, so you have plenty of time and
leave time for questions, since that's
some of the most important parts.
Despite Google engineers putting in
spinning text, you know, don't do that.
And then, you know, it's not a speech,
it's the first time you do it. It's a
talk, so you don't have to memorize it,
but have notes ready.
Practice is the key.
You want to do dry runs with friends to
get feedback. If you're giving a
professional talk,
the way you make impression is not only to
give a talk, but how you answer the
questions. I think for those of us in the
field a while, when you see somebody give
a dynamic talk and they really nail the
questions, you pay attention to that.
And then, so your practice ought to have
really tough questions, so you can
practice tough questions.
And then, with modern cell phones,
you can record yourself.
Not only your audio, you can watch
yourself. It's, you know, I have to tell
you, it's going to be a humbling experience.
You'll hear the crutches that you have in
your verbal speech. I start a lot of
sentences with so, I say, you'll be
shocked how bad it is, but everybody does
it, and this is the way you get better.
And I practice everything. I think of it,
I practice my talks just to show the
students who you're supposed to practice
your talks. But I practice my award
acceptance speeches, and they tear them
apart.
I would think an acceptance speech is
pretty good, but nope, nope, they make
them better. So,
practice.
Okay, now,
the other thing that I was going to do in
this talk is quoted Richard Hamming.
Richard Hamming actually came to Berkeley
when I was young and a professor, a larval
professor, and he gave this talk, You and
Your Research,
which is more or less how to do great
research like me.
And so, Richard Hamming of Hamming Code,
you know, Hamming Distance,
the reason memories don't make mistakes,
spent his career mostly at Bell Labs, and
it's pretty clear from watching these
videos, he's a very opinionated guy.
He doesn't, he's not saying, well, maybe
you should do this. But he watched careers
over Bell Labs, he saw people fail, he saw
people succeed,
and I'll quote him surely one minute
seconds every time.
So, this is him talking about the
importance of communication, and you'll
get his personality from this one.
Which brings me to the topic of
communication.
You need to learn to communicate orally in
talks like this,
written and written reports, and casual
conversations.
In the middle of a conference, you have to
be able to get up and say, that's wrong
for these reasons, bing, bing, bing, bing,
and you win.
If you sit around and say, well, I'll
write a report tomorrow after I've thought
about it some more,
the decision is made, we go ahead and it
doesn't matter what you do then.
The ability to communicate at three
levels. How do you learn it?
You can read books if you want to, but
forget it.
The way you learn as far as I'm concerned
is every time you go to a talk,
you listen not only to the talk, but to
the style that's done.
What talks are effective?
Why were they effective?
What aspects of the speaker can you adapt?
Which brings me to the topic of
communication.
You need to learn to communicate
orally in talks like this. Stop.
And then he
gave this talk a lot of times. This is the
one that's on your YouTube, right?
But there was a text one before and he
said in my early days I think you should
spend as much time in polishing and
presenting as you did in the original
research.
Now at least 50 % of it has to go in the
presentation.
Now if you know Hamming's idea of how do
you encode memory, it's beautifully
presented that almost everybody can
understand. So that was an example of him.
He thought not just came up with the math,
but he laid it out and had a very simple
encoding thing. It's almost like a parlor
trick is you can put a bit pattern in
there and tell you which one is wrong from
the way he does it. He made it very easy
to understand and as a result, every
single computer in the world
uses his idea.
But that was an example of him following
his own advice.
Yes.
Written?
I think I can get that.
Okay.
Okay, leading a project. Now I'm going to
go through the... I think I said this.
So,
academics have bad benchmarks,
papers,
or maybe even citations rather than impact
is what you're trying to do. I didn't
realize when I started I have six phases
for leading a project and we'll go through
the selecting a problem,
picking a solution, running a project,
finishing a project,
evaluating it and transferring technology.
So let me go through each of those.
Let's go back to Richard Hamming again.
He's going to talk about... One of the
guys.
And so I said, do you mind if I join you?
So I sit down and we talk about chemistry.
Set the stage here. So here's this pretty
opinionated guy who studies how people can
be great. He's kind of a hobby of his.
At Bell Labs,
one of the greatest research institutions
in the history of this country,
he's been having lunch with physicists,
but they started winning Nobel Prizes
inventing a transistor and things like
that and got promoted.
So he had to find a new group.
So he decided to hang out with the
chemist. So he just kind of butts his way
in as this outsider
to talk with the chemist.
Things for a long while.
And finally, one day,
I walk in and say,
if what you're working on is not important
and it's not likely to lead to important
things,
why are you working on it?
After that, I ate with the engineers.
That was spring. In the fall, going down
the Long Corridor Bell Labs,
my friend chemist got me and said,
you know, Hamming, that remark of yours
got underneath my skin.
I've spent this summer thinking about the
important problems in my field. I have not
changed my research, but I think it was
well worth the time.
I say, thank you, Dave, and walk on.
About two weeks later, I know he's made
head of the department.
About 10 or 12 years ago, I know he is a
member of the National Academy of
Engineering.
I have never heard of anything about any
other person at that chemistry table.
Not one.
The one man who could hear if what you're
doing is not important, not likely
important, why are you doing it? The one
man who could do become important. He did
succeed.
The rest of them who couldn't hear didn't.
It's that simple.
If you don't work on important problems,
you are not going to do important things
except by the dumbest of dumb luck.
And you realize when he's giving these
talks, the chemist that he was sitting
with were still around and could hear him
give these talks.
That's a charming guy.
Okay, so...
Selecting a problem. When I started at
Berkeley, I just jumped in and I'll tell
you about it in the next one.
Invent a new field and stick to it? No.
Try and do real stuff. Make sure other
people think it's important, not just you.
It's particularly easy to do that in
academia.
You're aiming for this positive impact,
big impact on computer science and
engineering.
And stick to it to your whole career. I
think in this fast, that's not what I did.
In this fast -moving field,
why not instead do a bunch of short
projects? Because a lot of research
projects aren't going to work.
These things always take longer to expect.
And how are you going to know if you're
working something for 20 years that this
is going to be an important problem for 20
years?
And what we found by doing lots of five
-year projects is that learning was more
of a number of projects than it was the
number of years. As you tackle something,
it was the new thing you learned from.
And then, a lot of times, as I'll say,
research doesn't work out, and you'd like
to fail
sooner rather than fail later.
What's worked well for us is multi
-disciplinary, multi -investigator
projects, trying to have somebody from
multiple fields on a single team.
And then to try and figure out the
strength and weaknesses of your local
environment. Universities are different.
There are strengths that obviously Google
has, and there are weaknesses too. So try
and figure out something that matches your
environment.
And make sure it's exciting that you want
to work on it for several years. And what
I've found is a compelling prototype that
we can build this thing that's really
going to be amazing is
inspirational.
Okay, so that's selecting the problem.
My first project, when I got to Berkeley
40 years ago, I spent about a week
thinking about it and joined some other
faculty, and it was ridiculously
ambitious. Three hardware faculty were
designing our own instruction set, build
our own chips,
build our own interconnections, network
switches, boards, systems, operating
systems.
We didn't have any experience in any of
it. We didn't have any research funding.
We didn't have any computing or CAD tools.
So what happened from all that? You know,
a couple of papers, right? Not bad for
academics.
Fortunately, I took a sabbatical during
that time, and went away and gave me a
chance to think about things differently.
And I came back and did the risk stuff.
Otherwise, I wouldn't have
tenure.
Picking a solution, let complexity be your
guide.
No,
keep things simple unless you've got a
really good reason not to.
I came up with this phrase early in my
career, is intelligence beams. On any
project, you have a sack of intelligence
beams that you get to spend.
So decide where you want to spend your
intelligence beams.
And then where it doesn't matter, you
know, you can use the common solutions.
And the best result you can possibly get
is afterward for them to say anyone could
have thought of that, right?
That doesn't seem so complicated. Anybody
could have thought of it. That you've
achieved things well.
Complexity costs everything.
You know, longer design, construction,
testing, and debugging.
And these delays lessen the impact of what
you do. So try and keep it simple. It's
hard to keep things simple, but that's the
goal.
The computer scientific,
nope.
You want to run experiments to discover
real problems. My friend John Straw says,
you use your intuition to ask questions,
not to answer them. We're really smart
people. We can make up what we think the
answer is, but that doesn't mean they're
right. What we need is to figure out the
experiments to figure out the real
answers.
So, you know, at Berkeley they asked me,
well, how do you pick a problem and
solution?
What we've done over these years, these
five -year projects is
we start before the end of our project, we
start meeting for at least a year to start
talking about what the next one will be.
We spend that much time thinking about it.
Typically, what we've done is saying, what
are some interesting technology trends
that are happening over the next five or
ten years that will shape the future of
computing, eight to ten years out?
To see if the mix of these trends have
some new opportunity,
for risk, it was probably
computer scientists were being able to do
integrated circuit design.
There was Moore's law that was taking off,
so a 32 -bit microprocessor was plausible.
What's the right way to design such a
microprocessor?
For RAID,
personal computers were getting popular.
They started building hard disks for them,
these cells called small hard disks.
They were being expensive.
Performance for input output was slow.
Processors were getting faster because of
risk.
Disperformance was slow. Maybe we could do
something with a lot of them.
For the network of workstation projects,
not only were workstations getting really
fast, but they were beginning to be local
area network switches, could we just build
a big computer out of a bunch of these
components and then how would that work?
Another thing that we've noticed over the
years are when you're all by yourself and
you're going to work in a new field, it's
very scary, but if there's a group of you
with different areas and you kind of go
after this thing, there's kind of safety
in numbers. You aren't all risking your
careers working on machine learning, but
the three of you working together seems
not quite as scary to be able to do that.
The big thing is to, when you've got these
ideas, is to find people whose opinion you
trust and try and get their feedback to
help you shape your vision. You don't have
to do exactly what they say, but you ought
to hear what they're saying.
And then pick a good name.
Apparently in some parallel universe, I'm
in the marketing department, but it's not
that is hard. I have these friends who show
off their Latin education who pick some
name that nobody can possibly spell, and
they even have a word for it now. You pick
the name, and then you
backfill in the acronym, and so they're
called Acronyms, right?
Nobody's ever going to remember that.
One of the projects my younger colleagues
picked is Aspire. It's actually 11 or 12
words. Nobody but him can remember it. So,
if that's true,
you're going to use the acronym model.
It's got to be three or four letters if
anybody's going to remember it.
You want to, the way we do it is put a
bunch of words on the wall that describes
the project.
Vowels are really valuable, and you want
to try three or four letters?
Three or four letters that are an English
word that kind of have something to do
with the project, so.
But I'm available as a consultant.
Running a project.
Do you want to avoid feedback?
That's one of the themes. No, we do these
periodic project reviews with outsiders.
We've been doing them for 30 years,
twice a year three -day retreat. How many
people here have been to a Berkeley -style
retreat?
All right. That's like a dozen people
here.
And
the outsiders are valued,
and, you know, it's huge benefits to doing
this.
At the end, we get the feedback from
everybody, and we don't argue with that
feedback, but we try to understand it.
It also creates deadlines, which are tough
everywhere,
but particularly academia builds team
spirit.
And
for the people working on it gives them a
chance to communicate and spread their
ideas and interact with others.
Consider a mid-course correction. Our
first project that I was doing was a multi
-processor. The risk ideas were just
starting to catch on, but they hadn't been
commercial yet. But by midway through the
project, there were commercial chips like
MIPS and Spark.
We should have
redirected our project to be used to
commercial processors, but I felt like
that was, you know, breaking our promise
and, you know, we should have stuck the
ones that we did customary, but we would
have had a much bigger impact with a multi
-processor
risk project then if we'd used commercial
instruction sets. So that's part of our
culture now.
It's a five -year project two and a half
years in. Maybe the world has changed in
some way and you should take advantage of
it. An example of that would have been the
Rad Lab, which was a couple of projects
ago we were doing internet services, and
then cloud computing got popular
in it, so we, you know, embraced that, and
that became a big theme of the Rad Lab.
Pick the size of the members of the team
carefully.
You know, tough personalities are hard on
everybody, not just tough personalities or
faculty, even tough personalities for
students, right? You know, it can make it
no fun to come to work, so
try and get good people. I think Berkeley
consciously tries not to hire Prima
Donnas, which makes it nicer.
And if, you know, if you have one expert
per area, it's a little easier. My
colleague Kathy Failed,
I've got opinions about programming
language from piers, but when she speaks,
you know, I listen, right? I don't. And
that makes it easier to do things.
Don't be distracted by others. This is not
going to be so radical for you guys, but
about ten years ago, we went to an open
collaborative thing where we got rid of
faculty offices.
What was happening
is that the students were staying home
because the computers were just as fast
and networks just as fast as home as they
were at work, and whether this is good for
a company or not, I'll leave to you, but
it's terrible for research because it's
not just put your head down and plow
ahead. We've got to talk to people because
you're not sure where you're supposed to
be going.
So we put it into the open space
and what, now that I've read about it,
what you're shooting for is communication
and concentration.
So people can come into work, they have to
be able to concentrate enough to get the
work done, but you want to have
spontaneous communication which leads to
innovation.
So bump into each other and have meeting
rooms.
We've got the meeting rooms optimized for
discussions and phone calls. We came, Jeff
Waltz brought us probably ten years ago
and we saw what you guys did with your
conference rooms and we imitated that.
And
like you guys, we have kitchens and free
drinks. We can't do food but we can do
drinks.
And the amazing thing is it accelerates
research.
Who would have thought space could
accelerate research?
It was startling what happened. We went
from faculty offices that had kind of
whiteboards there that were filled with
faculty reminders and you came in and you
got to work on like one square foot to put
your idea in there. Instead, we had giant
whiteboards.
There was no writing person. You couldn't
reserve it in the high-tech way. We copied
it with cell phones.
It came stimulating. People came in more.
There were more spontaneous meetings.
And then we noticed the zero to 60 time
for new people went incredibly faster by
having that kind of environment. So Mata
Bavaria in his second semester there, he
gave a talk at Carnegie Mellon. We never
had anybody do that before. Now Mata
Bavaria who the founder of Spark did a lot
of good things but it wasn't obvious then
that he was going to be that good as it
turned out. So maybe that had something to
do with it.
And so Richard Hamming has opinions on
this based on his experience.
Which I'm sure you're not surprised. Okay,
he's got two opinions. The first one is
open versus closed doors. And the only way
he can have this opinion was to keep track
of all of his colleagues. Which ones kept
the doors closed? Which ones were open?
Which ones were successful?
And he's...
Here's his idea.
The example I've given you already is
working with a door closed or open.
If you work with your door closed
you won't be interrupted. You'll get your
work done.
You work with your door open. People can
buy and stop and chat and so on and so on.
But I've noticed very clearly at Bell
laboratories,
those who work with a door shut
may be working just as hard ten years
later,
but they don't know what to work on. They
are not connected with reality.
Those who had the door open
may very well know what's important.
Now I cannot prove to you whether the open
door causes the open mind or whether the
open mind causes the open door.
I suspect a bill I could only establish
the correlation.
And it was quite spectacular.
Almost always.
The guy with the door closed were often
very well able.
Very gifted, but they seemed to work
always on slightly the wrong problem.
So you have to get wide feeling for what
is going on.
Okay.
And then
he believed that so much that this is how
his patterns, how he handled Friday
afternoons, about the importance.
Especially for researchers, you can start
to work really hard, but you could miss
the really important thing
by not interacting.
At the urging of some other people, partly
and partly in my own,
I used to set aside Friday noon and Friday
afternoon for great thoughts.
Meaning,
yes, I'll answer a telephone, yes, I'll
sign a sheet of paper,
but mainly what is the effect of computing
on science?
What the hell am I doing with this
computing machine?
How is it going to affect AT AT?
What should I be doing with computing?
What is the nature of software?
My friends all after a while got to know
Friday afternoon is great thoughts.
What's the nature of this and that and the
other thing?
I spent 10 % of my time trying to answer
the question of what are the important
problems in my field?
10 % Friday afternoon straight through.
Don't do it Monday morning because you'll
be interrupted immediately.
If you do it Friday afternoon, someone can
link it over on to Saturday and Sunday. If
you do it Monday morning, there's a hot
conference at 10 o 'clock and bingo,
everything is broken up.
I use it Friday afternoon for many, many
years. I recommend that you find a regular
time to stop and think
what are the important things? What is
going on? What is the nature of what you
are doing?
What is the characteristic of the job?
What are the fundamentals behind it? So
you'll have some idea
where you're headed so you can march in a
uniform direction and get far rather than
being a drunken sailor and getting
nowhere.
You're free to not ignore the advice but
then your career is that of a drunken
sailor.
Okay, finishing your project. I'll talk
about this some.
If people count the number of projects you
finish, not the ones you start.
In successful
projects, go through this unglamorous hard
phase of trying to finish it.
It's because design is a lot more fun.
It's a lot more fun to design things to
make stuff work.
But, you know, some positive things. Fred
Brooks, one of my heroes says there's no
winners on a losing team. No losers on a
winning team. If you win, anybody
involved, no matter what they did, they
win.
Improve productivity of team members. How
can you do that?
Organize each day. When are you figuring
out when you're most alert?
When you need an app or exercise or sleep?
When? How often should you be reading and
writing,
programming and email?
And what I found for successful
colleagues, they always used to do this,
you know, daily, weekly and even every six
months to see how they're doing on their
career.
These days, there's this idea of agile
scrum where you meet in the same place at
the same time and do sprints. I think this
is a pretty effective model.
And then reduce the projects of slate.
Again, Fred Brooks said adding people to a
late project makes it later in his classic
book, The Mythical Manhunt.
And finishing a project is how you acquire
taste. How do you get good taste? If you
don't finish it, you don't know really
what went wrong. It helps you pick good
problems and find simple solutions.
Okay. And then my friend John Hennessy, I
guess
at President Stamford said this a long
time ago, you can quickly tell whether or
not the authors have ever built something
and made it work.
And if you never make it work, you don't
acquire that taste.
Evaluating quantitatively never be proven
wrong.
Nope. If you can't be proven wrong, then
you can't be proven right.
And you have to, you know, we need
reproducible results. You're trying to get
people to use your ideas. If they can't
reproduce them, they're not going to take
your word for it.
And, you know, for better, for worse,
benchmarks to shape our field, and
especially in the commercial world, if we
have good ones that accelerate progress,
bad ones, then there's a choice between
helping sales or helping customers, and
often sales wins.
And then transferring technology. It's not
just you write a paper and everybody
starts using it.
You have to go out and stump it.
You know, this last year, there's a risk
five, which is an effort to be able to
have an open instruction set so that be an
open alternative, kind of like Linux is to
Microsoft Windows.
So I gave talks at, you know,
at ten universities this fall trying to
get the word out. Then if they kind of
like the ideas, then they read the papers.
Of course, you know, if you don't pick a
good problem, people aren't going to be
that interested.
And you can tell if it's a good problem if
more people get interested over time
rather than yours starts to do that. I
think I'm persuasive. The way I change
minds is with believable numbers. And so
you have to collect that quantitatively
and believe it. The other thing I learned
late in my career is your personality
affects technology transfer. There's this
person who I won't name who had a bunch of
interesting ideas and people wouldn't use
them. And I talked to people in the
industry about they hated that guy.
They hated that guy. If there was any
other way to do it at all, they would use
it because that would the last thing they
would do. So you could be a jerk if you
have the only possible solution, but it's
kind of hard to do that in computing.
Maybe in biology you can do that.
And then product groups, people don't want
to change. Product groups, there's risk
associated with change. Let's work for us
and this goes back.
So Fred Brooks, when he was a graduate
student, his advice was Howard Aiken.
And Fred Brooks said, I think these people
are going to steal your idea. These
companies are looking at his idea at
Harvard University, a drum memory system.
Watch out, Howard. And Aiken said in some
of the actions, the problem in this
business isn't to keep people from
stealing your ideas. It's making them
steal your ideas.
That's still true today 65 years later.
So what's worked for us is to find one
bold group, often not the leaders, but
some bold group willing to take a shot on
it and they are successful.
And then kind of the rest of the field is,
well, and for us,
it was Sun Microsystems for Risk and EMC
for RAID and INC to me and then Google for
Networks of Workstations.
But it's kind of like the rest of the
field, oh, damn
they tried it. It works. Okay, we'll
change, right?
People don't really,
as much as people enjoy ideas, they don't
want to take the risk. And then the other
way of transferring technology is to start
a company.
In my 40 years, everybody I've talked to
who's worked for a startup likes it doing
it once.
They absolutely, now there's some people
who love doing it more than once. A lot of
people once is enough.
But everybody thinks it was useful, they
learn a lot.
And then if it works, you know, if it
works out, you see not just your ideas,
but the product and of course you can
potentially make a lot of money that works
out and become famous.
The downsides are that, you know, you
learn about things you might not want to
learn about,
but
particularly lawsuits,
my friends who have lawsuits,
that's less fun.
And you don't get to do research and
development.
And then only 10 % of the startups make
it. But nevertheless, everybody thinks it
was worth it for once in their life, maybe
when you're younger.
So I didn't really realize that there were
six roles to being a leader of a project
and it changes over time.
But that's what I believe now. Now
so wrapping things up and there's time for
questions
here is the goal is to have impact is to
change the way people do computing and
engineering positively. Now,
we do these five -year projects. Now that
my career is
ending,
I will do 12, right? They overlap. So I
have been there 40 years, not 60 years.
You can't tell if a project is successful
for at least 10 years.
And the good news is three of them look
like they're pretty successful.
They're 10 years old. So that's like kind
of 25 % batting average, which is why I'm
glad I did a lot of projects.
There's two that are finished,
but haven't been 10 years. The Rad Lab did
spark and mess.
Those seem promising.
The Par Lab did communication avoiding
algorithms and demo and this RISC -5
stuff.
But, you know, it will take five or seven
years to know how significant it was. So
maybe I'll get up to, you know, five out
of 12, which is like 40%. But most of the
projects don't work, so I'm glad I did
short projects.
So solve a problem other people care
about. You taste that you acquire by
finishing projects and then
whoops.
And so, okay.
And I think the key theme of running over
my career is feedback. It's figuring out
ways to get feedback. Okay, with that, I'm
ready for questions.
APPLAUSE
I think there's a microphone here.
Okay, questions.
Without the first question, there won't be
multiple questions.
Oh, there it is.
Since you asked for hard questions, which
of your projects did you enjoy the most
and which of them do you think had the
most impact?
Which did I enjoy the most?
Let me do the most impact.
Because I'm kind of wrapping things up,
its plausible raid had the biggest
impact.
It's everybody uses it.
You know, the original raid paper won
three
test of time awards.
You know, if I had, it looks to me, if I
try to be a neutral observer, probably
raid is the most significant so far. Which
one did I enjoy the most?
I try to always make projects that I
really love. I try to make projects that
if I was a graduate student, I just died
to work on this project.
You know,
that's hard.
Maybe... Yeah, what are you about to do? I
don't know. The good thing about all the
projects, whether they're home
runs, is they produce great students.
And I didn't say that in the slide.
There's almost 300 students in those 12
projects that have,
which was
I had fun adding that number up.
Jeff.
So this isn't really a problem for most of
us here, but would you give different
advice to a pre -tenure academic versus a
post -tenure academic? Or do you think you
can do the kinds of things you're talking
about and not compromise your chances of
getting tenure? Yeah, so people ask me to
say something. So when Hennessy and I did
the risk stuff, which at the time was
hugely controversial. If you think deep
neural networks are controversial,
people,
a faculty member of another institution
wrote a hit piece on me personally, Dave
Patterson's a bad person about, and we
were talking about instruction set design.
But at the time Hennessy and I were saying
digital equipment, one of the leading
computer manufacturers in the world, had a
pretty stupid design.
So we
didn't worry about that.
Also, you have to believe in what you're
doing.
I just can't give the advice to do
something that
you don't believe in
and work on that because in fact when I
visited universities and I've seen that,
it's an assistant professor telling me, well
I don't really like what I'm working on,
but this is what I have to do to get
tenure and then I go talk to the chairman
and this guy is just doing incremental
stuff. He's never going to get tenure,
right? There's that gap there.
You know, when you're larval, you need to
make sure you publish,
you know, you need to go around and give
talks and stuff like that. But I think you
got to do projects you believe in.
Life's too short to work on. Yeah,
question here?
So you mentioned a couple of times
not to be a prima donna.
So it's easy to identify other people
being prima donnas. But how do you tell if
you're being a prima donna?
Are you married?
My family's perfect at pointing out my
flaws.
Well, I think
feedback is the one I go out of my way to
get feedback. If somebody hates my papers,
I send them new papers because they tell
me the honest thing to do. I would like to
think if I'm acting like a jerk that, you
know, I'm pretty sure my friends or my
family would
tell me that. I think you could ask.
I think you can ask, right?
Geez, people are afraid to tell you
something if not, but I think if you ask
did I handle that well or not, you can do
it.
I think some people in academia think
that's the way you,
that's the way people know that you're
famous. You've had some success, you start
acting differently and it's just bad
career advice.
Okay, other questions?
So full disclosure, I went to Brooklyn and
experienced one of these projects.
Amin was on the network workstation
project. I'm biased toward the model. My
question is, given the success of the
model, why do you think more
universities haven't adopted it?
I mean, even though it seems like the
stuff you're saying is really obvious,
it's also somewhat rare.
Yeah,
I got that exact same question at
Berkeley.
I think this time I'll be less humble.
You need to, you have to have somebody
who's willing to lead,
right?
For some reason, even though wrestling,
as I'll tell you, I wrestled in high
school and college as an individual sport,
I had great wrestling coaches who realized
we'd be more successful if we bonded as a
team,
even though it was an individual sport. So
I had that kind of role model going up and
so I think I'm good at kind of organizing
teams. So you have to have somebody who's
willing to do that.
The institution itself, Berkeley
told me day one have impact.
They didn't have any problem with multiple
people working on it. When you're an
assistant professor,
you make up rules like I have to have only
sold off in papers, otherwise they're
going to credit, but that's not true. So
the institution let us happen.
I think it was helpful that I'm a good
leader of people, but there's lots of good
leaders of people around. I don't
understand why that doesn't happen more.
It seems common sense.
It's not like I've kept this a secret for
40 years. I've been telling people at
Lawson Institution.
I'm not sure, but we're a lunatic fringe,
right? We put a group together. It's a
different group with interdisciplinary mix
and match. We tackle a problem.
We've already visited you guys on the next
project to get some feedback on it. I
don't know why more people don't do it.
You have to ask them.
You should ask them.
Why don't you guys act like Berkeley? I'm
sure they'd love that.
There's probably a nearby university.
I think we have about five or six more
minutes.
With that, I need to give
quickly
my life story.
I'm an accidental CS student. I was a math
major and wrestler in high school and
college.
At the end of my junior year, the math
class was canceled. I had to take a
course. There was no CS major. I just took
an intro to computer science
and I was hooked. That was it. My senior
year, I took every computer course I
could.
I'm an accidental student. I went to UCLA.
I casually mentioned at the end of one of
those courses to a new Ph. D. I'd rather
do this than work in a factory to pay my
college. He on his own went and found me a
job as an undergraduate student.
While I was an undergraduate student, even
though it was near the end of my senior
year, that wasn't too late to go to
graduate school. I asked my wife about
master's degree. She said, sure, it's only
four or five quarters.
When I got into the office, everybody else
in my office was getting a Ph. D. So I
thought maybe I should get a Ph. D. So I
decided to do that.
We lived on a research assistant salary
with my wife and two kids and I. We were
at, you know, poverty level at that time.
And then the project ended. I lost my R
. A. ship.
My advisor helped get me a job at an
aerospace company whose aircraft.
And then it was touch and go whether I had
finished my Ph. D. because I was working
20, 30, 40 hours. But I did mean it.
I'm an accidental Berkeley professor.
My wife grew up in,
right next door to Berkeley and when I was
graduating on the interview tour, she
says, I can't help but think you ended up
with Berkeley. And I said, look,
Berkeley's up here.
UCLA's down here. I'm graduating. This is
never going to happen. But she forced me
as a graduate student to call the chairman
of the department at Berkeley Computer
Science to find out about my application.
So I called this guy.
He said, well, Dave, you're in the top
ten, but not top five. And at the time I'm
thinking, wow, that wasn't so bad.
So turns out, he said that to anybody who
called.
But then he took my application.
Yeah, that seems interesting. Handed it to
somebody visiting Southern California.
We had a good conversation. They invited
me back to the interview and got a job
offer.
I
barely got tenure.
The first project I already told you about
was way too ambitious.
I did the sabbatical and did the wrist
stuff.
Tenure wasn't easy. I was one of those
guys that was using conferences where the
whole campus used journals but us. So I
was the guinea pig that went through that
and the wrist stuff was pretty new, but I
got it. After that, things got better.
But I still get papers rejected by those
jerks on the programming committee.
And so what have I learned? What works for
me?
For me, it was maximizing personal
happiness versus personal wealth. That's
always been my guideline.
Believe in this country, you think wealth
is happiness.
There's unhappy billionaires, right? In
this world. They're not the same thing.
Family first, especially in that kind of
job. You know, people ask you do things or
family can go down the list. I made my
family first. We had my wife and I, two
sons. So I did Indian guides.
I was the cup scout leader. I was the
soccer coach when there were field trips
out there.
So when my rebellious teenage boy grew up,
ah, you were never there. And I said,
Indian guides, cup scouts.
So I went down the list. He said, oh,
okay, maybe.
Passion, courage, and optimism. You might
be able to tell I'm a passionate guy. I
have to believe the thing I'm doing is
going to possibly change the world.
My optimism story goes back to high
school.
I started dating this girl who was dating
older guys who had corvettes and stuff
like that.
Nevertheless, after a couple of years and
a couple of updates, I asked her
if she would go steady with me.
I was really sad at the time.
She'd just been dating older guys and
didn't know what to say. She said, well, I
don't know how to say no. So me, being an
optimist and logical person, Nana knows a
yes. So I said, great, and I hugged her.
And she said, you know,
I'll let this guy down later. But we've
been married 48 years now. So I think
that's okay.
And then, yeah, I think we swing for the
fences, right? That's that thing.
Now, another thing. This is a saying that
a colleague told me that it's actually a
couple hundred years old. Friends come and
go, but enemies accumulate.
So this kind of... Ironically, the
physical courage that comes with wrestling
has,
to me, been intellectual courage. So when
I was president of ACM,
the person in charge of DARPA was cutting
back on academic funding.
So I decided to take him on with my friend
at Belozoska in Washington. And we tried
to get people from other universities to
join us. But they were afraid this guy
would be vengeful and cut him off, I
think, with good reason. So it was just us
taking him on with editorials and science
and stuff. So this guy was not a fan of
us. But we hadn't quite realized this is
unintentional.
But the other saying is the enemy of my
enemy is my friend. So we made a lot of
friends.
But keep that in mind.
Winning as a team versus an individual. In
my DNA,
I believe a team of, you know, average
people can work together and beat
superstars.
And then I've already quoted Fred Brooks
about that line.
Seek out honest feedback and learn from
it. It's easy to avoid feedback. But
that's how you get better.
The one warning sign I can pass on from my
fourth years
always dangerous is when somebody thinks
that there's the smartest person in the
room. There's a person in my field who
thinks he's the smartest person in the
room and everybody hates that guy. There
was a president of a university who
thought he's the smartest. That person was
fired for doing a lousy job.
The people who founded Enron
thought they were the smartest people in
the room. They went to prison and I even
have a relative who thought he was the
smartest
person in the room and he's a convicted
felon. So why would that be? Why would
this person be probably smart? If they
think they're the smartest, why would it
be such a bad sign? I think it's that they
don't want feedback from anybody. If
you're the smartest person in the room,
you don't need to talk to anybody about
your ideas. But anyway, run away if you
find something like that.
This thing happened to me. It was like God
spoken my ear one morning.
I remember waking up and it's not how many
projects you start. It's how many you
finish. It was like in my head.
Like somebody was telling me what to do.
Ever since that, that's what I've done.
What I do is one big project at a time. I
do other things, but there's one big thing
at a time. When Hennessy and I were doing
our textbook,
that was the big thing that I did that
year.
When I was president of ACM,
I took a sabbatical, so that was the one
big thing I did there that year. It turns
out if you do one big thing a year,
over 30 years you can get a lot of things
done.
A lot of academics, particularly, will
work on a thousand things at once and not
finish for many of them.
And then
have fun.
To be successful, you do have to work
hard. Our long-lost
colleague Jim Gray,
even in his 60s, he'd do one all night or
a month. So you have to work hard to be
successful. But you have to have fun.
As far as we know, you only get one chance
of this and if you get to the end without
having any fun, you've wasted a lot of
opportunities. I can put up a lot of
stuff. As long as I play soccer every
Sunday,
I can have a good time. So that's my
advice.
Thanks very much.