Today I want to tell you three stories
from my life. That's it. No big deal.
Just three stories.
The first story is about connecting the
dots.
I dropped out of Reed College after the
first six months but then stayed around as
a drop -in for another 18 months or so
before I really quit.
So why'd I drop out?
It started before I was born.
My biological mother was a young unwed
graduate student and she decided to put me
up for adoption.
She felt very strongly that I should be
adopted by college graduates so everything
was all set for me to be adopted at birth
by a lawyer and his wife.
Except that when I popped out they decided
at the last minute that they really wanted
a girl.
So my parents who were on a waiting list
got a call in the middle of the night
asking,
we've got an unexpected baby boy. Do you
want him?
They said,
of course.
My biological mother found out later that
my mother had never graduated from college
and that my father had never graduated
from high school.
She refused to sign the final adoption
papers.
She only relented a few months later when
my parents promised that I would go to
college.
This was the start in my life.
And 17 years later I did go to college but
I naively chose a college that was almost
as expensive as Stanford and all of my
working class parents' savings were being
spent on my college tuition.
After six months I couldn't see the value
in it.
I had no idea what I wanted to do with my
life and no idea how college was going to
help me figure it out.
And here I was spending all the money my
parents had saved their entire life.
So I decided to drop out and trust that it
would all work out okay.
It was pretty scary at the time but
looking back it was one of the best
decisions I ever made.
The minute I dropped out I could stop
taking the required classes that didn't
interest me and begin dropping in on the
ones that looked far more interesting.
It wasn't all romantic.
I didn't have a dorm room, so I slept on
the floor in friends rooms.
I returned Coke bottles for the five cent
deposits to buy food with and I would walk
the seven miles across town every Sunday
night to get one good meal a week at the
Hard Krishna temple.
I loved it and much of what I stumbled
into by following my curiosity and
intuition turned out to be priceless later
on.
Let me give you one example.
Reed College at that time offered perhaps
the best calligraphy instruction in the
country.
Throughout the campus every poster every
label on every drawer was beautifully hand
Calligrapher.
Because I had dropped out and didn't have
to take the normal classes I decided to
take a calligraphy class to learn how to
do this.
I learned about serif and sans serif
typefaces about varying the amount of
space between different letter
combinations about what makes great
typography great.
It was beautiful historical artistically
subtle in a way that science can't capture
and I found it fascinating.
None of this had even a hope of any
practical application in my life.
But 10 years later when we were designing
the first Macintosh computer it all came
back to me and we designed it all into the
Mac.
It was the first computer with beautiful
typography.
If I had never dropped in on that single
course in college the Mac would have never
had multiple typefaces or proportionally
spaced fonts and since Windows just copied
the Mac it's likely that no personal
computer would have them.
If I had never dropped out I would have
never dropped in on that calligraphy class
and personal computers might not have the
wonderful typography that they do.
Of course, it was impossible to connect the
dots looking forward when I was in college
but it was very, very clear looking
backwards 10 years later.
Again you can't connect the dots looking
forward you can only connect them looking
backwards so you have to trust that the
dots will somehow connect in your future.
You have to trust in something your gut
destiny life karma whatever
because believing that the dots will
connect down the road will give you the
confidence to follow your heart even when
it leads you off the well-worn path and
that will make all the difference.
My second story is about love and loss.
I was lucky I found what I love to do
early in life.
Was and I started Apple in my parents
garage when I was 20.
We worked hard and in 10 years Apple had
grown from just the two of us in a garage
into a two billion dollar company with
over four thousand employees.
We just released our finest creation the
Macintosh a year earlier and I just turned
and then I got fired.
How can you get fired from a company you
started?
Well as Apple grew we hired someone who I
thought was very talented to run the
company with me and for the first year or
so things went well but then our visions
of the future began to diverge and
eventually we had a falling out.
When we did our board of directors sided
with him and so at 30 I was out
and very publicly out.
What had been the focus of my entire adult
life was gone and it was devastating.
I really didn't know what to do for a few
months.
I felt that I had let the previous
generation of entrepreneurs down that I
had dropped the baton as it was being
passed to me.
I met with David Packard and Bob Noyce and
tried to apologize for screwing up so
badly.
I was a very public failure and I even
thought about running away from the valley
but something slowly began to dawn on me.
I still loved what I did.
The turn of events at Apple had not
changed that one bit.
I'd been rejected but I was still in love
and so I decided to start over.
I didn't see it then but it turned out
that getting fired from Apple was the best
thing that could have ever happened to me.
The heaviness of being successful was
replaced by the lightness of being a
beginner again less sure about everything.
It freed me to enter one of the most
creative periods of my life.
During the next five years I started a
company named NEXT another company named
Pixar and fell in love with an amazing
woman who would become my wife.
Pixar went on to create the world's first
computer animated feature film Toy Story
and is now the most successful animation
studio in the world.
In a remarkable turn of events Apple
bought NEXT and I returned to Apple and
the technology we developed at NEXT is at
the heart of Apple's current renaissance
and Doreen and I have a wonderful family
together.
I'm pretty sure none of this would have
happened if I hadn't been fired from
Apple.
It was awful tasting medicine but I guess
the patient needed it.
Sometimes life's going to
hit you in the head with a brick.
Don't lose faith.
I'm convinced that the only thing that
kept me going was that I loved what I did.
You've got to find what you love and that
is as true for work as it is for your
lovers.
Your work is going to fill a large part of
your life and the only way to be truly
satisfied is to do what you believe is
great work and the only way to do great
work is to love what you do.
If you haven't found it yet keep looking
and don't settle as with all matters of
the heart you'll know when you find it and
like any great relationship it just gets
better and better as the years roll on so
keep looking don't settle.
My third story is about death.
When I was 17 I read a quote that went
something like
if you live each day as if it was your
last someday you'll most certainly be
right.
It made an impression on me and since then
for the past 33 years I've looked in the
mirror every morning and asked myself if
today were the last day of my life what I
want to do what I am about to do today and
whenever the answer has been no for too
many days in a row
I know I need to change something
remembering that all be dead soon is the
most important tool I've ever encountered
to help me make the big choices in life
because almost everything
all external expectations all pride all
fear of embarrassment or failure these
things just fall away in the face of death
leaving only what is truly important
remembering that you are going to die is
the best way I know to avoid the trap of
thinking you have something to lose you
are already naked there is no reason not
to follow your heart no one wants to die
even people who want to go to heaven don't
want to die to get there and yet death is
the destination
share.
No one has ever escaped it.
And that is as it should be, because death
is very likely the single best invention
of life.
It's life's change agent. It clears out
the old to make way for the new.
Right now, the new is you.
But someday, not too long from now, you
will gradually become the old and be
cleared away.
Sorry to be so dramatic, but it's quite
true.
Your time is limited,
so don't waste it living someone else's
life.
Don't be trapped by dogma, which is living
with the results of other people's
thinking.
Don't let the noise of others' opinions
drown out your own inner voice.
And most important,
have the courage to follow your heart and
intuition.
They somehow already know what you truly
want to become.
Everything else is secondary.
Stay hungry.
Stay foolish.