so if you want to make six figures you
can't just be talking about you want to
make six figures you hear what I'm
saying to you tonight if you do the
three things I tell you to do tonight I
guarantee you whatever it is you want to
do in life you'll be able to do you will
be able to accomplish whatever you want
to acad mically financially relationally
whatever so three things all right I'm
going to tell you the story I got to get
out of here and the story is about you
guys have probably heard about this
before it was a it was a young man who
you know he wanted to make a lot of
money and so he went to this Guru right
and he told the guru you know I want to
be on the same level you on and so the
guru said if you want to be on the same
level I'm on I'll meet you tomorrow at
the beach at 4:00
a.m. he like the beach I said I want to
make money I don't want to swim Guru
said if you want to make money I'll meet
you tomorrow 4:00 a.m. so the young man
got there at 4:00 a.m. he already to
rock and roll got on the suit should
have wore shorts the old man grabs his
hand said how bad do you want to be
successful he said real bad he said walk
on out in the water so he walks out into
the water watch this when he walks out
into the water it goes way deep so he
like this guy crazy a he like I want to
make money he got me out here swimming I
didn't ask to be a lifeguard I want to
make money he got me so he said come out
a little further walked out a little
further then he had it right around this
area St the area so this old man crazy
he making money but he crazy he said
come on out a little further he came out
a little further was right at his mouth
my man like I'm about to go back in here
this God is mine so the old man said I
thought you said you wanted to be
successful he said I do he said walk a
little further he came dropped his head
in held him down hold him down my man
getting scratching holding him down I
got you I know you brushed it out but I
got you he had him held down I need you
for an illustration he had him held down
just before my man was about to pass out
he raised him up he said I got a
question for you somebody answered a
question for me he said when you were
underwater what did you want to
do Lee I'm looking for a different word
though L what's that word said I wanted
to
breathe he told the guy he said when you
want to succeed as bad as you want to
breathe then you'll be
[Music]
successful I don't know how many y'all
got asthma in here today but if you ever
had an asthma attack before you short of
breath so shortness of breath you
wheezing the only thing you trying to do
is get some air you don't care about no
basketball game you don't care what's on
TV you don't care about nobody calling
you you don't care about a party the
only thing you care about when you're
trying to breathe is to get some fresh
air that's it and when when you get to
the point where all you want to do is be
successful as bad as you want to breathe
then you'll be successful and I'm here
to tell you number one that most of you
say you want to be successful but you
don't want it bad you just kind of want
it you don't want it bad than you want a
party you don't want it as much as you
want to be cool you most of you don't
want success as much as you want to
sleep some of you love sleep more than
you love success and I'm here to tell
you today if you're going to be
successful you got to be willing to give
up
sleep you got to be willing to work off
for 3 hours of sleep 2 hours if you
really want to be successful some days
you going to have to stay up 3 days in a
row because if you go to sleep you might
miss the opportunity to be successful
that's how bad you got to want it you
got to go D without listen to me you got
to want to be successful so bad that you
forget to
eat Beyonce said once she was on the set
doing her thing three days had gone by
she forgot she didn't eat
CU he was engaged I never forget when 50
c was doing his movie I did a little
research on 50 and 50 said that when he
wasn't doing the movie he was doing the
soundtrack and they said when do you
sleep 50 sleep he said sleep sleep is
for those people who are broke I don't
sleep said I got an opportunity to make
a dream become a reality football
players how many football players got
anybody like football in here raise your
hand anybody like football em SMI I used
to be a Cowboy fan before they did my
boy Tom Landry wrong I used to be a
Cowboy fan and watch this there was a
commercial em Smith had won his first
Super Bowl and he had this commercial
one he was lifting weights I don't know
if you saw the commercial one he was
lifting and he said he said em said you
know what I want a Super Bowl so I can
rest now he doing his bch press so he
said I want a Super Bowl so I can rest
now so he throws up about 325 boom and
he rest for about 2 seconds
and
he
boom
boom boom did you see that he'd already
want a super ball he said I think I'm
going to take a rest and he rest for how
long one second most of you won't be
successful because when you're studying
and you get tired you
quit and I'm here to tell you today if
you got to somebody came in my office
the other day crying I said look don't
cry to give up cry to keep
going don't cry to quit you already in
pain you already hurt get a reward from
it don't go to sleep until you succeed
listen to me I'm here to tell you today
that you can come here you can jump up
you can do flips you can be excited when
we give away money but listen to me
you'll never be successful until I don't
have to give you a dime to do what you
[Music]
do you won't be successful until you say
I don't need that money cuz I got it in
here so listen to me em Smith said this
at the end of the commercial em Smith
said all men are created equal some work
harder in
pre-season I'm going say it again
because you might have missed it all men
are created equal some work harder in
pre-season so that means that there are
some people who are going to see the
professor going to see the TA and even
when the professor says I don't meet
with you my ta meet with you you say I
don't want to talk to your ta
that's I don't pay the TA I pay you to
teach me so you going to have to find
some time to meet me if I got to meet
you at the mall if I got to meet you at
your house you are going to see me
listen to me all men are created equal
some work hard in preseason when I went
to college guys were way smarter than me
4.0 3.0 they went to the ivy league high
schools came to Oakwood from these great
high schools most of them are not doing
what I'm doing why cuz it's not about
where you come from it's about heart you
come to a place where you know being
smart ain't enough you got to have heart
that's number one watch number two
number two catch number two I wrote it
down I want to make sure you got it it
says to be watch this watch this we're
talking about sacrifice now the
important thing is this you're right why
I'm saying it cuz I only have about
three more minutes listen to me the most
important thing is this to be able at
any moment to sacrifice what you are for
what you will
[Music]
become that's the number two thing you
got to catch that one to be able to
listen to me at any moment some of you
you can make sacrifices when Monday
Night Football is not on you can make a
sacrifice but when the game come on for
some reason you just attached to
it for some of you when your favorite
show come on you you can be you can make
sacrifices on Sunday when ain't nothing
going
on but when your favorite show comes on
Monday B some of you you focusing to the
phone ring and you like I got to answer
if I don't answer the phone I'm going to
die I'm saying to you today that there
are some of you if you give up your cell
phone you would be successful
but your cell phone is more important to
you than your
success I'm going say it again I'mma
hurt somebody I'mma hurt somebody some
of you need to give up your cell phone
because the time you spend on your cell
phone could be used for your success the
time you could be using to be successful
you're using it on the sale and the cell
phone is not bringing you nothing but a
bill and somebody has told you you
couldn't live without it I'm talking
about going deep now giving up stuff
watch what it says to be able at any
moment to sacrifice what we are for what
we could be I don't do well in math
you're right you ain't never
studied I'm not good in writing cuz you
have never written
before but I dare you to fail in writing
for a whole year to see if you can get
to the end I dare you to fail I dare you
to take that same class over and over I
dare you to stop dropping classes like
you soft
always want to give up I'm dropping why
you dropping I'm so grateful that the
slaves didn't drop and quit say I'm just
going to stop I'm a slave I'm just going
to be a slave I'mma quit listen to me
the slave said we will live because one
day we will become we won't always be
slaves so today although we're slaves we
going to act like we free and one day
our children will be free if the slaves
would have just said we quit we give up
we would have died in the middle passage
but some slaves said I don't care what
we go through we going to survive this
400 years of slavery we going to get
through this and you can't get through a
1825 you can't get through a writing
class and you got tutor after tutor
resource after resource the problem is
you ain't never felt no pain before
you're
soft it's a soft generation you quit on
everything our people did not quit harri
and told me not only made it she went
back I can got some
more she said you know what I made it
but I'm I'm going to walk all listen to
me sh not ride the bus I'm going walk
all the way back down to the South to
get some more and you quitting on
[Music]
1825 now watch this you quit after you
listen to me you get a sleeping bag and
you wait for
him you wait for the first instructor to
come in and you come out just sleeping
back I need
help you quit after you do that
you quit after you had listen to me a a
w
party I'm I'm having a party everybody
come over I got fol everything and let
them get over there let it be all the
best writers all right I fol y'all I
want to have a writing
[Music]
party I'm serious you quitting you ain't
even tried yet last one I'm sorry last
one listen to me pain is
temporary it may last for a minute or an
hour or a day or even a
year but eventually it will
subside and something else will take its
place if I quit however it will last
forever listen to me I'm telling you as
I leave telling you as I leave I was
homeless for 2 and 1/2 years and the
problem with most of you you never felt
no pain before yall
spoiled y'all spoil some of y'all spoil
just bottom line your parents have done
everything for you you never had to do
nothing for yourself you're spoiler we
going to keep it real tonight some of
you are spoiled brats every time you
ever got in trouble somebody in your
house got you out of
it every time you done something you're
not supposed to do people say Eric your
mother's a tyrant you're right she
kicked me out you're right she's mean
but she developed a man because she put
me out there and said you going to have
to grow up and some of you have never
learn to grow up and so every time
something get hard you quit you call
Mama I dare you to take a little
pain I dare you I dare you not to go
home somebody said I I going go home I
feel bad go go through
it you ain't going to die at the end of
pain and success you're not going to die
because you feeling a little
pain I'm not eating like I eat at home
that's why you're about to go to the
next level cuz if you keep eating like
you ate at home you'll keep being a boy
or a girl it's time to become man
woman
so don't don't worry about a little pain
my greatest asset is I was homeless so I
can't feel a whole lot of pain I've
already been alone there not a whole lot
it's notot not a whole lot of hurt I can
feel on a little paper on a little test
so I leave you I leave you listen to me
we have gotten to a point where it's
midterms and we moving forward the days
of you getting money I'm not saying we
quitting but I'm saying a day has got to
go from external to internal you have to
give it everything you got no more TV no
more parties no more playing if you
don't have a 4.0 what you need to be
doing is studying get off the phone I I
I'm sorry I'm not available until the
end of this
[Music]
year no I'm for real you reached the
right number but you called me at the
wrong time call me back January
1st I'm about to get busy
now huh I want you to have a countdown
of your own and say when the countdown
is over with a real sh watching me cuz
when I was homeless I knew something was
wrong I knew that wasn't the best of me
and one day I said well a real Eric
Thomas please stand
up with a real Eric Thomas please stand
up stop being this High School Dropout
stop giving up stop sleeping on the
street stop walking up and down FCO
Avenue like you ain't got nothing and
get your GED stop being afraid to take a
test stop being afraid to go to cop cuz
your daddy didn't go and your mama
didn't go stop being afraid and be the
best air time you can be but listen to
me it's going to be hard it took me 12
years to get a 4-year degree but I got
it and guess what on a degree it don't
have dates so if it took you four and it
took me 12 it don't show up
nowhere but I'm exactly where I want to
be because I realize I got to commit my
very being to this thing I got to I got
to breathe it I got to eat it I got to
sleep it and until you get there you'll
never be a successful in life but once
you get there I guarantee you the world
is yours so work hard and you can have
whatever it is you want thank you guys
for your
[Applause]
time