what's the Millenial question apparently
Millennials as a generation
a group of people who were born
approximately 1984 and after are tough
to manage and they're accused of being
entitled and narcissistic
self-interested unfocused lazy but
entitled is the big one and and because
they confound leadership so much what's
happening is leaders are asking the
Millennials what do you want and
Millennials are saying we want to work
in a place with purpose love that we
want to make an impact you know whatever
that means we want free food and bean
bags and so somebody articulates some
sort of purpose there's lots of free
food and there's bean bags and yet for
some reason they're still not happy and
that's because you that they're missing
there's a there's a missing piece what
I've learned is that there I can break
it down into four pieces right there are
four four things four characteristics
one is parenting the other one is
technology
third is impatience and the fourth is
environment the generation that we call
the Millennials too many of them grew up
subject to not my words failed parenting
strategies you know where for example
they were told that they were special
all the time they were told that they
have anything they want in life just
because they want it right they were
told some of them got into honors
classes not because they deserved it but
because their parents complained and
some of them got a is not because they
earned them but because the teachers
didn't want to deal with the parents
some kids got participation medals they
got a medal for coming in last right
which the science we know is pretty
clear which is it devalues the metal and
the reward for those who actually work
hard and that actually makes the person
who comes in last to feel embarrassed
because they know they didn't deserve it
so actual makes me feel worse right so
you take this group of people and they
graduate school and they get a job and
the thrust and turn it into the real
world and in an instant they find out
they're not special their moms can't get
them a promotion
that you get nothing for coming in last
and by the way you can't just have it
because you want it right and in an
instant the entire self-image is
shattered and so you have an entire
generation that's growing up with lower
self-esteem than previous generations
the other problem to compound it is
we're growing up in a facebook Instagram
world in other words we're good at
putting filters on things we're good at
showing people that life is amazing even
though I'm depressed right
and so everybody sounds tough and
everybody sounds like they got it we'll
figure it out and the reality is there's
very little toughness and most people
don't have it figured out and so when
the more senior people say what we do
they sound like this is what you got at
it and they have no clue so you have an
entire generation growing up with lower
self-esteem than previous generations
right through no fault of their own
through no fault of their own right they
were dealt a bad hand right now let's
add in technology we know that
engagement with social media and our
cell phones releases a chemical called
dopamine that's why when you get a text
feels good right
so you know we've all had it or you're
feeling a little bit down or feeling a
bit lonely and so you send out ten texts
to ten friends you know high high high
high high because it feels good when you
get a response right right it's why we
count the likes it's why we go back ten
times to see if and if it's going if our
my Instagram is growing slower I would
do something wrong do they not like me
anymore right the trauma for young kids
to be unfriended right because we know
when you get it you get a hit a dopamine
which feels good it's why we like it
it's why we keep going back to it
dopamine is the exact same chemical that
makes us feel good when we smoke when we
drink and when we gamble in other words
it's highly highly addictive right we
have age restrictions on smoking
gambling and alcohol and we have no age
restrictions and social media and cell
phones which is the equivalent of
opening up the liquor cabinet and saying
to our teenagers hey by the way this
adolescence thing if it gets you down
but that's basically what's happening
that's basically what's happening right
that's basically what happened you have
an entire generation that has access to
an addictive numbing to chemical
dopamine through social media and cell
phones as they're going through the high
stress of adolescents why is this
important
almost every alcoholic discovered
alcohol when they were teenagers when
we're very very young the only approval
we need is the approval of our parents
and as we go through adolescence we make
this transition where we now need the
approval of our peers very frustrating
for our parents very important for us
that allows us to acculturate outside of
our immediate families into the broader
tribe right it's a highly highly
stressful and anxious period of our
lives and we're supposed to learn to
rely on our friends some people quite by
accident discover alcohol and numbing
effects of dopamine to help them cope
with the stresses and anxieties of
adolescence unfortunately that becomes
hardwired in their brains and for the
rest of their lives when they suffer
significant stress they will not turn to
a person they will turn to the bottle
social stress financial stress career
stress that's pretty much the primary
reasons why an alcoholic drinks right
what's happening is because we're out
allowing unfettered access to these
dopamine producing devices and media
basically it's becoming hardwired and
what we're seeing is as they grow older
they to many kids don't know how to form
deep meaningful relationships their
words not mine they will admit that many
of their friendships are superficial
they will admit that their friends that
they don't count on their friends they
don't rely on their friends they have
fun with their friends but they also
know that their friends will cancel out
them that something better comes along
deep meaningful relationships are not
there because they never practice the
skillset and worse they don't have the
coping mechanisms to deal with stress so
when significant stress starts to show
up in their lives they're not turning to
a person they're turning to a device
they're turning to social media they're
turning to these things which offer
temporary relief we know the science is
clear we know that people who spend more
time on Facebook so far higher rates of
depression than people spend less time
on Facebook write these things balanced
alcohol is not bad too much alcohol is
bad gambling is fun too much gambling is
dangerous right there's nothing wrong
with social media and cell phones it's
the imbalance right if you're sitting at
dinner with your friends and you're
texting somebody who's not there that's
a problem that's an addiction if you're
sitting in a meeting with people you're
supposed to be listening to and speak
and you put your phone on the table face
up or face down I don't care that sends
a subconscious message to the room that
you're not just you're just not that
important to me right now right that's
what happens and the fact that you
cannot put it away it's because you are
addicted right if you wake up and you
check your phone before you say good
morning to your girlfriend boyfriend or
spouse you have an addiction and like
all addiction in time it'll destroy
relationships it'll cost time and it'll
cost money and will make your life worse
right so you have a generation growing
up with lower self-esteem that doesn't
have the coping mechanisms to do with
stress stress right now you add in the
sense of impatience right they've grown
up in a world of instant gratification
you want to buy something you go on
Amazon it arrives the next day you want
to watch a movie log on and watch your
movie you don't check movie times you
want to watch your TV show binge you
don't even have to wait week to week to
week right I know people who skip
seasons just so they can binge at the
end of the season right Instagram if
occasion you want to go on a date you
don't even have to learn how to be like
you don't even have to learn and
practice that skill you don't have to be
the uncomfortable and which this is yes
when you mean known says no when you
mean no but yes when you you have to
swipe right bang I'm a stud right you
don't have to learn the social coping
mechanisms right everything you want you
can have instantaneously everything you
want instant gratification except job
satisfaction and strength of
relationships
there ain't no app for that they are
slow meandering uncomfortable messy
processes and so I keep meeting these
wonderful fantastic idealistic
hard-working smart kids they've just
graduated school they're in their
entry-level job I sit down with them
when I go how's it going they go I think
I'm going to quit I'm like why they're
like I'm not making an impact I'm like
you've been here eight months it's as if
they're standing at the foot of a
mountain and they have this abstract
concept called impact that they want to
have in the world which is the summit
what they don't see is the mountain I
don't care if you go up the mountain
quickly or slowly but there's still a
mountain and so what this young
generation needs to learn
is patience that some things that really
really matter like love or job
fulfillment joy love of life
self-confidence a skill set any of these
things all of these things take time
sometimes you can expedite pieces of it
but the overall journey is arduous and
long and difficult and if you don't ask
for help and learn that skill set you
will fall off the mountain or you will
the worst case scenario the worst case
scenario and we're already seeing it the
worst case scenario is we're seeing
increase in suicide rates we're seeing
an increase in this generation we're
seeing an increase in accidental deaths
due to drug overdoses we're seeing more
and more kids drop out of school or take
leaves of absence due to depression
unheard of these are this is this is
really bad the best case scenario the
bet those are all bad cases right the
best case scenario is you'll have an
entire population growing up and going
through life and just never really
finding joy they'll never really find
deep deep fulfillment in work or in life
they'll just just walk through life and
it'll G just it's fine how's your job
it's fine the same is yesterday how's
your relationship it's fine like that's
that's the best-case scenario which
leads me to the the fourth point which
is environment which is we're taking
this amazing group of young fantastic
kids would just dealt a bad hand it's no
fault of their own and we put them in
corporate environments that care more
about the numbers than they do about the
kids they care more about the short-term
gains than the long-term life of this
young human being we care more about the
year than the lifetime right and so we
are putting them in corporate
environments that aren't helping them
build their confidence that aren't
helping them learn the skills of
cooperation that aren't helping them
overcome the challenges of a digital
world and finding more balance that
isn't helping them overcome the need to
have instant gratification and teach
them the joys and impact and the
fulfilment you get from working hard
over on something for a long time
cannot be done in a month or even in a
year and so with thrusting to them them
in corporate environments in the worst
part about it is they think it's them
they blame themselves they can't they
think it's them who can't deal and so it
makes it all worse it's not I'm here to
tell them it's not them it's the
corporations it's the corporate
environment it's the total lack of good
leadership in our world today that is
making them feel the way they do they
would dealt a bad hand in it and I hate
to say it but it's the company's
responsibility
sucks to be you like we have no choice
right this is what we got and I wish
that society and their parents did a
better job they didn't so we're gonna
we're getting them in our companies and
we now have to pick up the slack we have
to work extra hard to figure out the
ways that we build their confidence we
have to work extra hard to find ways to
teach them social the social skills that
they're missing out on
there should be no cell phones and
conference rooms none zero and I don't
mean the kind of like sitting outside
waiting to text I mean like when you're
sitting and waiting for a meeting to
start nobody go this is what we all do
we all sit here and wait for the meeting
to start meaning starting ok we start
the meeting no that's not how
relationships are formed remember we
talked about it's the little things
relationships are formed this way we're
waiting for a meeting to start we go
how's your dad I heard he's in hospital
oh he's really good thanks for asking
he's actually at home now oh I'm really
glad it was really amazing I know it was
really scary girl that's how you form
relationships hey did you ever get that
report on oh my god no I didn't I'll
help you out I've totally are can I help
you out with that
really that's how trust forms trust
doesn't form at an event in a day even
bad times don't form trust immediately
it's the slow steady consistency and we
have to create mechanisms where we allow
for those little innocuous interactions
to happen but when we allow cell phones
and company mist okay have the meeting
and then my favorite is like when
there's a cell phone there and you go
like this you go
it rings and go I'm not gonna answer
that mr. magnanimous you know when
you're out for dinner with your friends
like I do this with my friends when
we're going out for dinner and we're
leaving together we'll leave our cell
phones at home who are we calling maybe
one of us will bring the phone in case
we need to call an uber or take a
picture of our meal
bang come on I'm not I'm an idealist but
I'm not insane I don't even I mean it
looked really good
we'll take one phone and so it's like an
alcoholic the reason you take the
alcohol out of the house is because we
cannot trust our willpower we're just
not strong enough but when you remove
the temptation it actually makes it a
lot easier and so when you just say
don't check your phone people literally
will go like this and somebody would go
to the bathroom and what's the first
thing we do because I wouldn't want to
look around the restaurant for a minute
and a half you know but if you don't
have the phone you just kind of enjoy
the world and that's where ideas happen
the constant constant constant
engagement is not where you have
innovation and ideas ideas happen when
our minds wander we go and you see
something on I bet they could do that
that's called innovation right but we're
taking away all those little moments
right
you should not end none of us none of us
should charge our phones by our beds we
should be charging our phones in the
living rooms right remove the temptation
you wake up in the middle of night cause
you can't sleep you won't check your
phone which makes it worse but if it's
in the living room it's relaxed it's
fine hiya
but it's my alarm clock fine alarm clock
they cost $8 I'll buy you in a while