welcome everyone it's my uh pleasure to
uh welcome all of you to uh Professor
David Patterson's talk uh David
Patterson probably needs no introduction
uh he's been a professor of computer
science at uh University of California
Berkeley for 40 years now and uh he's
made a lot of pioneering contributions
in computer systems a lot of which are
Technologies we use at Google and
elsewhere so risk uh reduce instruction
at computers uh raid network of
workstations and a lot more uh he has a
pretty long bio here I didn't realize he
has won 35 Awards and all of them are
pretty prestigious uh National Academy
of engineering National Academy of
Sciences Silicon Valley Engineering all
of Fame I E1 nman medal and I'm sure I'm
offending some significant award by not
saying that but uh he's had a very
distinguished career and this talk today
uh in his own words uh collects advice
that I wish I had been given when I
started my career and given how
distinguished that's been uh I think
it's a talk we are all going to uh
benefit from so welcome well uh this is
a what happened is I uh decided uh uh
somebody wrote me these slides about how
to have a bad career been out there for
a long time and they asked me if there
was a video of it and I couldn't find
one uh I actually figured out that I
gave this talk first 20 years ago but
I've given it over the years so I
decided to record it at Berkeley and it
ended up and I announced that my plans
to retire that went two days before this
so uh it it got a lot of visibility so
and it's fun to come here as as far as I
can tell all of my oh yeah sorry as far
as I can tell
on all of my former students are going
to end up here
sometime also have to ask them if
they're leaving where they are I know
where they're ending up and so it's it's
it feels like it's a home week here as I
said this is the advice I wish I would
have had uh in my uh career uh this got
started uh I got about 30 years ago uh
decided want to give advice on talk so I
wrote how to give a bad talk talk and
that was a lot of fun and about 10 years
later how to have a bad career and and
uh about a couple years ago I did how to
have a bad Research Center so this is my
bad
series uh now I'm just going to put the
uh if you're interested uh these slides
are certainly available as well as the
talk and there's a lot of papers and
things that you can site if you want to
read more about it and I'd like to thank
a bunch of people for making suggestions
that I've incorporated or their careers
inspired them one of those of those two
uh so uh the parts there's two parts to
the talk the kind of tongue and cheek
how to have a bad career and then how to
avoid a bad career and then I'll open up
for questions and answers and then I'll
wrap things up whenever we have to wrap
things up and take the last five or 10
minutes talking about my story how I got
here and what works for me so uh so you
want to be a leader of the field
especially if you're an Academia so how
could you do that well invent a new
field is a really good way to do that
and you want to be the only person in
that field so how can you invent a field
and be the only person
uh well one way is you know different
from other fields you want to be the
Lone Ranger and a way you can be the
Lone Ranger the only one is there is
your personality can help uh can help if
you adopt the Primadonna
personality and some people don't know
who what a primadonna is but if you
adopt that personality nobody will want
to work with you and you can drive
people away and then you'll be the
world's leading expert cuz you're the
only one in that field in terms of the
research Horizons for your new field you
want to be have a lot of flexibility on
success uh you know you don't want to
get too fine and uh and if you say it's
20 years out then you know you got 19
safe years right and nobody's going to
accuse you of doing engineering work if
it's 20 20 years
out and uh you know stick to that topic
for your whole career now if I'd only
followed that advice my dissertation was
on micro programming if I'd stuck to
this I would absolutely be the world's
expert in microprogramming partly
because no one's built a computer with
micro code in 25 years and you kind of
think of it like it's like fashion you
like skinny jeans are popular now or
they were popular 25 years ago if you
just kept them you could reuse your own
Gene so research is like that wait
they'll come back to
you okay uh let complexity be your guide
confuse thy enemies the best thing you
can say it's so complicated I can't
can't understand what you're talking
about and that's that that you done a
good
job one reason is it's easier to claim
credit for things if somebody else has
done some work you can say well that was
in my paper and since they don't
understand it how can they contradict
you
right the other thing that's surprising
it's really a lot easier to be
complicated you read the first end
papers and then it's you figure out the
next one and people publish it it's
really much harder to be simpler than to
be complicated so that's the easy way to
do it and this sentence captures it
right if it's UNS simple how could you
dis sish colleagues departments around
the world be positively appreciative and
so on so on that there you go that's a
way to speak and to talk never be proven
wrong the first thing you want to do is
don't Implement anything it's hard to
prove you wrong if you don't implement
it now if some out of control colleague
builds something then whatever you do
don't run any quantitative experiments
if you if they're not quantitative then
you can't be proven
wrong uh you've got the intuition you
can just kind of extrapolate with the
results there are put that in without
any
experiments and you know your job isn't
to help the critics you know that's
their job to figure out uh don't help
them out now uh another reason is that
clearly the success of the career is to
publish as much as you can and it takes
time to build and to uh measure so if
you don't do that you can get more
results and have a more successful
career if somebody does it the last
thing you want to do is run any
benchmarks because then they could
compare your results to other things the
uh advice of being
uh that uh you've got those those safe
years and the benchmarks can
just the the way you get out of that is
to say well these this computer is for
future uh programs not for current
programs and then uh these benchmarks
are too Antiquated to run on my computer
now the other thing that we do in
computer science is we uh reject all the
past you know we're a new field we're
both science and engineering so we're
not hidebound
by oldfashioned things like the
scientific method we have the computer
scientific method instead of a
hypothesis we have a
hunch a sequence of experiments we know
that sequential is slow so what we do we
change one one experiment all the
parameters at once that's much faster
than the sequential approach Paralis is
a good idea and rather than prove or
disprove
hypothesis we discard if it doesn't
support the hunch you know we've got
there's lots of data it's a big data
throw away the data there's still plenty
of data
left um and document for others
reproduce we've already done it we'll
have more results of the field if we
don't waste our time trying to reproduce
each other's results that's the computer
scientific method don't be distracted by
others avoid
feedback uh you know a big part of that
is conversation and if you don't say
anything people might think you're not
very smart so the Corel are of that is
loud is smart okay so be loud in
conversations even when you don't know
what you're talking about people will
think you know what you're talking
about um if you're the words leading
expert you don't really need to read
other things because you're the expert
right uh and you don't want to you don't
have to be interact with others because
they're not as good as you are in terms
of doing reviews for paper if it's
simple and obvious it insult the prior
authors if you accept something simple
and obvious they probably thought of it
so you should reject it uh if their
quantitative results and I've gotten
this review before well I already knew
that so there's no surprise to reject it
and just you know everything else you
might as well just
reject uh you know they're kind of
competitors to you in some way and if
they P paper doesn't get published then
you win so that's a good
guideline now publishing journals is
technology transfer you're the leading
person in the world you're the expert
all you have to do is write in the
journal it's not your job to make it
understandable to others to the ordinary
Engineers going to conferences just
wastes some of your valuable time that
you could be coming up with new ideas
and you know having to interact with uh
industry and things like that that's a
Time waster you write the journals
you're
done now clearly the winner is the one
with the most papers at the end of the
career so I've come up with this Pyramid
of Success for publication and it
follows the rule four and and the
guideline is the lpu leas poal unit the
lpu is good for you so you start off
with one idea then with rule of four you
get four Journal papers out of that uh
with a miracle of world processing then
you can get 16 extended abstracts and 64
technical reports from one single idea
that's 84 Publications I guess that and
then in terms of getting credit for it
uh my advice is to change your name to
the Swedish spelling of
Anderson and then and then and then
there's awkward time oh how are we going
to put the office on the table will say
well I've always done it alphabetically
you all my papers that all right writing
cams for a bad
career uh Thou shalt not Define terms
that's what dictionaries are before and
explaining things that'll just insult
the reader so you want to be a little
bit more mysterious than
that uh Thou shalt use replace I will
build with I have been built you know
probably by the time your paper gets
published in a journal somebody have
implemented it so it's okay to kind of
do
that V sh not mention drawbacks to your
report report that's not your job that's
the job of the critics to figure out
drawbacks you know if you hide that
they'll never notice it uh Thou shalt
not reference any papers again except
for maybe your own or at your
institution and if if the papers were
any good they'd be people at your
institution so don't you don't do that
and then you should publish before
implementing because that's when your
system is the fastest you know
okay talk Commandments for a bad career
this is my bad career talk uh th Shelt
not be neat you know why take the time
to spend it on your slides to you know
fix spelling errors grammatical errors
you've got to you could spend that time
on
Research Thou shalt not wite space you
know you use up a lot of slides that's a
lot of kilobytes being wasted there you
can save like 100 kilobytes a year which
saves some
money uh Thou shalt not covet brevity do
you really want to sustain The
Stereotype that Engineers can't write
right you want to show full
paragraphs uh beautiful beautiful
English and read it
aloud uh Thou shalt cover the naked
slides I'll show you what I mean by that
later but you don't want to expose the
whole slide to everybody and and shock
them uh Thou shalt not print large the
important people sit in the front
right so who cares about guys in the
back uh shalt not use color use of color
indicates uh you know uncareful research
you're emphasizing some words over
others and it's just too showy to use
color Thou shalt not illustrate
confucious says uh a picture is worth
10,000 words who cares about the wisdom
of the ages
right and uh Thou shalt not make eye
contact you want to be humble kind of
pretend to be humble keep your eyes down
and you know try not to let anybody see
you uh Thou shalt not skip slides long
talk I guarantee in this room somebody
has done looked up at their looked at
their watch see how many slides they
have then their solution is I'll just
talk faster right that's what people do
you prepare the slides they want to see
them all and if you have to just cut off
the conclusions the last couple of
slides if you run out of time and then
this is the Golden Rule this one can
save you if even if you violate the
others Thou shalt not practice how can
you be spontaneous if you practice right
you'll it'll feel it'll feel practiced
if you practice so don't do that that's
the last thing you should
do uh so here's an example of doing it
it's actually says PowerPoint but it's
it's using Google Slides so uh trying
these commandments so uh print small now
these features somebody some engineer
Google put these features in so you have
to use them to be a good Google employee
um so you want to hide your naked slides
there that's a some variety but again no
use of
color there you go that's another
dramatic entrance and then uh this last
the next one is just my favorite I'm
glad somebody put the time in to put
this in because it's very
useful there you go but
a okay so that was the bad career advice
let's talk about Alternatives career uh
this is taken from my career which span
40 years so it's kind of an academic I
hope it'll apply to here it's in systems
not in theory uh and I'll go through
these pieces uh one by one so advice to
writing uh bad papers uh and I again I
put some writing tips there the writing
tips actually have some grammatical
errors in them following my bad
tradition but uh you can go look take a
look so do the opposite of the bad paper
Commandments uh do Define your terms
distinguish will do from have done if
you're writing for critical review
reviewers are very skeptical people
they're going to assume the worst they
are much more impressed if you point out
the drawbacks rather than they have to
discover
them uh and you know you have to measure
performance and reference the work to be
a
scholar and the good news is you guys
build a wonderful service to make that
much easier to do these days in scholar
uh the great the best piece of advice I
ever got was to read Strunk and white uh
Strunk believed in brevity so much he
cherish Brey so much he couldn't write a
long book the book itself is maybe 80
Pages or so and it's chalk full of good
advice then uh you know we do this the
advices basically go kind of top down
you just write write a onepage outline
with a tentative uh title with budgets
how much you need to write a lot of
writing that saves a lot of writing if
you don't have to do it then a paragraph
map which is a topic sentence as it goes
the way through and it includes uh
figures and captions even today in 2016
it takes forever on a computer to draw a
figure and since you might throw that
you're probably going to throw that
figure right to change it the best
technology to do that today is go to a
whiteboard you even have colored pens
take a little self phone picture and
stick that in your document that'll take
you you know one tenth the time as
trying to do something on a computer
because you know you might throw it away
and then re write the
draft um I like the Scientific American
style which has really long captions not
everybody does that but you can move
text in there and associate with the
figure I think that works well I really
like tables a lot there's a lot of Drey
facts I love putting them into tables
that works well for
me uh then in terms of when you're
starting to polish the text read aloud
your ear is better than your eyes when I
start reading a document and I I forget
and I stop saying it out loud I I lose
track but if you hear the words you can
hear terrible sentences and grammatical
errors if you hear it there's technology
and fact I was I just learned about this
thing it was from an English Professor
who talk a massive open upline course at
Berkeley said why aren't you using a
grammar checker and she said this is the
world's best one Pearson writer and it
cost you a whole $20 a year and it will
prevent terrible grammatical errors and
even help style in fact I think I was
thinking I should you guys should buy
this it's it's one of the things you're
missing from Google Documents is a
really and this is the world's best one
uh I I'm it's a it's I'm impressed that
they can pull this off and then you get
feedbacks and Friends of course to get
feedbacks and friends if you're writing
to a deadline you actually have to get
it done early which seems to be science
fiction for graduate students at least
but get it done early then he gives you
time to give your friends feedback you
can iterate and if you don't do that if
you're writing something for review then
who's your reviewer it's the program
committee and what I've seen sitting on
program committees is a lot of the times
the paper gets rejected not because you
didn't do something it's because the
program committee didn't understand what
you did and why if you interact with
Outsiders you've got this chance of
clearing that up that if you don't as
suppos if you just look at it yourself
okay how to write not write bad papers
bad talks basically do the opposite of
the bad Commandments there's two parts
preparation and practice uh most people
take about two minutes a slide for some
reason I take one minute a slide I don't
know why um you should plan on that a
minute or a minute and a half so you
have plenty of time and leave time for
questions since that's some of the most
important parts don't despite Google
Engineers putting in spinning text you
know don't do
that uh and then you know it's not a
speech it's the first time you do it
it's a talk so you don't have to
memorize it but have notes
ready practice uh is the key uh you want
to do dry runs with friends to get
feedback if you're giving a professional
talk you know the way you make
impression is not only to give a talk
but how you answer the questions I think
for those of us in the field a while
when you see somebody give a dynamic
talk and they really nail the questions
you pay attention to that
uh and then so your practice ought to
have really tough questions so you can
practice the tough questions and then uh
with modern cell phones uh you can
record yourself you not only your audio
you can watch yourself it's you know I
got to tell you it's going to be a
humbling experience you'll hear the
crutches that you have in your verbal
speech I start a lot of sentences with
so I say h you'll be shocked how bad it
is but everybody does it and this is the
way you get better and I practice
everything I I think of it I practice my
talks just to show the students you're
supposed to practice your talks but I
practice my Award acceptance speeches
and they tear them
apart I would think an accepted speech
was pretty good but no no they get make
them better so
practice okay now uh the other thing
that I was going to do in this talk is
uh is quote Richard Hamming Richard
Hamming actually came to Berkeley when I
was young and Professor a laral
professor and he gave this talk you and
your research which is more or less how
to do great research like me and so uh
Richard Hamming of Hamming code you know
Hamming distance the Reon memories don't
make mistakes uh spent his career mostly
at Bell labs and it's pretty clear from
watching these videos he's a very
opinionated guy he he doesn't he's not
say well maybe you should do this he
says do this but he watched careers over
Bell Labs he saw people fail he saw
people succeed and I'll quote quote him
show one minute seconds every time so
this is him talking about the importance
of communication and you'll get his
personality from this
one which brings me to the topic of
communication you need to learn to
communicate orally in talks like this
written and written reports and Casual
conversations in the middle of a
conference you have to be able to get up
and say that's wrong for these reasons
bing bing bing bing and you win if you
sit around and say well I'll write a
report tomorrow after I've thought about
it some more the decision is made we go
ahead and it doesn't matter what you do
then the ability to communicate at three
levels now how do you learn it you can
read books if you want to but forget it
the way you learn as far as I'm
concerned is every time you go to a talk
you listen not only to the talk but to
the style it's done what talks are
effective why were they effective what
aspects of the speaker could you
adapt okay that's for Hamming and then
which brings me to the topic of
communication oops you need to learn to
communicate
or it talks like stop
stop uh and then he uh and there's
another he gave this talk lots of times
this is the one it's on your YouTube
right that's how I found it but there
was a text one before and he said in my
early days I think you should spend as
much time in polishing and presenting as
you did in the original research now at
least 50% of it has to go in the
presentation now if you know hamming's
idea of the me of how do you encode
memory it's beautifully presented that
almost everybody can understand so that
was an example of him he thought not
just came up with the math but he laid
it out and had a very simple encoding
thing it's almost like a parlor trick is
you can put a bit pattern in there and
tell you which one is wrong from the way
he does it he made it very easy to
understand and as a result every single
computer in the world uses his idea but
that was an example of him following his
old advice this come
on right I think I can get and stopped
okay uh okay leading a project now I'm
going to go through through the uh uh I
think I said
this
um so academics have bad benchmarks
papers or maybe even citations rather
than impact is what you're trying to do
I didn't realize when I started there's
I have six phases for leading your
project and we'll go through the
selecting a problem picking a solution
running a project finishing a project
evaluating it transferring technology so
let me go through each of those let's go
back Richard Hamming again he's going to
talk about the a problem and so I said
do mind if I join you so I sit down and
we start talk about chemistry and said
set the set the stage here so so here's
this pretty opinionated guy who studies
how people can be great he's it's kind
of a hobby of his so he at Bell lab's
you know one of the greatest research
institutions in the history of this
country he's been having lunch with
physicists but they all they started
winning Nobel prizes inventing the
transistor and things like that and got
promoted so he had to find a new group
so he decided to hang out with the
chemist so he just kind of butts his way
in as this Outsider uh to talk with the
chemists other things for a long while
and finally one day I walk in and say if
what you're working on is not important
and it's not likely to lead to important
things why are you working on
it after that I ate with the engineers
that was spring in the fall Going Down
The Long Corridor Bell Labs my friend
chem stopped me and said you know
Hamming that remark of yours got
underneath my skin I've spent the summer
thinking about the important problems in
my field I have not changed my research
but I think it was well worth the time I
say thank you Dave and walk on about two
weeks later I know he made head of the
department about 10 or 12 years ago I
notic he is member of the National
Academy of engineering
I have never heard of anything about any
other person that chemistry table not
one the one man who could hear if what
you're doing is not important not likely
important why are you doing it the one
man who could did become important he
did succeed the rest of them who
couldn't hear
didn't it's that
simple if you don't work on important
problems you are not going to do
important things except by the dumbest
of dumb
luck and you realize when he's giving
these talks the chemist that he was
sitting with were still around I could
hear him give these
talks that's Charming
guy okay so picking selecting a problem
when I started Berkeley I just jumped in
and I'll tell you about it in the next
one invent a new field and stick to it
no try to do real stuff make sure other
people think it's important not not just
you uh it's particularly easy to do that
in Academia you're aiming for this
positive impact big impact on computer
science and
engineering uh and stick to it to your
whole career I I think in this fast
that's not what I did in this fast
moving field why not instead do a bunch
of short projects because a lot of
research projects aren't going to
work uh it always the these things
always take longer than you expect uh
and you know how are you going to know
if you work on something for 20 years
that this is going to be an important
problem for 20
years and what we found by doing lots of
five-year projects is that learning was
more of the number of projects than it
was the number of years as you tackle
something it was the new thing you
learned
from uh and then a lot of times as I'll
say research doesn't work out and you'd
like to fail you know fail sooner rather
than fail
later uh what's worked well for us is
multidisiplinary multi-investigator
projects trying to have somebody from
multiple fields on a single
team uh and then to try and figure out
the strength and weaknesses of your
local environment at universities are
different there strengths that obviously
Google has that and there's weaknesses
too so try and figure out something that
matches your
environment and make sure it's exciting
that you want to work on it for several
years and what I've found is a
compelling prototype that can if we can
build this thing it's really going to be
amazing is is
inspirational okay so that's selecting
the problem my first project when I got
to Berkeley 40 years ago I spent about a
week thinking about it in joining some
other faculty and it was ridiculously
ridiculously ambitious three Hardware
faculty we're design our own instruction
set build our own chips build our own
interconnection network switches board
systems operating systems we didn't have
any experience in any of it we didn't
have any research funding we didn't have
any Computing or CAD tools so what
happened from all that you know a couple
of papers right not bad for academics
fortunately I took a a sabatical during
that time and went away and gave me
chance to think about things differently
and I came back and did the rist stuff
otherwise I wouldn't have uh tenure
today uh picking a solution let
complexity be your guide no keep things
simple unless you've got a really good
reason not to uh I came up with this
phrase early in my career is
intelligence beans on any project you
have a sack of intelligence beans that
you get to spend so decide where you
want to spend your intelligence beans uh
and then where it doesn't matter you
know you can use the common Solutions
and the best result you can possibly get
is afterwards for them to say anyone
could have thought of that right that
doesn't seem so complicated anybody
could have thought that that's that
you've achieved things well complexity
costs everything you know longer design
construction testing and debugging and
these delays lessen the impact of what
you do so try and keep it simple it's
hard to keep things simple but that's
the goal the computer scientific nope
you want to run experiments to discover
real problems is my John oout says you
use your intuition to ask questions not
to answer them we're really smart people
we can make up what we think the answer
is but that doesn't mean they're right
what we need is to figure out the
experiments to figure out the real
answers so you know at Berkeley they
asked me well how do you how do you pick
a problem and solution uh what we've
done over the these years these fiveyear
projects
is uh we start before the end of one
project we start meeting for at least a
year to start talking about the next one
we spend that much time thinking about
it typically what we've done is saying
what are some interesting technology
trends that are happening over the next
5 or 10 years that will shape the future
of computing 8 to 10 years out to see if
the mix of these Trends have some new
opportunity for risk it was probably uh
computer scientists were were being able
to do uh integrated circuit design there
was Morris law that was taking off so a
32-bit microprocessor was plausible
what's the right way to design such a
microprocessor for raid uh personal
personal computers were getting popular
they started building hard diss for them
these socalled small hard diss they were
in expensive uh performance for for
input output was slow processors were
getting faster risk this performance was
slow maybe we could do something with a
lot of them uh for the network or
workstation projects not only were
workstations getting really fast but
there were beginning to be uh local area
network switches can we just build a big
computer out of a bunch of these
components and then how that
work uh you know another thing that
we've noticed over the years is when
you're all by yourself and you're going
to work in a new field it's very scary
but if there's a group of you with
different areas and you kind of go after
this thing there's kind of safety in
numbers you aren't all risking your
careers working on machine learning but
the three of you working together seems
not quite as scary to be able to do
that and uh you know the big thing is to
when You' got these ideas is to find
people people whose opinion you trust
and try and uh get their feedback to
help you shape your vision you don't
have to do exactly what they say but you
ought to hear what they're say and then
pick a good name the Apparently in some
parallel universe I'm in the marketing
department but uh it's not that hard you
know I have these friends who show off
their their Latin education who pick
some name nobody can possibly spell and
they even have a word for it now you
pick the name and then you back fill in
the acronym and so they're called
backronyms right nobody's ever going to
remember that the the pro one of the
projects my younger colleagues picked is
a Spire it's actually 11 or 12 words
nobody but him can remember it so if
that's true you're you're going to use
the acronym model it's got to be three
or four letters if anybody's going to
remember it uh you want to the way we do
it is put a bunch of words on the on the
wall that describes the project vowels
are really valuable and you want to try
three or four letters three or four
letters that are an English word that
kind of have something to do with the
project so but I'm a available as a
consultant uh running a project do you
want to avoid feedback uh that's one of
themes no we do these periodic project
reviews with Outsiders we've been doing
them for 30 years twice a year three day
how many people here have been to uh
Berkeley style Retreat all right that's
like a dozen people here
uh and um we The Outsiders are valued
and you know it's huge benefits to doing
this uh at the end we get the feedback
from everybody and we don't argue with
that feedback we try and understand it
it also creates deadlines which are
tough in everywhere but particularly in
Academia builds team
spirit and for the people working on it
gives them a chance to communicate and
spread their ideas interact with with
others uh consider midcourse correction
our first project that I was doing was a
a multiprocessor the risk ideas were
just starting to catch on but they
hadn't been commercial yet but by Midway
through the project there were
commercial chips like myips and Spark we
should have redirected our project to be
use the commercial processors but I felt
like that was you know breaking our
promise and you know we should have
stuck the ones we did customly but we
would had a much bigger impact with a
multiprocessor risk project then if we'
use commercial instruction set so that's
part of our culture now it's a five-year
project two and a half years in maybe
the world has changed in some way and
you should take advantage of it an
example of that would have been the rad
lab which was a couple of projects ago
we were doing internet services and then
cloud computing got popular in it so we
you know embraced that and that became a
big theme of the red
lab uh pick the size the members of the
team
carefully uh you know tough
personalities are hard in everybody not
just tough personalities for faculty
even tough personalities for students
right you know it it can make it no fun
to come to work so trying and get good
people I think Berkeley consciously
tries not to hire Pradas which makes it
nicer and if you know if you have one
expert per area it's a little easier my
colleague Kathy yelick I've got opinions
about programming language and compilers
but when she speaks you know I listen
right I don't and that makes it easier
to do things don't be distracted by
others this is not going to be so
radical for you guys but about 10 years
ago we went to an open uh uh
collaborative thing where we got rid of
Faculty offices what was happening is
that the students were staying home
because the computers were just as fast
and the network just as fast as home as
they were at work and whether this is
good for a company or not I'll leave to
you but it's terrible for research
because it's not just put your head down
and plow ahead we got to talk to people
because you're not sure where you're
supposed to be
going uh so we put it into the open
space uh and what now that I've read
about it what you're shooting for is
communication and concentration so
people can come in work they have to be
able to concentrate enough to get the
work done but you want to have
spontaneous communication which leads to
Innovation so bump into each other and
have meeting
rooms uh we've got the meeting rooms
optimized for discussions and phone
calls we came Jeff Waltz brought us
probably 10 years ago and we saw what
you guys did with your conference rooms
and we imitated that uh at uh and like
you guys we have kitchens and free
drinks we can't we can't do food but uh
we can do drinks um and amazing thing it
accelerates research who would have
thought space could accelerate research
uh it it was uh startling uh what
happened we went from faculty offices
that had kind of whiteboards there that
were filled with faculty reminders when
you came in you got to work on like one
square foot to put your ID in there
instead we had giant whiteboards uh
there was no writing pres you couldn't
reserve it in the high-tech way we
copied it was with the cell phones uh it
came stimulating people came in more
there was more spontaneous
meetings uh and then we noticed the 0 to
60 time for new people went incredibly
faster in by having that kind kind of
environment so mate zaharia the uh in
his second semester there he gave a talk
at Carnegie melan and we'd never had
anybody do that before Nam mat zaharia
who's the founder of spark did a lot of
good things but it wasn't obvious then
that he was going to be that good as it
turned out and so maybe that had
something to do with
it uh and so Richard Hamming has
opinions on this based on his
experience which I'm sure you're not
surprised okay he's got two opinions the
first one is open versus closed doors
and the only way he can have this
opinion was to keep track of all of his
colleagues which ones kept the doors
closed which ones open which ones were
successful and he's here's his
ideas the example I've given you already
is working with a door closed or opener
if you work with your door closed you
won't be interrupted you get your work
done you work with your door open people
come byy and stop and chat and so on and
so
on but I've noticed very clearly at B
Laboratories those who were with the
door shut may be working just as hard 10
years later but they don't know what to
work on they are not connected with the
reality those who had the door open may
very well know what's
important now I cannot prove to you
whether the open door causes the open
mind or whe the open mind causes the
open door I Su suspect a both I can only
establish the correlation and it was
quite
spectacular almost always
the guy with the door closed were often
very well able very gifted but they seem
to work always on slightly the wrong
problem so you have to get wide feeling
for what is going
on okay and then he believed that so
much that this is how his his patterns
how he handled Friday afternoons about
the importance especially for
researchers you can start work really
hard but you could miss the really
important thing if by not
interacting at the urging of some other
people partly and partly in my own I
used to set aside Friday noon and Friday
afternoon for great thoughts meaning yes
I'll answer a telephone yes I'll sign a
sheet of paper but mainly what is the
effect of computing on
science what the hell am I doing with
this Computing
machine how is it going to affect
AT&T what should I be doing with
Computing what is the nature of
software my friends after a while I got
to know Friday afternoon's great
thoughts what's the nature of this that
and the other thing I spent 10% of my
time trying to answer the question what
are the important problems in my field
10% Friday afternoon straight
through don't do it Monday morning
because you'll be interrupted
immediately if you do it Friday
afternoon someone can linger around the
Saturday and Sunday if you do it Monday
morning there a hot conference at 10:00
in Bingo everything's broken up I use it
Friday afternoon for many many years I I
recommend that you find a regular time
to stop and think what are the important
things what is going on what is the
nature of what you are
doing what is the characteristic of the
job what are the fundamentals behind it
so you have some idea of where you're
headed so you can March in a uniform
Direction and get far rather than being
a drunken sail and getting
nowhere you're free to not ignore his
advice but then your career is that of a
drunken sailor okay
okay finishing your project I'll talk
about this some uh if people count the
number of projects you finish not the
ones you start right uh and successful
projects go through this unglamorous
hard phase of of trying to finish it and
it's because design is a lot more fun
it's a lot more fun to design things to
make stuff
work but uh you know some positive
things Fred Brooks one of my hero says
there's no winners on a losing team no
losers on a winning team if if you win
anybody in no matter what they did they
win improve productivity of team members
how can you do that uh organize each day
when are figuring out when you're most
alert uh when you need a nap or exercise
or
sleep uh when how often should you be
reading and writing uh programming and
email and what I found it for successful
colleagues they always used to do this
you know daily weekly and even every six
months to see how they're doing on their
career uh these days there's this idea
of agile scrum where you meet in the
same place at the same time and do
Sprints I think this is a pretty
effective
model and then reduce a project so if
it's late again Fred Brooks said adding
people to a late project makes it later
in his classic book the mythical man
month uh and finishing a project is how
you acquire taste how do you get gr
taste if you don't finish it you don't
know really what wrong and it helps you
pick good problems and find Simple
Solutions okay and then my friend John
Hennessy I guess uh president Stanford
said this a long time ago you can
quickly tell whether or not the authors
have ever built something and made it
work and if you never make it work you
don't acquire that taste evaluating
quantitatively never be proven wrong uh
nope if you can't be proven wrong then
you can't be proven
right and you have to you know we need
reproducible results you're trying to
get people to use your ideas if they
can't reproduce them they're not going
to take your word for
it so and you know for better for worse
benchmarks shaper field and especially
in the commercial world if we have good
ones it accelerates progress bad ones
then there's a choice between helping
sales or helping customers and often
sales
wins and then transferring technology
it's not just you write a paper and
everybody starts using it uh you have to
go out and stump it uh you know this
last year there's a RIS five which is an
effort to be able to have an open
instruction set so that be an open
alternative kind of like Linux is to
Microsoft Windows so I gave talks at the
you know at 10 universities this fall to
try and get the word out then if they
kind of like the ideas then they read
the
papers uh it of course you know if you
don't pick a good problem people aren't
going to be that interested and you can
tell if it's a good problem if more
people get interested over time rather
than your start to do that I think I'm
persuasive the way I change Minds is
with believable numbers and so the you
have to collect that quantitatively and
believe it the other thing I learned
late in my career is your personality
affects technology transfer there's this
person who I won't name who had a bunch
of interesting ideas and people wouldn't
use them and I talk to people in
Industry about they hated that guy they
hated that guy if there was any other
way to do it at all they would use it
because they would that would the last
thing they would do so you could be a
jerk if you have the only possible
solution but it's kind of hard to do
that in Computing maybe in biology you
can do that
uh and then product groups people don't
want to change product groups there's
risk associated with change so it's
worked for us uh and and this goes back
so Fred Brooks when he was a graduate
student his advisor was Howard Ain and
he Fred Brooks says I think these people
are going to steal your idea these
companies are looking at his idea at
Harvard University a drum memory System
Watch Out Howard and what Akin said in
southern ACC the problem in this
business isn't to keep people from
stealing your ideas it's making them
steal your ideas and that's that's still
true today 65 years later so what's
worked for us is to find one gold bold
group often not the leaders but some
bold group willing to take a shot on it
and they are successful and then kind of
the rest of the field is well and for us
it was Sun Microsystems for risk and EMC
for raid and Inky and then Google for
networks of workstations but it's kind
of like the rest of the field oh damn
they tried it it works okay we'll change
right
people don't really as much as people
enjoy ideas they don't want to take the
risk and then the other way of
transferring technology is to start a
company in my 40 Years everybody I've
talked to who's worked for a startup
likes it doing it once they they they
they absolutely now there's some people
who love doing it more than once a lot
of people once is enough but they
everybody thinks it was useful they
learn a lot uh and then if it works you
know it works out you see not just your
ideas but the product and of course you
can po L make a lot of money if that
works out and become famous the
downsides are that you know you learn
about things you might not want to learn
about but uh and particularly lawsuits
my friends who lawsuits that's less fun
and you don't get to do research and
development uh and then only 10% of the
startups make it right but but
nevertheless everybody thinks it was
worth it that for once in their life
maybe when you're younger so I didn't
really realize that there were six roles
to being a leader of a project and it
changes over time uh but that's uh
that's what I believe now now so
wrapping things up and there's time for
questions here is the goal is to have
impact is to change the way people do
Computing and Engineering a positive way
now I we do these five-year projects now
that my career is uh ending I've I will
do 12 right they overlap so I I've been
there 40 years not 60 years you can't
tell if a Project's successful for at
least 10 years and
the good news is three of them looked
like they were pretty successful they 10
years old so that's like kind of 25%
batting average which so I'm glad I did
a lot of projects uh there's two that
are finished but haven't uh you know it
hasn't been 10 years the rad lab did
spark and mesos those seem promising the
par lab did communication avoiding
algorithms Jim demo and this RIS five
stuff but you know we it'll take five or
seven years to know how significant it
was so maybe I'll get up to you know
five out of 12 which is like 40% but
most of the projects don't work so I'm
glad I did short
projects uh so solve a problem other
people care about you taste that you
acquire by finishing projects and then
uh whoops and and so okay and and I
think the key theme of running over my
career is is feedback is figuring out
ways to get feedback okay with that I'm
ready for
questions I think there a microphone
here oh there's one okay
questions without the first question
there won't be multiple question oh
there
is since you asked for hard questions
which of your projects did you enjoy the
most and which of them do you think had
the most impact which did I enjoy the
most ah I let me do the most impact I
because I'm kind of wrapping things up I
it's plausible raid had the biggest
impact
uh it's everybody uses it you know uh
the pap the original raid paper won
three test of time
Awards uh I I you know if I had it looks
to me as a as if I try to be a neutral
Observer probably raid is the most uh
significant so far which one did I enjoy
the most I try and always make projects
that I really love right I try to make
projects that if I was a graduate
student I just die to work on this
project uh
um you know that's
hard uh maybe children yeah which of my
children do I love the
most I don't know the good thing about
all the projects whether or not they
they're home runs is they produce great
students and uh and I didn't say that in
the slide there's almost 300 students in
those 12 projects that that have uh that
which was uh I was had fun adding that
number
up Jeff
so this isn't really a problem for for
most of us here but would you give
different advice to a pre-tenure
academic versus a post- tenure academic
or do you think you can do the kinds of
thing you're talking about and not
compromise your chances of getting
tenure yeah so people ask me that
something so when Hennessy and I did the
rist stuff which at the time was hugely
controversial if you think deep neural
networks are
controversial they have the people PE uh
a faculty member of in other institution
wrote a a hit piece on me personally
Dave Patterson's a bad person about and
we were talking about instruction set
design you know so you then at but at
the time you know Hennessy and I were
saying well uh digital equipment one of
the leading computer manufacturers in
the world had a pretty stupid design you
know so yeah so we uh you know we did we
didn't worry about that also you have to
believe in what you're doing I just
can't give the advice to do something
that uh you don't believe in uh and work
on that because when in fact when I've
visited universities and I've seen that
it's assistant professor telling me well
I don't really like what I'm working on
but this is what I have to do to get
tenure and then I go talk to the
chairman and this guy's just doing
incremental stuff he's never going to
get tenure right there's that Gap there
uh I you know is when you're larvel you
need to make sure you publish you know
you need to go around and give talks and
stuff like that but I I think you gotta
do projects you believe
in otherwise Life's too short to work on
other things Yeah question here
um so you mentioned a couple times uh
not to be a primadonna um so it's easy
to identify other people being padas but
how do you tell if you're being a
primadonna uh are you
married my my family is really good at
pointing out my
flaws
uh well I think I think you uh I think
feedback is the one I go out of way and
way to get feedback if somebody hates my
papers I send them new papers because
they tell me tell me the honest thing to
do I would like to think if I'm acting
like a jerk that uh you know I'm pretty
sure my friends or my family would would
would tell me that I think you could ask
right I think you you can ask right gez
people are afraid to tell you something
if not but I think if you asked did I
handle that well or not uh you do
it I think some people in Academia think
that's the way you uh that's the way
people know that you're famous you've
had some success you start acting
differently and it's just bad career
advice okay other
questions so full disclosure I I went to
Brooklyn and experienced one of these
projects um so I'm I'm mean was on the
network workstation project I'm biased
toward the model uh my question is given
the success of the model why do you
think more universities haven't adopted
it I mean even though it seems like the
stuff you're saying is really obvious
it's also somewhat rare yeah I got that
exact same question at Berkeley uh I
think this time I'll be less humble you
need you need to you have to have
somebody who's willing to lead right for
some reason even though wrestling uh as
I'll tell you I wrestled in high school
and college as an individual sport I had
great wrestling coaches who realize we'd
be more successful if we bonded as a
team even though it was individual sport
so I had that kind of role model going
up and so I think some I'm good at you
know kind of organizing teams so you
have to have somebody who's willing to
do that the institution itself Berkeley
told me day one have impact they didn't
have any problem with with multiple
people working on it when you're an
assistant professor you make up rules
like I have to have only sold auor
papers otherwise they credit but you you
that's not that's not true so the
insation let us happen I think it was
helpful that you know I'm a good leader
of people but there's lots of good
leaders of people around I don't
understand why they why that doesn't
happen more it's yeah I said it seems
common sense you know it's not like I've
kept this a secret for 4 years I've been
telling people at lost institution so I
I'm not sure but we're a lunatic fringe
right we we put a group together it's a
different group with interdisciplinary
mix and match we tackle a problem we're
you know we've already visited you guys
to on the next project to get some
feedback on it I don't know why more
people don't do it you have to ask them
why don't more people you should ask
them why don't you guys act like
Berkeley I'm sure they'd love
that there's probably a nearby probably
a nearby University you
could yeah I think we have about five
more five or six more minutes okay I uh
all right with that then I I I need to
give my uh quickly give my life story
okay so uh I'm an accidental CS student
I was a math major and wrestler in high
school and college uh the end of my
junior year the math class was cancelled
I I had to take a course there was no CS
major so I just took an intro computer
science and I was hook that was it my
senior year I took every computer course
I
could uh I'm an accidental student at I
went to uccla graduate student I just
casually mentioned at the end of one of
those courses to a new PhD that boy i'
sure rather do this than work in a
factory to pay my away the college and
he on his own went and found me a job as
undergraduate student um while I was an
undergraduate student even though it was
near the end of my senior year that
wasn't too late to go to graduate school
I asked my wife about Master's Degree
she said sure it's only four or five
quarters and then when I got into the
office everybody else in my office was
getting a PhD so I thought maybe I
should get a PhD so I decided to do that
uh we lived on a research assistant
salaries my wife and two kids and I we
were at you know poverty level at that
time and then the project ended I lost
my ra ship my adviser helped get me a
job at a Aerospace company H aircraft
and then it was touch and go whether I'd
rather finished my PhD because I was
working 10 I mean 20 30 40 hours but I
did mean it I'm an accidental Berkeley
Professor my wife uh grew up in the
right next door to Berkeley and when I
was graduating on the interview tour she
says I can't help but think you're ended
up with Berkeley and I said look
Berkeley's up here 's down here I'm
graduating this is never going to happen
but she forced me as a graduate student
to call the chairman of the department
at Berkeley computer science to find out
about my application so I called this
guy
he said well Dave you're in the top 10
but not top five and at the time I'm
thinking wow that wasn't so bad so turns
out he said that to anybody who
called but but then he took my
application yeah that seems interesting
handed it to somebody visiting Southern
California we had a good conversation
they invited me back to the interview
and got a job offer I uh barely got
tenure uh the first project I already
told you about it was way too ambitious
uh I did the SA and did the rist stuff
tenure wasn't easy I was one of those
guys that was using conferences where
the whole campus used journals but us so
I was the guinea pig uh that went
through that and the risk stuff was
pretty new but I but I got it after that
things got better but I still get papers
rejected by those jerks on the program
committee and so what have I learned
what works for me uh uh for me it was
maximizing personal happiness versus
personal wealth that's always been my
guideline believe in this country you
think wealth is happiness there's
there's unhappy billionaires right in
this world they're not they're not the
same thing um family first especially in
that kind of job you know people ask you
do things your family can go down the
list I made my family first so I did we
had my son wife and I had two sons so I
did Indian guides I I was the CB scout
leader I was the soccer coach when there
were field trips out there so when my
rebellious teenage boy grew up ah you
were never there and I said Indian
guides CB
Scouts so I went down the list and he
said oh okay maybe
uh passion courage and optimism you
might be able to tell I'm a a passionate
guy I have to believe the thing I'm
doing is uh G to possibly change the
world my optimism story goes back to uh
high school I'm dating started dating
this girl who was dating older guys who
had Corvettes and stuff like that uh
nevertheless after a couple dates I
asked her if she would go steady with me
as you say at the time she' just been
dating older guys and didn't know what
to say she says well I don't know how to
say no so me being an optimist and a
logical person not a no as a yes so I
said great and I hugged her and she said
you know uh you know I'll let this guy
down later but we've been married 48
years now so so I think that's okay um
and then yeah I think uh we swing for
the fences right that's that thing uh
now another thing this is a saying that
a colleague told me that's actually a
couple hundred years old friends come
and go but enemies accumulate uh so this
kind of ironically the physical courage
that comes with wrestling has to me been
intellectual courage so when I was
president of ACM the person in charge of
darer was cutting back on academic
funding so I decided to take him on with
my friend at lazasa in Washington and we
tried to get people from other
universities to join us but they were
afraid this guy would be vengeful and
cut him off I think with good reason but
so it was just us taking him on with
editorials and Science magazine stuff so
this guy did was not a fan of us now but
we hadn't quite realized this is
unintentional but the other saying is
the enemy of my enemy is my friend so we
made a lot of
friends but keep that in mind uh winning
is a team versus IND individual I in My
DNA I believe a team of you know average
people can work together and beat
Superstars uh and then uh I've already
quoted Fred Brooks about that line uh
seek out honest feedback and learn from
it it's easy to avoid feedback but
that's you get
better uh the one warning sign I can
pass on from my 40 years the always
dangerous is when somebody thinks they
the smartest person in the room there's
a person in my field who thinks he's the
smartest person in the room and
everybody hates that guy there was a
president of a university who thought it
smartest that person was fired for doing
a lousy job uh the people who founded
Enron uh thought they were the smartest
people in the room they went to prison
and and I I even have a relative who
thought he was the smartest person in
the room and he's a convicted felon so
the one so why would that be why would
this person they're probably smart if
they think they're the smartest why
would it be such a bad sign I think it's
that they don't want feedback from
anybody if you're the smartest person in
the room you don't need to talk to
anybody about your ideas so I think but
anyways run away if you find somebody
like that uh this uh thing happened to
me it was like God spoke in my ear one
morning and it I remember waking up you
know and it was it's not how many
projects you start it's how many you
finish it was like in my head like
somebody was telling me what to do so
that's ever since that that's what I've
done so what I do is one big project at
a time I do other things but there's one
big thing at a time so when Hennessy and
I were doing our textbook that was the
big thing that I did that year when I
was president of ACM I took a sabatical
so that was the one big thing I did
there that year and so it turns out if
you do one big thing a year over 30
years you can get a lot things done but
a lot of academics particularly will
work on a thousand things at once and
not finish very many of them and then
uh and then have fun you know to be
successful you do have to work hard you
know our long lost uh colleague Jim Gray
even in his 60s he do one all nighter a
month so you have to work hard to be
successful but you have to have fun uh
you know as far as we know you only get
one chance of this and if you get to the
end without having any fun you've wasted
a lot of opportunities I can put up a
lot of stuff as as long as I play soccer
every Sunday I I can have a good time so
that's my advice thanks very much
[Applause]