Today I want to tell you three stories
from my life. That's it. No big deal,
just three stories.
[Music]
The first story is about connecting the
dots.
I dropped out of Reed College after the
first 6 months, but then stayed around
as a dropin for another 18 months or so
before I really quit.
So why' I drop out?
It started before I was born.
My biological mother was a young unwed
graduate student and she decided to put
me up for adoption.
She felt very strongly that I should be
adopted by college graduates. So
everything was all set for me to be
adopted at birth by a lawyer and his
wife.
Except that when I popped out, they
decided at the last minute that they
really wanted a girl.
So, my parents, who were on a waiting
list, got a call in the middle of the
night asking, "We've got an unexpected
baby boy. Do you want him?" They said,
"Of course."
My biological mother found out later
that my mother had never graduated from
college and that my father had never
graduated from high school. She refused
to sign the final adoption papers.
She only relented a few months later
when my parents promised that I would go
to college. This was the start in my
life.
And 17 years later, I did go to college.
But I naively chose a college that was
almost as expensive as Stanford.
And all of my workingclass parents
savings were being spent on my college
tuition. After 6 months, I couldn't see
the value in it. I had no idea what I
wanted to do with my life and no idea
how college was going to help me figure
it out. And here I was spending all the
money my parents had saved their entire
life.
So I decided to drop out and trust that
it would all work out okay. It was
pretty scary at the time, but looking
back, it was one of the best decisions I
ever made.
The minute I dropped out, I could stop
taking the required classes that didn't
interest me and begin dropping in on the
ones that looked far more interesting.
It wasn't all romantic. I didn't have a
dorm room, so I slept on the floor and
friends rooms. I returned Coke bottles
for the 5-cent deposits to buy food
with, and I would walk the seven miles
across town every Sunday night to get
one good meal a week at the Hari Krishna
Temple. I loved it. And much of what I
stumbled into by following my curiosity
and intuition turned out to be priceless
later on. Let me give you one example.
Reed College at that time offered
perhaps the best calligraphy instruction
in the country. Throughout the campus,
every poster, every label on every
drawer was beautifully
handcalliggraphed.
Because I had dropped out and didn't
have to take the normal classes, I
decided to take a calligraphy class to
learn how to do this. I learned about
serif and sans serif type faces, about
varying the amount of space between
different letter combinations, about
what makes great typography great.
It was beautiful, historical,
artistically subtle in a way that
science can't capture. And I found it
fascinating.
None of this had even a hope of any
practical application in my life.
But 10 years later when we were
designing the first Macintosh computer,
it all came back to me and we designed
it all into the Mac. It was the first
computer with beautiful typography. If I
had never dropped in on that single
course in college, the Mac would have
never had multiple type faces or
proportionally spaced fonts. And since
Windows just copied the Mac, it's likely
that no personal computer would have
them.
If I had never dropped out, I would have
never dropped in on that calligraphy
class, and personal computers might not
have the wonderful typography that they
do. Of course, it was impossible to
connect the dots looking forward when I
was in college, but it was very, very
clear looking backwards 10 years later.
Again, you can't connect the dots
looking forward. You can only connect
them looking backwards. So, you have to
trust that the dots will somehow connect
in your future. You have to trust in
something. Your gut, destiny, life,
karma, whatever. Because believing that
the dots will connect down the road will
give you the confidence to follow your
heart even when it leads you off the
well-worn path. And that will make all
the difference.
[Music]
My second story is about love and loss.
I was lucky. I found what I love to do
early in life. W and I started Apple in
my parents' garage when I was 20. We
worked hard and in 10 years, Apple had
grown from just the two of us in a
garage into a two billion dollar company
with over 4,000 employees. We just
released our finest creation, the
Macintosh, a year earlier, and I just
turned 30.
And then I got fired.
How can you get fired from a company you
started?
Well, as Apple grew, we hired someone
who I thought was very talented to run
the company with me. And for the first
year or so, things went well. But then
our visions of the future began to
diverge. And eventually, we had a
falling out. When we did, our board of
directors sided with him. And so, at 30,
I was out and very publicly out. What
had been the focus of my entire adult
life was gone. And it was devastating.
I really didn't know what to do for a
few months. I felt that I had let the
previous generation of entrepreneurs
down, that I had dropped the baton as it
was being passed to me. I met with David
Packard and Bob and tried to apologize
for screwing up so badly. I was a very
public failure and I even thought about
running away from the valley. But
something slowly began to dawn on me. I
still loved what I did.
The turn of events at Apple had not
changed that one bit. I'd been rejected,
but I was still in love. And so, I
decided to start over.
I didn't see it then, but it turned out
that getting fired from Apple was the
best thing that could have ever happened
to me. The heaviness of being successful
was replaced by the lightness of being a
beginner again, less sure about
everything. It freed me to enter one of
the most creative periods of my life.
During the next 5 years, I started a
company named Next, another company
named Pixar, and fell in love with an
amazing woman who would become my wife.
Pixar went on to create the world's
first computer animated feature film,
Toy Story, and is now the most
successful animation studio in the
world.
In a remarkable turn of events, Apple
bought Next and I returned to Apple. And
the technology we developed at Next is
at the heart of Apple's current
renaissance. and Loren and I have a
wonderful family together.
I'm pretty sure none of this would have
happened if I hadn't been fired from
Apple. It was awful tasting medicine,
but I guess the patient needed it.
Sometime life Sometimes life's going to
hit you in the head with a brick. Don't
lose faith. I'm convinced that the only
thing that kept me going was that I
loved what I did. You've got to find
what you love. And that is as true for
work as it is for your lovers. Your work
is going to fill a large part of your
life. And the only way to be truly
satisfied is to do what you believe is
great work. And the only way to do great
work is to love what you do. If you
haven't found it yet, keep looking and
don't settle. As with all matters of the
heart, you'll know when you find it. And
like any great relationship, it just
gets better and better as the years roll
on. So keep looking. Don't settle.
My third story is about death.
When I was 17, I read a quote that went
something like, "If you live each day as
if it was your last, someday you'll most
certainly be right."
It made an impression on me. And since
then, for the past 33 years, I've looked
in the mirror every morning and asked
myself, if today were the last day of my
life, would I want to do what I am about
to do today? And whenever the answer has
been no for too many days in a row, I
know I need to change something.
Remembering that I'll be dead soon is
the most important tool I've ever
encountered to help me make the big
choices in life. Because almost
everything, all external expectations,
all pride, all fear of embarrassment or
failure, these things just fall away in
the face of death, leaving only what is
truly important. Remembering that you
are going to die is the best way I know
to avoid the trap of thinking you have
something to lose. You are already
naked. There is no reason not to follow
your heart.
No one wants to die. Even people who
want to go to heaven don't want to die
to get there. And yet death is the
destination we all share. No one has
ever escaped it. And that is as it
should be because death is very likely
the single best invention of life. It's
life's change agent. It clears out the
old to make way for the new. Right now,
the new is you. But someday, not too
long from now, you will gradually become
the old and be cleared away. Sorry to be
so dramatic, but it's quite true.
Your time is limited, so don't waste it
living someone else's life. Don't be
trapped by dogma, which is living with
the results of other people's thinking.
Don't let the noise of others opinions
drown out your own inner voice. And most
important, have the courage to follow
your heart and intuition. They somehow
already know what you truly want to
become. Everything else is secondary.
Stay hungry. Stay foolish.